<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Advice to a son. The second part. By Francis Osborn.</title>
            <title>Advice to a son. Part 2</title>
            <author>Osborne, Francis, 1593-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 229KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 103 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90198</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861398</idno>
  <idno type="VID">113531</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240870990</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing O514</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1887_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200733</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861398</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99861398e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90198)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113531)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 235:E1887[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Advice to a son. The second part. By Francis Osborn.</title>
                  <title>Advice to a son. Part 2</title>
                  <author>Osborne, Francis, 1593-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 189, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Robinson in Oxford,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an index.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Young men --  Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113531:1"/>
            <p>ADVICE TO A SON. <hi>The Second Part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY FRANCIS OSBORN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Robinson</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113531:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113531:2"/>
            <head>The STATIONER To The READER, Concerning this <hi>Second Part</hi> of <hi>Advice to a Son.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur Author,</hi> from whom I formerly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented you with <hi>a Rope of smaller Pearls,</hi> viz. <hi>His Adviso's thredded in a more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent and exact method,</hi> doth now offer these <hi>Bigger</hi> ones to your
<pb facs="tcp:113531:3"/> acceptance <hi>single</hi> and <hi>loose;</hi> which as they are in <hi>magnitude,</hi> so may you not unpossibly <hi>rate</hi> them at <hi>a like proportionable value.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of <hi>Confusion,</hi> you know, is taken as a Symbol of <hi>Greatnesse:</hi> But I shall onely, in the <hi>Authors</hi> vindication, pre-acquaint you, That a Piece of this nature will not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be of the lesse <hi>solid advantage</hi> unto <hi>you,</hi> who may begin and leave off where you please: <hi>These</hi> being, in all hands, like <hi>Cards,</hi> more <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull,</hi> if not <hi>usefull, shuffled,</hi> then in <hi>suits;</hi> through which all sorts may be tempted to <hi>read them over,</hi> and (so) not improbably gain a <hi>knowledge</hi> they would never have sought for, but upon such an omissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: wherefore whether you consider the whole <hi>Pack,</hi> or do but <hi>draw here and there,</hi> you shall be a <hi>Winner.</hi> And <hi>the Author himselfe</hi> may have the <hi>more</hi> time to employ upon
<pb facs="tcp:113531:3"/>
               <hi>somewhat else</hi> in order to <hi>your service,</hi> being freed from the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of any <hi>nicer sorting these Aphorismes;</hi> which, really consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, is but the <hi>Pedantick part</hi> of the <hi>Writer,</hi> and of <hi>most use</hi> where there is <hi>least intrinsick worth</hi> in a <hi>Book</hi> to commend it selfe: The <hi>speciousnesse</hi> of the <hi>Form</hi> not sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome betraying the <hi>Readers judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to the <hi>swallowing</hi> such <hi>sordid</hi> and <hi>refuse Matter,</hi> as would be found but a <hi>gilded Doggs — if taken in pieces and throughly examined.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113531:4"/>
            <head>To my dear Brother <hi>William Draper</hi> Esq; of <hi>Netherworton</hi> in <hi>Oxfordshire.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce it is become a generall <hi>custome</hi> to affix before <hi>Bookes</hi> the <hi>names</hi> of the <hi>Authors best friends;</hi> I could not without cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in question so manifest a truth as your <hi>desert,</hi> and running the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of being esteemed ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full my selfe, but present you with <hi>what followes:</hi> for which (however it fares) I shall descend no lower in my desires, then that <hi>your name</hi> may remain as perpetuall a <hi>monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to my <hi>merit,</hi> as I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent it will prove of your <hi>goodnesse,</hi> which can never die or be out of credit: whereas <hi>Bookes</hi> are during one Age <hi>neatly bound</hi> and <hi>choicely preserved,</hi> and the next, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the <hi>basest</hi> of <hi>imployments.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:113531:4"/> Nor had I ever exposed my self to the danger of a present censure, no lesse then a future contempt, but that I gain by <hi>writing a diversion from discontent,</hi> the highest felicity my fortune ever gave me leave yet to injoy: who, notwithstanding the <hi>cold commendation Authors</hi> find during their <hi>lives,</hi> shall venture so far on the constancy of my owne <hi>Fortune,</hi> (which some are pleased to call <hi>desert</hi>) and the worlds judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as to peep abroad again up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my single security, without so much as desiring <hi>your protection,</hi> though a frequent Petition in such like <hi>Epistles,</hi> or borrowing <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations</hi> from my <hi>Acquaintance,</hi> more ready to lend me their good word, then I was ever yet able to deserve it, which doth not seldome betray the <hi>Reader</hi> into the purchase of an <hi>ill Book;</hi> or at best, gratifies his expectation no more, then a
<pb facs="tcp:113531:5"/> base and rotten <hi>Inne</hi> can a <hi>Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> because <hi>prefaced</hi> by a gawdy <hi>sign-post. All I beg,</hi> is, that in case it comes short of <hi>former ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plause,</hi> you would consider <hi>me,</hi> not your <hi>self,</hi> as the party abused. And not weigh <hi>your acceptance</hi> or <hi>my will to serve you</hi> at the common Beam, but by the Standard of your <hi>love,</hi> in which you have so far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded those of my own <hi>blood,</hi> as I cannot but acknowledge you, and subscribe my self</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your most affectionate Brother, <hi>FR. OSBORN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113531:5"/>
            <head>To the READERS.</head>
            <p>DId all your <hi>Heads</hi> owne a like <hi>Mode</hi> and <hi>Figure,</hi> they could not but be fitted with <hi>something</hi> here might give the <hi>Buyer</hi> satisfaction for the price of the Book: but you are found in the generality, so contrary to the <hi>Camelion</hi> (a true Emblem of <hi>Hypocrisie, Levity,</hi> and <hi>Sophisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi>) as not to tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>colour</hi> for what you judge, from the tincture of <hi>Sense</hi> and <hi>Reason,</hi> but the <hi>pied</hi> and <hi>contaminated constructions</hi> fuming from brains suborned out of <hi>Interest,</hi> or a contrary practice to condemn of <hi>Errour, Ignorance,</hi> or <hi>Irreligion,</hi> all things though never so modest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proposed, that suit not with their
<pb facs="tcp:113531:6"/>
               <hi>breeding,</hi> or fall not within the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row circle of their <hi>understanding.</hi> An unsociable Lunacy that lies as far below my notice, as Fortune, which hath already advanced me (maugre such contrary indeavours) in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of sublimer Spirits, not onely beyond an ordinary <hi>esteem, but the highest I could ever be tempted</hi> to carry of my self. Wherefore though I have formerly numbred it amongst the lowest impertinencies, to fore-stall a <hi>Readers acceptance</hi> by any other courtship then the choicest <hi>indeavour</hi> to give him plenary <hi>satisfaction:</hi> yet I cannot think it suitable with <hi>gratitude</hi> to pass <hi>unregarded</hi> so much as hath already been shewn; or to doubt of the like in future: not to be done without calling in question the <hi>constancy,</hi> if not the <hi>Judgement</hi> of a <hi>considerable part of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And from hence, and no <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of my own, I do implore this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,
<pb facs="tcp:113531:6"/> that in case any have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or may hereafter be led into <hi>scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall</hi> through a <hi>sinister construction</hi> of what I have <hi>written,</hi> as dissonant from the <hi>Church of England</hi> (though a question I find, if relating to any it is rather to others conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, then mine own) you would excuse, or pass it over as an accidental <hi>Lapse,</hi> or, which I hope is truer, a meer <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stake,</hi> rather arising from a too high presumption on the <hi>Readers charity,</hi> then any real defect in mine own; who ever thought it a <hi>lesse impiety to limit reason, then Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If these <hi>Aphorismes</hi> (which I protest I picked out of <hi>wast pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> long since thrown by) appeare unsuitable to the <hi>times</hi> (perhaps sooner led through <hi>Enthusiasmes,</hi> then <hi>Theoremes</hi>) I own not a <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> bold enough to deny it. Nor did I intend that <hi>my Name</hi> or <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> should have ever become the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
<pb facs="tcp:113531:7"/> of Discourse,</hi> but that I found it unpossible <hi>to conceal it:</hi> The <hi>hope</hi> of <hi>which,</hi> and not <hi>ostentation</hi> drew me first to the <hi>Presse;</hi> as <hi>want</hi> of a more <hi>profitable imployment</hi> tempts me, being made bold through <hi>custome,</hi> to feed it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Francis Osborn.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113531:7"/>
            <head>ADVICE TO A SON. THE SECOND PART.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough it may without question be reckoned amongst <hi>Solomons Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Places</hi> of <hi>Vanity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eme.</note> yet nothing in this world appeares more <hi>Naturall</hi> or affects <hi>Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> with greater <hi>delight,</hi> then <hi>the hope men have their</hi> names <hi>may extend towards eternity:</hi> the essentiall <hi>cause</hi> of the most, if not all the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evill</hi> we find done, by pious <hi>Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> or destructive <hi>Tyrants;</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever the <hi>first</hi> may pretend in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to <hi>Religion,</hi> or the <hi>Latter</hi> suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in reference to <hi>Policy.</hi> The <hi>propagation of Fame,</hi> though con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113531:8"/>
                  <hi>a flatulent Humor,</hi> being hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be found absent from <hi>Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> or any other <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,</hi> to <hi>martyrdome</hi> it selfe. <hi>Glory</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the most <hi>acceptable</hi> thing we can <hi>injoy here,</hi> or <hi>hope for hereafter;</hi> the <hi>ayme</hi> both of the <hi>Covetous</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall,</hi> the <hi>Valiant</hi> and <hi>Coward;</hi> the one seeking to gain it through the <hi>exposing,</hi> the other by a more wary <hi>preservation</hi> of his <hi>Life</hi> &amp; Estate: <hi>all running</hi> through <hi>contrary wayes,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the gaudy <hi>ball</hi> of <hi>Fame:</hi> which though every one desires to find his <hi>name</hi> ingraven upon; yet none <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reach</hi> the <hi>records</hi> of <hi>paper, writing</hi> being the most <hi>approved recipe,</hi> yet <hi>discovered</hi> against <hi>consuming Oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> which infests the <hi>actions</hi> of the <hi>best</hi> of Princes, and benights those of the <hi>worst;</hi> who doe not seldome <hi>owe</hi> their <hi>repute</hi> to strangers. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> since there cannot be a more <hi>innocent</hi> and <hi>probable</hi> way to <hi>dilate</hi> a <hi>remembrance</hi> beyond the <hi>bankes</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113531:8"/> of <hi>Forgetfulnesse,</hi> then <hi>Books;</hi> why may not I (indebted to none, but my own deare-bought <hi>experience</hi>) be allowed the <hi>Vanity</hi> (if capable of such a title) to <hi>affix</hi> my <hi>name</hi> (since unable to build it a more lasting <hi>Monument</hi>) before <hi>these papers?</hi> where it may live if <hi>rescued</hi> out of the <hi>over-officious</hi> and <hi>strict</hi> hands of <hi>Contemporaries,</hi> the most <hi>severe censurers</hi> of the <hi>writings</hi> of the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Age,</hi> who in the absence of other <hi>juster pretences,</hi> will <hi>rather</hi> (then want matter for <hi>Reproofe</hi>) with the <hi>Maligners</hi> of the <hi>Prophet Daniel,</hi> pick something to <hi>carpe</hi> at, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to his <hi>God</hi> or the <hi>Magistracy:</hi> Though none are <hi>lesse busy</hi> in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigning the <hi>Lapses of power,</hi> or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine <hi>more obedient</hi> to the <hi>yoke</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> then such as know there can be no <hi>safety</hi> or <hi>propriety</hi> without it. Yet many <hi>halfe-witted men,</hi> presuming on the single war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of their owne <hi>purblind Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113531:9"/> do not onely overstride the Opinion of the <hi>Major part</hi> for <hi>num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> and <hi>weight,</hi> but the dictates of their owne <hi>Conscience;</hi> who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but <hi>Know,</hi> if they have any <hi>knowledge</hi> at all, That the <hi>wisdome,</hi> to which <hi>Solomon perswades</hi> no less then <hi>adornes</hi> with so many <hi>Divine epithetes,</hi> voting it the <hi>companion of the Almighty, artificer of nature, And without whose assistance nothing ever was, or is, of all that hath been made. The director of Angells in the preservation of Man,</hi> and <hi>the Tutor of man to all the understanding a Creature is able to comprehend in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to its maker,</hi> is thereby <hi>blasphemed</hi> in her <hi>children,</hi> no lesse then her <hi>King reproached;</hi> as if the <hi>followers</hi> of the <hi>pathes</hi> to <hi>Heaven</hi> could be <hi>leaders</hi> to <hi>Hell,</hi> or not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Heires</hi> of the rich <hi>Donative</hi> our blessed <hi>Saviour</hi> gives to all shall <hi>knock</hi> and <hi>seek</hi> at the <hi>gates</hi> of <hi>eternall knowledge;</hi> where no voice is <hi>intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:113531:9"/> but that of <hi>wisdome,</hi> the <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Nor did I ever yet meete the owner of so <hi>impudent</hi> a <hi>presumption,</hi> amongst all the <hi>recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of reason,</hi> as durst venture our dull and <hi>callous knowledge</hi> against the <hi>activity</hi> of an <hi>eagle-winged Faith:</hi> but do confesse a like claudication in their <hi>understandings,</hi> as <hi>Jacob</hi> found in his <hi>legg,</hi> after a <hi>wrestling with his maker.</hi> Yet since <hi>Saint Paul</hi> drawes the <hi>Bill</hi> of our <hi>Indicte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> out of the <hi>Book of Gods uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall goodnesse</hi> (to none legible, but through the light of <hi>Reason</hi>) it cannot but afford cause to magnify <hi>the eternall mercy</hi> towards <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi> in giving them <hi>Faith</hi> to regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late their <hi>workes,</hi> and support their <hi>wisdome,</hi> without which it becomes <hi>foolishnesse to God;</hi> wherefore in no other sense capable of the name of <hi>Knowledge.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113531:10"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">To preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, no prudence.</note>2. <hi>Neglect</hi> or <hi>dissemble</hi> the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of an <hi>Injury,</hi> till <hi>Time</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure you out a competent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of <hi>Charity</hi> to <hi>forgive,</hi> or so much <hi>power</hi> as may <hi>requite</hi> or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne</hi> it: Lest you convert into a <hi>Habit</hi> or irreconcileable <hi>Enmity,</hi> such <hi>Words</hi> or <hi>Actions</hi> as might not unpossible <hi>at first,</hi> result from no more bitter a Root then <hi>Chance</hi> or <hi>Mistake</hi> in you both. Wherefore <hi>no prudence</hi> to put <hi>the worst Constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> on <hi>all you heare or see,</hi> As such peevish and <hi>Melancholy Constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> do, who like <hi>Glasses</hi> retaine in their <hi>Fancies,</hi> as meerly relating to themselves, the <hi>Reflections</hi> of all things passe in their <hi>presence.</hi> For since the <hi>Eyes, Tongues</hi> and <hi>Lookes</hi> are the <hi>Windowes</hi> and <hi>Doores</hi> no less then <hi>Interpreters</hi> of the <hi>Hearts of men,</hi> and so the <hi>businesse</hi> of <hi>wisdome,</hi> to keep every thing from <hi>breaking out, that may be safer hid than re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed:</hi> it implies a like <hi>caution</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113531:10"/> ought to be had in <hi>reference</hi> to That is suffered to <hi>enter.</hi> Nor doth the want of a through inspection in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this, seldome spoile the Affaires of <hi>Princes,</hi> no lesse than meaner men's; who by measuring <hi>the persons will</hi> to <hi>advance</hi> or <hi>depresse</hi> their <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs,</hi> according to such <hi>hopes</hi> and <hi>fears</hi> as they calculate proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their own former desert or inconsiderate Opinion of the party, marre their Market, not onely through a <hi>too great confidence</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive at need all the <hi>friendship</hi> they have <hi>dearly payed for,</hi> but an <hi>over-jealousy</hi> of ill from such as they look upon in their apprehensions as <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obliged.</hi> The <hi>Exchange</hi> of <hi>Courtesies</hi> or <hi>Injuries,</hi> running <hi>high</hi> or <hi>low,</hi> not according to an exact proportion of <hi>Equity,</hi> but the value tis rated at in the <hi>esteem of the receiver.</hi> Thus the <hi>Old Earle of Essex,</hi> by placing a greater confidence in the <hi>Citizens of London,</hi> where he <hi>spent</hi> his <hi>Revenue,</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:113531:11"/> then in <hi>Wales,</hi> from whence he <hi>recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> it, <hi>Denudated</hi> himself of the most probable <hi>protection</hi> the <hi>extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> of his bad <hi>Fortune</hi> had left him. His <hi>Tenants</hi> and <hi>Friends</hi> being more likely to have proved <hi>cordiall</hi> at a <hi>distance</hi> from the <hi>Court,</hi> than those found to gather their <hi>lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> under the <hi>shadow</hi> of it; And so more probable to increase, than raise a power first in his favour. Which maturely weighed, proves <hi>the study of Friends,</hi> and <hi>Enemies the most po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique and usefull imployment.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">No enemy so contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, as to be despised.</note>3. <hi>Despise</hi> no <hi>Enemy,</hi> especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at <hi>Court:</hi> For where <hi>Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy</hi> holds the <hi>Scales,</hi> a small <hi>drachm</hi> of <hi>Detraction</hi> will turne the <hi>Beame.</hi> Mens <hi>Lives</hi> no lesse then <hi>Fortunes</hi> being so <hi>unsteady,</hi> as they lie obnoxious to <hi>blasting</hi> by the breath of far meaner persons then themselves; who making use of all advantages do not rarely bring grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113531:11"/>
                  <hi>Strength, Wisdome,</hi> and <hi>Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> then their own to <hi>destruction;</hi> So as the world hath been abused through an often repeated <hi>Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> if a <hi>fool of State</hi> did not helpe to <hi>anticipate</hi> the <hi>Death</hi> of a hopefull <hi>Prince.</hi> And if the indeavors of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice</hi> and <hi>Revenge</hi> be thus <hi>prevalent</hi> in a <hi>Court,</hi> where <hi>Civility</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> pretend at least to command, How prejudiciall must the neglect of this caution appear in the <hi>Field</hi> where nothing but <hi>Passion</hi> is obeyed, and all <hi>advantages</hi> conducing to <hi>safety,</hi> allowed in <hi>Prudence,</hi> if not <hi>Honour?</hi> And where <hi>Fortune</hi> to <hi>exercise</hi> the <hi>dominion</hi> she usurps over <hi>Strength,</hi> and <hi>Probability,</hi> suffered a <hi>Dwarfe</hi> not long since to kill a <hi>Man.</hi> This makes me admire the <hi>Valor</hi> more then <hi>discretion</hi> of <hi>an acquaintance</hi> of mine, That met an <hi>armed enemy</hi> in a formal and premeditated <hi>Duel</hi> with a <hi>wooden Dagger</hi> &amp; a <hi>rebated Rapier.</hi> I confess this <hi>gallant Soul</hi> did worst
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113531:12"/> him; which appeared <hi>lesse</hi> because no more then his <hi>contempt</hi> ingaged him to. But if <hi>Chance</hi> (the Lady of such events) had turned her face the <hi>other way,</hi> his <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>prudence,</hi> if not <hi>Life (seldome ransomed, if at the mercy of a Coward)</hi> had been lost in the <hi>Indiscretion</hi> of the <hi>action:</hi> The <hi>Generality</hi> taking no other <hi>prospect</hi> of things then through the <hi>Event:</hi> and under this <hi>Topick</hi> may be <hi>inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> such as <hi>return a disarmed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my his Sword,</hi> with a number of <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> more incident to a <hi>Romantique valour.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">To contend with inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours brings discredit.</note>4. <hi>Have peace with all men,</hi> is as <hi>wholsome</hi> an <hi>Aphorisme</hi> in <hi>Policy</hi> as <hi>Divinity.</hi> But being uncapable of so strict an <hi>Observati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> as in <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Prudence</hi> it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves, <hi>Let me advise you</hi> to shun, or break off all <hi>Contests</hi> with much inferior persons to your self. And because <hi>Example</hi> re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ives a more
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113531:12"/> lively <hi>tincture</hi> from <hi>Memory,</hi> then <hi>Precept,</hi> I shall instance it as a blot in the greatest <hi>Rochet</hi> that did in my time appear in the <hi>Court of England,</hi> or <hi>indeed</hi> any I ever heard of since the <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>formation:</hi> who managed a <hi>Quarrel</hi> with <hi>Archy the Kings Fool,</hi> &amp; by <hi>indeavouring</hi> to explode him the <hi>Court,</hi> rendred him at last so <hi>considerable,</hi> by calling the <hi>Prelats Enemies</hi> (which were not a few) to his <hi>rescue,</hi> as the fellow was not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly able to continue the dispute for divers years, but received such in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements from standers by, as he hath oft, in my hearing, belched in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> such <hi>miscarriages</hi> as he was really guilty of, and might, but for this <hi>foul-mouth'd Scot,</hi> have been forgotten: Adding such other <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches</hi> of his own, as <hi>the dignity of his calling</hi> and <hi>greatnesse of his parts</hi> could not in <hi>Reason</hi> or <hi>Manners</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, Though so far hoodwink'd with <hi>Passion,</hi> as not to discerne that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113531:13"/> all the <hi>Fool</hi> did was but a Symptom of the <hi>strong</hi> and <hi>inveterate Distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> raised long before in the <hi>Hearts</hi> of his <hi>countrymen</hi> against <hi>the calling of Bishops:</hi> Out of whose former <hi>ruins</hi> the major part of the <hi>Scottish Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> had feathered, if not built their <hi>Nests.</hi> Nor did this too <hi>low-placed Anger</hi> lead him into a lesse <hi>absur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity,</hi> then an indeavor to bring him into the <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> till the <hi>Lord Coventry</hi> had, by acquainting him with <hi>the priviledge of a Fool,</hi> shown <hi>the ridiculousnesse of the attempt:</hi> yet not satisfied, he, through the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the <hi>Queen,</hi> got him at last discharged the <hi>Court;</hi> whither he brought after the same mind under a <hi>Cloak,</hi> he had before born in his <hi>Fools Coate. Nor</hi> is it more wisdome for any, <hi>especially Kings,</hi> to drive <hi>base people</hi> into the drak corners of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaire,</hi> where they do not only lose the sense of their own <hi>felicity,</hi> in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming <hi>Instrumentall to the Malice
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113531:13"/> and Ambition of others,</hi> but <hi>all duty</hi> and naturall respect to <hi>Friends, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and <hi>Governours.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <p>5.<note place="margin">A friend necessary to a Courtier.</note>
                  <hi>A true Friend</hi> becomes the <hi>fortune</hi> of every <hi>Profession,</hi> but is the most necessary <hi>Uten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sil</hi> I did ever observe belonging to a person at <hi>Court:</hi> where eyes are so <hi>seeled up</hi> and <hi>covered</hi> with <hi>preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, envy,</hi> &amp;c. as little notice is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the <hi>highest desert,</hi> till through the <hi>approbation</hi> of a <hi>stander-by</hi> they are <hi>pointed to it.</hi> The mode of <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> being, <hi>as I have often found,</hi> to rest better satisfied with <hi>others atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stations,</hi> than <hi>their own.</hi> The cause that in <hi>Palaces Merit</hi> is lesse vendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the <hi>first</hi> than <hi>second hand; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding</hi> commonly from the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty</hi> of the <hi>party,</hi> which <hi>defect</hi> none but a <hi>faithfull friend</hi> is able to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply▪ I could name a couple of <hi>Jesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> (no waies miraculous for <hi>parts,</hi> considering the forraine advantages
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113531:14"/> received from their <hi>Relations</hi> and <hi>breeding</hi>) who did by making it their businesse to <hi>cry up one the other</hi> in all <hi>companies,</hi> and upon every <hi>occasion,</hi> swell themselves to such a repute, as they became in a short time able to benight the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of a <hi>Prince</hi> in his own <hi>opinion</hi> no meane <hi>Polititian.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">To oblige a prince, or state, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous.</note>6. Though it is your <hi>duty</hi> no lesse then <hi>Honor</hi> to have <hi>deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved well</hi> of <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State:</hi> Yet it may be no <hi>unseasonable advice (considering how soone the best of Subjects have their desert expunged by envy</hi> or <hi>forgetfulnesse, after their use is over)</hi> to extend <hi>expectation</hi> beyond the present <hi>occasion:</hi> By which you may have the hope to <hi>continue</hi> your <hi>Princes▪ Favour, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly conclusive where Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ceaseth.</hi> Wherefore <hi>the well Managing of Merit</hi> is none of the weakest effects of <hi>Prudence,</hi> because
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113531:14"/> uncapable to be <hi>restrained</hi> within <hi>the compasse of any generall rules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Signall actions</hi> being not seldome so hudled up by <hi>Fortune,</hi> as they are in a short time <hi>forgotten</hi> or much <hi>l ssened</hi> by <hi>sharers</hi> and <hi>envy</hi> before the <hi>principall Operator</hi> is able to make <hi>his best market</hi> of them: To whom <hi>a brave achievement</hi> hath sometimes proved <hi>fatall; Nothing being more terrible in the eyes of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, then the Apparition of an unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded Desert;</hi> whose chiefest me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diators are <hi>Shame, Hope</hi> or <hi>Feare:</hi> wherefore he that keeps not all or one of these for his friend, may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a <hi>Reward</hi> from <hi>Heaven</hi> sooner then <hi>Earth.</hi> The old <hi>Earle of Bristol</hi> was none of the most imperfect Scholars in this Lesson; who, through a <hi>prodigious dexterity,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the <hi>Confident</hi> of <hi>two Princes,</hi> that drove on, if not contrary, divers Designes. And was <hi>at his returne</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:113531:15"/> able to appear before the <hi>English Parliament</hi> where he worsted the greatest <hi>Minion</hi> the <hi>Folly, Love,</hi> or <hi>Wisdome</hi> of any King since the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest</hi> ever bred in this <hi>Nation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Selfe praise great impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note>7. I note it as a great <hi>blemish,</hi> and so much the more deplorable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause not seldome mingled with the <hi>best parts, for a man to cry up his own Excellencies.</hi> Through which, though the <hi>simple</hi> may be led into <hi>Admiration,</hi> it produceth, from the more <hi>Judicious, Contempt</hi> and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy: Conjuring up a severer <hi>scrutiny</hi> into the parties <hi>personall Lapses</hi> and <hi>Naturall Imperfections,</hi> then <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> ought to <hi>Alarum. A modest rate</hi> put by the <hi>owner</hi> upon his peculiar <hi>desert, being the most ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall Medium</hi> to <hi>multiply fame.</hi> Though the same <hi>Aphorismes</hi> in <hi>Morality,</hi> no more then those of <hi>Physick</hi> are not alwaies found to work the <hi>same effects</hi> upon all <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plections</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:113531:15"/> and <hi>Constitutions:</hi> the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> being ordinary through <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> or a <hi>Prejudice</hi> arising from a <hi>different opinion.</hi> For let the <hi>Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> utter never so Rationall and exact a <hi>Truth, Nothing</hi> but what <hi>quadrats</hi> with the <hi>Companies respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive understandings</hi> and <hi>experience,</hi> can settle upon him the <hi>Hearers Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe:</hi> Not seldome better Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with a <hi>probable Lye,</hi> then in the serious relation of a more <hi>prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Truth.</hi> The <hi>predication</hi> of which is not onely an <hi>Incroachment</hi> upon the sole <hi>Immunity</hi> of <hi>Thrones</hi> and <hi>Pulpits,</hi> But a dangerous <hi>Intrusion</hi> upon the elements of <hi>Civility;</hi> so farre as sometimes to produce <hi>Quarrels,</hi> ever <hi>disputes:</hi> Not in Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to be looked upon, by the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter,</hi> under a modester notion then <hi>a returne of the Lye.</hi> Nor can such <hi>Improbabilities</hi> at best, passe their <hi>hearers,</hi> without the thoughts of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>slighted</hi> by the <hi>Relator;</hi> as owners
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113531:16"/> (in his Opinion) of a <hi>Credulity</hi> capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be <hi>deluded. And this mature<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly considered</hi> might hang the <hi>Lock</hi> of a greater <hi>restraint</hi> upon the <hi>Mouths</hi> of <hi>Travellers, Huntsmen, Mountebanks,</hi> &amp;c. who to render their <hi>professions</hi> of more <hi>value,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, if brought to the <hi>Candle,</hi> they might possibly appear to be, doe <hi>torture</hi> their <hi>Company</hi> with no lesse <hi>Impertinent,</hi> then <hi>Improbable Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> And if it were as farre war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by discretion, <hi>To name the persons</hi> that have <hi>smutted</hi> their <hi>fame</hi> through a <hi>Breach</hi> of this <hi>Topicke,</hi> as it is fit to <hi>avoyd</hi> the like <hi>excesse,</hi> you would blesse your self to hear the <hi>recitall</hi> of so many <hi>brave Spirits,</hi> and such whose <hi>desert</hi> is impregnable against the stormes of <hi>Time,</hi> which <hi>this quality</hi> hath, to my knowledge worsted in their <hi>repute,</hi> so far as to render them <hi>Ridiculous in Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny:</hi> of which I shall leave you this one <hi>namelesse example</hi> of a <hi>Knight,</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:113531:16"/> who using to make make <hi>Multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Glasses</hi> of what he in his long and great <hi>Travailes</hi> had <hi>Observed,</hi> professed he once conversed with a <hi>Hermite</hi> that was, in the Opinion of all men, able to commute any <hi>Metal</hi> into <hi>Gold</hi> with a <hi>stone</hi> he kep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> still hanging at his <hi>Girdle:</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked <hi>of what kind it was,</hi> and not readily <hi>Answering,</hi> the witty <hi>Lord of Saint Albans</hi> standing by, said he did verily believe, it was a <hi>whetstone,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Neither may it be <hi>happily amisse here,</hi> to disswade you from all <hi>immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate praise</hi> or <hi>dispraise</hi> of any <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> or <hi>thing</hi> your <hi>experience</hi> or <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance</hi> hath had the <hi>Fortune</hi> to <hi>cope withall;</hi> lest some in <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> out of an humor of <hi>Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> (no lesse <hi>frequent,</hi> than <hi>odious</hi> to <hi>Society</hi>) or a <hi>disaffection,</hi> should as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume the <hi>contrary Cudgell,</hi> and by that ingage you in an ungratefull <hi>dispute</hi> or a more destructive and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113531:17"/>
                  <hi>Quarrell:</hi> As befell an <hi>Earl</hi> at <hi>Greenwich,</hi> that received some prejudice in his <hi>honour</hi> from the <hi>Ma. of Ham,</hi> for crying up the <hi>Civility</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> higher than that of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> which grew at last to such <hi>terms,</hi> as might have produced worse <hi>effects,</hi> had not the <hi>Earls wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> directed him to the <hi>Throne,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">To jest with Princes not safe.</note>8. Though <hi>Kings,</hi> and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in <hi>Superlative power,</hi> when <hi>loose</hi> from <hi>serious Imployments,</hi> assume so farre the <hi>sociable humors</hi> of Humanity, as <hi>to break out</hi> into <hi>sprightfull &amp; facetious extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> with other <hi>Courtiers;</hi> yet ought not this <hi>freedom</hi> to allure them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to so <hi>high</hi> and <hi>familiar</hi> a <hi>Presumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as to <hi>retaliate</hi> the like againe: Since <hi>scorn</hi> or <hi>smart</hi> proportionates not its acceptance to the extent of this <hi>Innocency</hi> and <hi>good meaning</hi> of the Subject that first gave the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion, but the <hi>Iealousy</hi> of the Prince
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113531:17"/> that received it. Such <hi>accidents</hi> though they may passe <hi>current</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the short time of a <hi>present com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce,</hi> yet do not faile upon <hi>Rumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> and the <hi>tincture, Enemies</hi> are found to give all that may advance their <hi>profit</hi> or <hi>malice,</hi> to change the former superscription of <hi>mirth</hi> and impresse of <hi>Love,</hi> into an Inveterate <hi>hatred</hi> and thirst for <hi>Revenge.</hi> An <hi>Instance</hi> hereof appeares in <hi>William Earle of Pembroke, none of the least Obsequious Observers of the times;</hi> who naturally or rather Customari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (since the former may be lyable to question) <hi>abominating a Frogge,</hi> had one thrown into his <hi>Neck</hi> by <hi>King James:</hi> And did in requitall cause a <hi>Pigge</hi> (of an equall <hi>disgust</hi> with the same <hi>Prince</hi>) to be put un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his <hi>close stool:</hi> where though it produced no <hi>extraordinary ill effect for the present, it being as usuall</hi> a thing with <hi>his Majesty</hi> to be <hi>frighted,</hi> as &amp;c. Yet after the <hi>prank (Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:113531:18"/> enough of it self) had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scanted upon, and the worst of <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations</hi> made by some (The ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Jewes</hi> being at that time usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally given to the <hi>Scots) The King was much affected with it;</hi> and the more, because done at <hi>Wilton</hi> under the <hi>Earls own roof:</hi> It remaining alwaies a Natural or Usurped <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative in Princes,</hi> if not of all in power, to <hi>put their particular sense on the words and actions of inferior per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons.</hi> Wherefore he that relates wholly to the <hi>Honour</hi> or <hi>Friendship</hi> of his <hi>Prince,</hi> had need of more <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi> and <hi>Circumspection</hi> then doth ordinarily attend a <hi>free birth;</hi> or such as <hi>remaine galled</hi> through any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine <hi>discontent</hi> or <hi>Anxiety,</hi> which renders the Patient <hi>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chy</hi> and <hi>unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Counsell to be givē with cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>9. It is not prudence, through <hi>contrary Counsell</hi> to <hi>tamper</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much in the <hi>miscarriages</hi> of <hi>others,</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:113531:18"/> not relating to your own <hi>Interest, especially</hi> if absolutely flowne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all recovery of <hi>Prevention:</hi> For, though, like <hi>Physick,</hi> it may appeare <hi>of wholsome Consequence</hi> for the future, it remaines at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of <hi>no good savour</hi> to the <hi>Party:</hi> And renders the <hi>sight</hi> of him it is received from <hi>ungratefull.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with <hi>much caution, if at all</hi> to be administred to <hi>People</hi> of <hi>Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> who do not seldome, in stead of <hi>doubling</hi> their own <hi>circumspecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> onely place a stricter <hi>watch</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Informer,</hi> in hope <hi>to pay him</hi> in the <hi>same Coyne,</hi> never current but amongst those of <hi>choice</hi> and <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did</hi> natures: <hi>Counsell implying,</hi> in most peoples Opinions, <hi>an overpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing your own Judgement, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of others.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <p>10.<note place="margin">To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h at a mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable.</note> It is a no lesse violation of <hi>friendship,</hi> then <hi>Charity,</hi> to <hi>laugh</hi> when another by accident
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113531:19"/> falls into a <hi>Mischance;</hi> And hath proved, <hi>in my experience,</hi> the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of many <hi>Quarrells,</hi> and bred a <hi>strangenesse</hi> between persons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore very <hi>Intimate</hi> in Affection. Wherefore it ought to be refrained towards people of <hi>meane quality,</hi> lest <hi>custome</hi> should <hi>render</hi> it more difficult to abstaine from it, if the same Fortune becomes the lot of a <hi>greater man</hi> or <hi>dearer Acquaintance.</hi> As it fell out at the <hi>new Lodge</hi> by <hi>Barnet;</hi> where after a great Dinner, <hi>King James</hi> walking out, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>neglected</hi> by such as led him, stumbling at a <hi>Mole-hill,</hi> fell down, and managed his <hi>Legges</hi> after so ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous a posture as many of the company could not hold from <hi>Laughter:</hi> which his Majesty took so ill, as he called them <hi>Traytors,</hi> and protested <hi>Revenge;</hi> nor would he suffer any of them to take him up, Till Mr. <hi>John West</hi> the Keeper, at whose house and charge the <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:113531:19"/> was, came, and by <hi>a witty conceit</hi> (of which he was full) fetched them off. Swearing <hi>no good subject could refraine to rejoyce at his Majecties activity, to see him so nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as to come over and over:</hi> Now though this <hi>Buffoonery</hi> did for the present seeme to compound for the reall <hi>folly</hi> of the rest, that had seen and forgot many things the <hi>Court</hi> might have learned them; Yet <hi>the King</hi> did <hi>Remember</hi> some of them, as no well wishers to his continuance in being, but rather inclining to, &amp;c. <hi>To conclude,</hi> if it was thought man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners by our <hi>Ancestors,</hi> not to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered whilest another <hi>Sneezed,</hi> it can be no <hi>Charity</hi> if <hi>Discretion</hi> to <hi>laugh</hi> when he is likely to <hi>break his Neck.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <p>11.<note place="margin">To upbraid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral defects uncivill.</note> It becomes not <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> no more than <hi>Discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> to <hi>Upbraid</hi> others with such <hi>Imperf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctinns,</hi> as may by <hi>acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> fall to, or accompany People
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113531:20"/> from their <hi>Birth:</hi> No more in the <hi>Owners</hi> power to help, then it lyes in the <hi>Scorners</hi> ability to shield his own <hi>person</hi> or <hi>issue</hi> from falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a like <hi>Disaster: None being so precisely happy,</hi> as not sooner or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in their <hi>Bodies, Mindes, Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> or <hi>Estates,</hi> to receive some <hi>ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish</hi> if not an Ugly <hi>mulct</hi> from the hand of <hi>Fortune; to whose Injuries the best men are subject during this Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Especially with Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stardy.</note>But that which appeares the highest Injustice is <hi>the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Bastardy,</hi> in no Nation looked upon under so great a noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Reproch,</hi> as amongst the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish,</hi> Though for the most part re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compensed with the richest <hi>Indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> For if a <hi>Fault,</hi> it belongs <hi>sole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> to the <hi>Parents;</hi> wherefore the less discernable through what Organ of equity, <hi>any more than an ordinary humane contamination should attach
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113531:20"/> the Child.</hi> Since the single <hi>Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of a <hi>wife</hi> (of no great validity in other things) is the chief authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke proof we can produce for the <hi>integrity</hi> of these we esteem most <hi>Legitimate.</hi> From whence we may learne how to rate their <hi>Malice,</hi> That missing of matter considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to traduce <hi>the Reign of Q. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> take in her <hi>Birth</hi> for the <hi>Faultes</hi> (if capable to be called so) of her <hi>Father.</hi> Forgetting, no such thing as <hi>Bastardy,</hi> in relation to <hi>plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of wives</hi> and <hi>Concubines,</hi> can be allowed in Nature, without as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persing the <hi>Patriarches</hi> and <hi>People of God.</hi> Wherefore the contrary <hi>Custome</hi> cannot be of validity e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to question the <hi>Descent</hi> of a <hi>Prince,</hi> whose <hi>possession</hi> of the <hi>Crown</hi> is not only sufficient to create a <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> but what <hi>Ceremony</hi> (in all things not diametrically opposite to the apparent dictates of God) shall be imposed upon the <hi>Subject. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narches</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:113531:21"/> themselves remaining dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged and uncapable of limitation by <hi>Custome</hi> or any <hi>Law</hi> that is but meerly <hi>respective</hi> to <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Order:</hi> so as <hi>King James</hi> and his <hi>Son,</hi> though the <hi>highest indulgers</hi> of the <hi>Ecclesiasticall Canons</hi> and <hi>Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions,</hi> Have often to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge so far dispensed with the <hi>legal houres</hi> appointed for <hi>Matrimony,</hi> as to exchange them from <hi>Morning</hi> to <hi>Night:</hi> things meerly Complemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall vanishing in the presence of the <hi>supreme Magistrate.</hi> Nor was any thing in the most rigid opinion wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to her <hi>Legitimation,</hi> but a <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensation, professed by all Historians Signed, Sealed</hi> and <hi>sent</hi> into <hi>England.</hi> Now though the <hi>Pope</hi> did retract it, out of Reason of State, and dread of <hi>Charles the fifth,</hi> whose <hi>Aunt Queen Catharine was,</hi> I presume the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> under the protection of whom <hi>his Holinesse assumes the power of not erring, can in no mans
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113531:21"/> Opinion be thought to repent the approving what none but an Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Malice is able to question, the Lawfullnesse</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> being in all places left to a greater <hi>Liberty,</hi> than <hi>Subjects</hi> may in a stricter Sense be lyable to. It remaining improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to conjecture, that <hi>Henry the</hi> 8<seg rend="sup">th</seg> should Repudiate so virtuous a <hi>Lady</hi> out of a less trivial desire than the obtaining the <hi>Nations quiet,</hi> and prevent <hi>Civil warre;</hi> by leaving behind him an <hi>Heire of his body.</hi> But to lay aside such <hi>bables;</hi> onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable with <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Fooles,</hi> He had the <hi>consent</hi> of all uninte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rested <hi>Divines,</hi> beyond Seas, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a considerable number of the most <hi>Learned</hi> in his own Church; from whom there is no naturall, if Just appeale to any but God, or an impartiall <hi>Councill; a Phenix not likely to be found, till</hi> the old <hi>man of Sinne</hi> be consumed, And <hi>Our Saviour</hi> in his own Person
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113531:22"/> become <hi>Monarch of the whole Earth.</hi> Thus when the <hi>gall</hi> of <hi>Interest</hi> and <hi>Malice</hi> becoms mingled with <hi>Ink,</hi> it doth not onely blot and disfigure the beauty of <hi>Truth,</hi> but the Honor of all Authors that indeavour to maintaine it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The issues not bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the marks of their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors an ill ground of jealousie.</note>12. Some <hi>Families</hi> are noted of a <hi>propensity</hi> more to <hi>Folly, Lust, Infelicity, Stamering,</hi> &amp;c. others to <hi>Beauty, Temperance, Modesty, Probity, Hospitality,</hi> with many respective mulcts and benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies in nature. The Causes of which may be easier sought for, than found amongst the perfections and blemishes of <hi>Ancestors.</hi> Since the <hi>Belly</hi> being changed upon every <hi>discent, it remaines little probable</hi> the <hi>Burthen</hi> should retaine the same markes from any more occult qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity than <hi>Imitation.</hi> As may be gues<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed from an <hi>honorable Family,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for <hi>many Generations</hi> to <hi>Stutter,</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:113531:22"/> and another that retained <hi>a cast with their eyes:</hi> Both which may in <hi>my opinion</hi> be attributed in more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability to the effects of an <hi>ordinary Commerce than any quality inherent in their Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The longer than ordinary succession of <hi>great Lippes</hi> observed in the <hi>House of Austria</hi> cannot appeare a Miracle to any that considers they have not, for many Ages <hi>Married</hi> out of <hi>their nearst Kindered.</hi> I note this not only to guard you from <hi>Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousy,</hi> the most impertinent Devill fancy can <hi>be at any time haunted with;</hi> But to prevent falling into the common errour both of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and Moderne <hi>Philosophers,</hi> That ground <hi>Conclusions</hi> upon bare report or at best <hi>single experiments,</hi> which exposeth them to easie Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futations: Manifest in <hi>Pliny,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:113531:23"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of Crosses highest folly.</note>13. If it be the highest <hi>advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,</hi> deducible from the <hi>Study</hi> of <hi>philosophy, Calmely to beare the affronts of Fortune,</hi> how can the depth of their <hi>Indiscretion</hi> be fatho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, That, <hi>absolved from perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall causes</hi> of <hi>Discontent,</hi> extract rhe Spirit of <hi>Anxiety</hi> out of such <hi>remote accidents,</hi> as <hi>Custome,</hi> not <hi>Nature</hi> hath laid in the way of humane <hi>feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city,</hi> through which we become far more unadvised than <hi>Beasts.</hi> And amongst these may be numbred <hi>the Immoderate desire of,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">As an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate desire of, or care for po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity.</note>
                  <hi>and care for Children;</hi> in some so ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous and intemperate, as to let <hi>themselves</hi> and their <hi>families</hi> (of which they are part) to want <hi>all things</hi> for <hi>the present</hi> the (onely time we can call ours) out of hope to leave them <hi>something</hi> after their <hi>Death:</hi> which doth prove as often <hi>too much,</hi> as <hi>too little.</hi> Since through this <hi>excesse</hi> (like an over-propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Byas</hi> on a <hi>Bowle</hi>) they are
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113531:23"/> led out of all care for <hi>greater prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or becoming <hi>better</hi> than at first they were <hi>left:</hi> who quite unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the <hi>use</hi> of <hi>money,</hi> are as far to seek, how to <hi>improve,</hi> as decently to <hi>spend</hi> it. Yet, in my apprehension, no <hi>perturbation</hi> beares the marks of a more ridiculous <hi>folly,</hi> than lyes patent in an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent <hi>Jealousy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Impertinent Jealousie.</note> in relation to <hi>women;</hi> no more able to ransome their <hi>Repute</hi> out of the hands of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction,</hi> Than the <hi>Patient</hi> is to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie his <hi>Curiosity</hi> with a pleasanter <hi>Recipe</hi> than an apparent <hi>Detection.</hi> Thus, by snatching up <hi>Negative E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils,</hi> we render our selves Insensible of any <hi>positive Good:</hi> Like <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> who if dispossest or deni'd the <hi>gauds</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> will <hi>in a peevish hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor</hi> throw away <hi>their own.</hi> Nor are we seldome cast into a <hi>present trouble,</hi> out of the contemplation of <hi>Mischiefes not yet arrived: The things we feare resembling so far
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113531:24"/> those we desire, that for the most part they seem greater</hi> at a <hi>distance, than nearer hand:</hi> From whence the <hi>Mind</hi> may be Judged as crazed and Infirme as the <hi>Body,</hi> and no lesse af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with vapors. Nor are these <hi>distempers</hi> so frequent in vulgar and <hi>empty heads,</hi> as those <hi>Stuffed</hi> with <hi>Learning;</hi> A meer <hi>Drug,</hi> and in this, like <hi>Rubarbe; whose operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are farre more effectuall upon a slight infusion than taken in the Masse;</hi> not seldome observed rather to <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct</hi> than <hi>open</hi> the <hi>Organes</hi> of <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding,</hi> which ought not to be <hi>crammed</hi> faster than she is able to <hi>concoct,</hi> nor kept in a <hi>coope</hi> without taking the prospect of all worldly <hi>experience;</hi> A rude quantity of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate notions</hi> being apter to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Sayle,</hi> than <hi>Ballast:</hi> the major part of <hi>Learning</hi> appearing, like <hi>Diamonds,</hi> richer in <hi>Splendor,</hi> than use: And cannot, alone, and unassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted by the <hi>conversation</hi> of all sorts
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113531:24"/> of <hi>Professions,</hi> measure out the true and Mathematical Latitude of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>felicity,</hi> not prohibited <hi>by,</hi> though bounded <hi>within</hi> the compasse of <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son;</hi> In whose absence it is either lost in <hi>excesse,</hi> or <hi>smothered</hi> in <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> flattered</hi> into the first through <hi>Voluptuousnesse,</hi> and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the other by <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> which makes them to suspect all things <hi>pleasant,</hi> of <hi>Sinne,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the contrary is more likely to be <hi>naturall.</hi> Since at long running, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers more indulged by <hi>Policy,</hi> are found to meet at the <hi>same Market,</hi> or a worse. And to draw us <hi>with more ease</hi> into the <hi>Iron Trappes</hi> of <hi>Infelicity,</hi> and <hi>Restraint,</hi> they baite them with the Scraps of a broken <hi>hope</hi> and Childish <hi>allurement,</hi> That our <hi>Fathers</hi> were <hi>caught</hi> before us. Yet the wily <hi>Priests,</hi> quite dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of the Lamber of a <hi>Family,</hi> and all Oppression incident to a <hi>Secular life,</hi> cannot but injoy the most <hi>Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city,</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:113531:25"/> vainely sought under any but <hi>a free Condition,</hi> which all injoy so far as they are <hi>willing,</hi> or left <hi>able</hi> by others to unconcern themselves of the <hi>world:</hi> which no protection can so totally perform as that of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> in which, like a <hi>Cave</hi> or <hi>Grotto,</hi> such of the <hi>Ecclesiastickes</hi> as are any way <hi>superintendent</hi> over others, are situated under as mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate an aspect during the <hi>Sun-shine</hi> of <hi>prosperity,</hi> as the <hi>stormes</hi> of an <hi>adverse fortune;</hi> the <hi>thunders</hi> of <hi>warre</hi> (I meane <hi>till this Sulfurous age</hi>) seldome breaking out over their <hi>Cells. But now</hi> since the blood of the <hi>Saints</hi> together with their <hi>names</hi> are expunged the <hi>Gates</hi> and <hi>Doores</hi> of the <hi>Sanctuary, Good works</hi> have lost their <hi>value,</hi> &amp; nothing more in esteem than <hi>new Opinions.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>since in the absence</hi> of a prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from the <hi>Altar,</hi> nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines without able to secure us quite from the sense of <hi>Oppression,</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:113531:25"/> let us turne our indeavours towards such <hi>remedies</hi> as <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophy</hi> are found to prescribe us; And <hi>according to their advice pack up our hopes and feares into as nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a Room as we can possibly, by which we shall render the Last more portable,</hi> and <hi>the first lesse tedious.</hi> And in reference to this, all <hi>affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> beyond the degrees of a natural and compell'd <hi>Necessity,</hi> or any thing likely to dilate them, are warily to be avoided, during the <hi>best times,</hi> as contrary to <hi>felicity;</hi> and in the <hi>worst,</hi> as obstructors of the wayes to <hi>evasion,</hi> The most usefull <hi>knack</hi> belonging to the <hi>Engin</hi> of <hi>Life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <p>14. No <hi>virtues</hi> deserve to be more indulged,<note place="margin">Patience and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration most n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cessary in humane life.</note> both in our selves and others, than <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Moderation:</hi> The <hi>first</hi> being no lesse requisite to <hi>arme</hi> us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the open <hi>Hostility</hi> of <hi>Fortune,</hi> than the <hi>other</hi> to <hi>guard</hi> us from the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113531:26"/>
                  <hi>excesses</hi> that do usually accrue to such as are placed in the gaudy <hi>Pageant</hi> of her favour: and therefore kept in compasse with the greater diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, because bounded by no more forraigne or externall a <hi>check,</hi> than the party is able to give out of the strength of his own Judgement, prompted by an experience had of her <hi>uncertaine carriage,</hi> whereas <hi>ill Luck</hi> (or to speak more Christian) <hi>a seeming desertion of the benignity of providence,</hi> is rendred much the more <hi>supportable</hi> through an absolute <hi>Necessity,</hi> And so, under an <hi>unavoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable restraint</hi> rather <hi>Imposed,</hi> than voluntarily <hi>submitted to.</hi> The rarest president for <hi>Moderation</hi> I ever met with, was the last <hi>Bishop of London,</hi> who extracted by the Chimistry of this <hi>Mountebank Diety,</hi> and Alem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becked through a number of great Mutations, from one of the Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est of <hi>Vicars,</hi> to the highest of <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surers,</hi> was in none of them elated
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113531:26"/> above the <hi>Meridian</hi> of the ground he first stood on, or did <hi>debauch</hi> through his miscarriage the dignity of any <hi>place</hi> he passed through: Nor did he suffer, with <hi>a more sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine brow,</hi> the breaking of all the <hi>Glasses</hi> this pied <hi>Goddesse</hi> had blown in his favour; But did, after the <hi>Curtaines</hi> were drawne, and the <hi>Tragedy</hi> acted, without any <hi>visible reluctancy</hi> turne his eyes towards the same landscipe of <hi>Country plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, he had as it were against his will been taken from.</hi> I have (deare Son) but named him, whom I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem sit to be placed in your heart for the <hi>best paterne of Moderation</hi> I ever met with, As he might have remained for <hi>patience,</hi> Had he not been <hi>eclipsed</hi> through the <hi>far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter sufferings</hi> of a <hi>Person</hi> more <hi>Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did,</hi> and no lesse <hi>Miraculous</hi> in this virtue, as none can attest better, than this <hi>Prelate</hi> whose <hi>Patron</hi> he was.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:113531:27"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick's neglected, the ruine of great families.</note>15. I find the <hi>Oeconomickes</hi> though <hi>most</hi> useful to <hi>Being,</hi> the <hi>least</hi> esteemed with our <hi>Gallants:</hi> Looked upon by some as <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viall,</hi> by others as <hi>dishonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> and <hi>unbecomming a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sculine Imployment.</hi> Yet a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall <hi>neglect</hi> of <hi>them</hi> may be found in experience the <hi>ruin</hi> of the <hi>greatest Families</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>their</hi> more exact prosecution keeps up mens <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states</hi> in <hi>Italy;</hi> where the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> are celebrated as most generally <hi>wise,</hi> and therefore <hi>not unfitly</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed in this for <hi>an universall pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne,</hi> but where they border too near the confines of <hi>penury</hi> and <hi>base<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,</hi> most unbecomming the <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome</hi> and <hi>plenty</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> And where, <hi>in this particular</hi> (till the <hi>Sword</hi> received a <hi>Commission</hi> from God to <hi>devoure</hi> all things good and <hi>honorable</hi> in the <hi>Land</hi>) our <hi>Noble men</hi> equalled the <hi>Princes,</hi> and our <hi>King</hi> exceeded in <hi>Hospitality</hi> all the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113531:27"/>
                  <hi>Monarches</hi> in the known world: And might yet have done more, had the true Elements of <hi>Thrift</hi> bin maintained in an equall proportion, by providing all things at the <hi>best hand,</hi> and making use of <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>seasons;</hi> in which I confesse so much as purely belongs to <hi>Huswifry,</hi> ought, if not in <hi>discretion,</hi> yet in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to <hi>Custome</hi> to be left to <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> provided they own <hi>abilities competent for the Imployment:</hi> which is yet some times so farre contradicted by <hi>Experience,</hi> as the first <hi>leak</hi> of a <hi>Husbands fortune</hi> is found to rise in the <hi>Kitchin,</hi> and such <hi>Roomes</hi> as <hi>a Man of quality</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not decently <hi>visit.</hi> Nor is there a better way <hi>patent</hi> to obviate this falling into a <hi>Hectique,</hi> through such a <hi>dysentery,</hi> then by an equall <hi>ballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing</hi> all <hi>weekly accounts;</hi> Never no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>wisdom</hi> any more blemish to <hi>Honour,</hi> than to know how many <hi>Horses</hi> he keepes in the <hi>Stable,</hi> a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113531:28"/> place that cannot be denied to be made, by <hi>use</hi> rather than <hi>Reason,</hi> more becomming his presence than the <hi>Pastry</hi> or <hi>Larder.</hi> Nor is the <hi>Keeping</hi> of a <hi>regulated expence (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnified rather than decryed in the highest Courts of wisdome)</hi> Neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed so much out of Scorne as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. <hi>Fathers especially Rich ones,</hi> being so farre to learne themselves what is most fit their <hi>Children</hi> should be taught, as they keep them so long in the <hi>Latine School,</hi> till the time is lapsed most proper for <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick the most neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary part of Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</note> and to make a <hi>perfect Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptant:</hi> the most necessary part of the <hi>Mathematiques,</hi> and so much, as cannot be in any commerce spared. It remaining in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubitable, that none <hi>so industri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> as to call himself to a <hi>weekly</hi> or at lest an <hi>annuall reckoning,</hi> did <hi>ever</hi> through his own default <hi>spend</hi> an <hi>estate.</hi> Whereas the want of this <hi>first rudiment of Thrift,</hi> hath, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113531:28"/> the compasse of my experience, brought diverse to a bit of <hi>Bread,</hi> and demolished the <hi>houses</hi> of the most <hi>antient Gentry</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> Now if any desire to understand, how <hi>our more illiterate Fathers</hi> came to escape this Curse; an answer lyes ready, That the greatest part of their <hi>Revenues</hi> did consist in <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions</hi> of all sorts, payed punctually at a <hi>day,</hi> and so easily <hi>accompted</hi> for and <hi>remembred.</hi> And this <hi>abundance</hi> they injoyed kept them pleased and in <hi>friendship</hi> with their <hi>estates,</hi> wanting neither <hi>Company</hi> nor <hi>respect:</hi> through which they became lesse▪ liquorish after the <hi>glory</hi> and small <hi>delights</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and the <hi>Court;</hi> towards which <hi>they did seldome look,</hi> but upon constraint; having never tasted them in <hi>youth,</hi> as now they do, <hi>the only time to contract an affection to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place or thing.</hi> So as <hi>That</hi> we call the <hi>breeding</hi> of our <hi>Gentry,</hi> is the maine Reason of their <hi>undoing:</hi> the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113531:29"/> glorious <hi>aspects</hi> the <hi>City</hi> affords rendring the more sollid <hi>pleasures of the Country</hi> contemptible &amp; distast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. And thus Infatuated, from the hope <hi>of a redemption</hi> by an <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> or <hi>Wife,</hi> they drop into an <hi>Ocean</hi> of <hi>Debts,</hi> between the <hi>Sylla</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rybdis</hi> of a <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Country-House;</hi> which, for want of <hi>moderating their</hi> expence (a thing <hi>Arithemetick</hi> is the readiest, if not the only means to <hi>Reforme</hi>) it becomes no lesse terrible to look upon in relation to <hi>sollitude</hi> and <hi>dilapidations,</hi> than un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to abide in, for feare of the <hi>Sherife.</hi> But however this may prove good counsell to <hi>others,</hi> it is of small concernment to <hi>you;</hi> who I thank God are of another temper and a more <hi>mathematical Education.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Great wealth sometime a snare</note>16. <hi>Great wealth</hi> is not seldom the birthright of <hi>Fooles,</hi> being for the most part a result of the <hi>Fathers Covetousnesse:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:113531:29"/> found more <hi>easy</hi> for such <hi>Heires</hi> to double, then to <hi>expend</hi> with <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor decency</hi> and <hi>moderation</hi> so much of it as is sit to be allotted for <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spitality,</hi> out of vast <hi>revenues.</hi> The most likely reason why the <hi>Families</hi> of <hi>Citizens</hi> are consumed through <hi>Prodigallity,</hi> or beare <hi>to posterity</hi> the markes of <hi>basenesse;</hi> because un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with the true Elements of <hi>housekeeping;</hi> through an equall mixture and moderate temper of which, <hi>Honor</hi> comes to <hi>be genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Opinion of the world:</hi> There appearing as wide a Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence (for the most part) betwixt a <hi>Gentleman</hi> of <hi>blood,</hi> and one of <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune</hi> as lyes between the Confines of <hi>moderation</hi> and <hi>excesse.</hi> From whence <hi>it often chanceth</hi> that <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick wealth</hi> doth become rather a <hi>Misfortune,</hi> than a <hi>blessing,</hi> by procuring not onely <hi>Diseases,</hi> but bringing <hi>Braves</hi> and <hi>Trapanners</hi> like <hi>drones</hi> and <hi>waspes</hi> into the <hi>Houses</hi> of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113531:30"/> such ignorant <hi>Gallants,</hi> as by reason of a <hi>low breeding</hi> are not able to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend what is convenient, or take the true height of their <hi>acquaintance</hi> and an exact survay of what <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> may with <hi>decency</hi> and <hi>safety</hi> be kept. From whence we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it easier to attaine <hi>wealth,</hi> than the <hi>wisdome</hi> to <hi>spend</hi> it without transgressing the rules of <hi>Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or falling upon the extremes of <hi>basenesse</hi> and <hi>excesse.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">No relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on besides a Father to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fided in.</note>17. Sad experience hath, amongst others, left me this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questioned Legacy, <hi>That no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, below a Father, is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fided in by Younger Children.</hi> The feare of having their <hi>Joynter</hi> que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stioned, Obliging a <hi>partiality</hi> in <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes</hi> towards their <hi>first borne;</hi> a <hi>terme</hi> more pernitious to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of <hi>Man-kind,</hi> than the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of it might possible prove to the persecutors and oppressors of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113531:30"/> the Children of God: These <hi>Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>psies</hi> (sound commonly Slaves to their wives or vices) and performing their taske in this world under a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher canopy of Honour than some of their <hi>younger brethren</hi> ever stood neare, have, besides the <hi>cruelties</hi> and unnaturall <hi>burdens</hi> they lay upon them, through their power and a bare deception in <hi>Law,</hi> converted into <hi>stuble</hi> the <hi>straw</hi> their more cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable <hi>Fathers</hi> left their <hi>brethren</hi> to cover them withall. And for <hi>Uncles</hi> &amp;c. their eyes are so intent upon the Splendor of the <hi>House,</hi> as they oversee, out of feare, or Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, all but the <hi>top-branch, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the weakest.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But lest <hi>Interest</hi> should trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port me into a generall declamation against <hi>the most Noble part of the Nation,</hi> out of a particular experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the <hi>ill Natures of Some.</hi> I shall conclude with an advice to put all <hi>younger Children</hi> to such <hi>courses</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:113531:31"/> as may protect them from undoing by the worst of Heires. It being unlikely the <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>England</hi> should stand <hi>unbent</hi> in their favour, so long as they remaine the <hi>Major part</hi> in all <hi>Parliaments,</hi> And have not throughly survaied the wayes to <hi>Infelicity</hi> and <hi>ruin.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Great por<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ions a snare to Daughters.</note> And for <hi>Daughters,</hi> they do not sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prove miserable through <hi>great portions</hi> which causes <hi>snares</hi> to <hi>be laid for them in every place;</hi> they becoming the lot of <hi>Serving-men,</hi> or <hi>Roysters:</hi> or in case the <hi>old Churle</hi> attaines a more <hi>honorable</hi> designe, though perhaps lesse <hi>discreet</hi> (it not being a rarity in Custome to see such <hi>despised</hi> and their <hi>money</hi> and <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states</hi> spent to feed others more <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable,</hi> though lesse rich) A La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy thus created out of a <hi>Daughter</hi> (of these ordinary <hi>Insects</hi> Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) proving in the generality the most despicable animall breathing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:113531:31"/>
               <p>18.<note place="margin">The Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse of knowledge.</note> Nothing is <hi>expunged</hi> with more <hi>difficulty</hi> than the Lines <hi>Custome</hi> and <hi>Education</hi> have formerly drawne in the <hi>Credulity</hi> of <hi>Youth:</hi> which through a no lesse Indiscreet then Imperceptible <hi>Insinuation,</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders all other <hi>usances</hi> and <hi>Opinions distastfull,</hi> and not seldom <hi>Atheisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</hi> belonging to any <hi>Climate</hi> or <hi>Inculcation</hi> but that under which they had the fortune to be borne; like <hi>Parrots,</hi> that only <hi>applaud</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, And in the meane time pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim all others <hi>Fooles</hi> or <hi>Knaves,</hi> upon no more authentique <hi>warrant,</hi> than that <hi>they have done it,</hi> and <hi>were taught so to do, from their Infancy.</hi> A Habit resembling <hi>Beauty,</hi> which though but <hi>Skin-deep,</hi> doth for the most part <hi>prevaile against Reason</hi> her Self: Taught by the <hi>generality</hi> (as Children do the <hi>Bells</hi>) to comply with the <hi>Fancy,</hi> and not the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:113531:32"/>
                  <hi>Imagination</hi> to submit to the reall sense. Wherefore such <hi>variety of Judgments</hi> can be no <hi>prodigy,</hi> where <hi>Truth</hi> &amp; <hi>Falshood</hi> are weighed at so <hi>unsteady a Beame.</hi> And if any thing could prove able to make good the advantage asserted to be found in <hi>the wisdome of precedent Ages</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>the present,</hi> I should rather seek it in the <hi>restraint</hi> and <hi>confinement</hi> the Tyranny of <hi>Custome</hi> keeps us under, than any <hi>defect</hi> in <hi>ability,</hi> or <hi>poverty of Nature;</hi> not observed to be more <hi>prodigall</hi> in <hi>one Age</hi> than <hi>another.</hi> Though confessed some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to make <hi>wisdome</hi> and <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> so <hi>Itinerant,</hi> as to passe from place to place; and may not unpos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly quit our Horizon, when it shall be again <hi>Night</hi> with <hi>us,</hi> and the same dismall <hi>Cloud of Ignorance</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend <hi>England,</hi> as is now known to hover over those former elegant people of <hi>Greece.</hi> But if the <hi>Profit</hi> of some, and <hi>fear</hi> of others be still
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:113531:32"/> able to Manacle the <hi>hands</hi> and <hi>sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle the Feet</hi> of such as are in pursuit after <hi>Reason,</hi> by <hi>confining</hi> them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that narrow compasse of our <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors</hi> discoveries, how is it likly <hi>this Generation</hi> should equall the former, whose <hi>cogitations</hi> were freely <hi>alowed</hi> to expatiate in the wide fields of <hi>Philosophy,</hi> &amp; to implead all things, at the barre of <hi>Reason,</hi> thought guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>falshood</hi> without giving <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall</hi> or receiving <hi>blame?</hi> Whereas the <hi>Authors</hi> of <hi>these times</hi> want not only their <hi>rewards</hi> and <hi>Impunity,</hi> but lye under a Severer <hi>Censure</hi> for vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating some <hi>probable truths,</hi> than <hi>they</hi> were <hi>exposed</hi> to for all their <hi>mistakes:</hi> witnesse <hi>Galileus,</hi> &amp;c. To conclude; it is no more suitable to Prudence, for a man to <hi>hazard</hi> his <hi>credit</hi> for the <hi>advancement</hi> of others <hi>Knowledge,</hi> than tis likely to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove <hi>them</hi> or satisfie <hi>himself</hi> by a bare <hi>repetition</hi> of what hath been said many hundred yeares since,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:113531:33"/> though perhaps never believed till these latter and more credulous Ages had rendered it <hi>vendible</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the protection of <hi>Silence</hi> or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of State not to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated to the vulgar.</note>19. <hi>Moone-ey'd Horses,</hi> whose light is said to increase or wane sutable to the flux or reflux of that <hi>mad Planet, Blanch</hi> and <hi>start</hi> more by <hi>Day</hi> than <hi>Night;</hi> not out of any reall <hi>deformity</hi> resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the <hi>Object,</hi> but their <hi>Sense:</hi> which renders them of a farre more <hi>pernicious concernment, when they are able to lead, than kept un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Capacity fit onely to follow and obey.</hi> And this is not meerly verified by experience in reference to <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> and the owners of <hi>Phanatique Opinions</hi> concerning <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> But all <hi>halfe-witted persons</hi> else <hi>from the Prince in the Throne to the Doctor in the Chaire. Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmenesse</hi> being as <hi>Nauseous</hi> to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:113531:33"/>
                  <hi>Policy</hi> as <hi>Religion,</hi> and as likely to vomit out and desile the old and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>government</hi> of a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as a <hi>Church.</hi> In mistaking <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasmes</hi> for <hi>Prophesies, Memory</hi> for <hi>Conscience,</hi> and <hi>Anger</hi> for <hi>Zeale;</hi> by none <hi>better understood</hi> than the <hi>Romans,</hi> who to draw this popular Monster from approaching the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cana of State,</hi> (not possibly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main alwaies in so serene a temper, and under such an exact discipline as may admit a through inspection of the Multitude without danger.) They never ceas't feasting their <hi>fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacies</hi> at home with <hi>Spectacles of pleasure</hi> (in some of which they placed <hi>Religion,</hi> catching with one bayte both the <hi>profane</hi> and <hi>supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi>) and macerating abroad their <hi>Martiall humours</hi> at the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest and expense of the <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> (as they in a no lesse high than false Arrogancy sty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all but themselves)<note place="margin">Stage-Playes a a good di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version of the people.</note> gaining
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:113531:34"/> through the <hi>Mediation</hi> of <hi>Stage-Playes</hi> and <hi>Gladiators</hi> the same, if not a greater advantage, than the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> drawes from a <hi>Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> of <hi>Wives,</hi> and the unanimous Inculcation of his <hi>Priests:</hi> whereas the <hi>Romans</hi> never owned any <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession</hi> of so insinuating a temper as to cover <hi>Hypocrisy,</hi> nor any <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasmes</hi> (yet did all with an unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous consent acknowledge <hi>God</hi>) as were ever found to produce <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion,</hi> A sinne recorded by truth it self to be <hi>worse than witchcraft,</hi> and therefore not unpossibly the cause why the <hi>Devil</hi> was so earnest of old with the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and <hi>is now so busy</hi> with the <hi>Christians</hi> to make them commit it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of contrary opinions dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</note>It is ordinary with <hi>Custome, Education,</hi> and <hi>Ignorance,</hi> the <hi>Three Grand Impostors</hi> of the world, to face the peoples <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences</hi> with some specious <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:113531:34"/> to <hi>hoot</hi> and <hi>cast stones</hi> at eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Profession,</hi> but what practice hath rendred familiar to themselves; whilst the more intrinsike <hi>knack</hi> of the work intends solely <hi>Honour, Profit,</hi> and <hi>Ease</hi> of the <hi>Magistracy;</hi> The <hi>Center,</hi> towards which all things approved of, do by a Naturall or Impulsive force, tend. It being unpossible the <hi>Pope</hi> together with the <hi>Fryers,</hi> &amp;c. should keep up the price of their <hi>sophisticated wares,</hi> day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uttered, were not the <hi>passage</hi> to <hi>heaven</hi> streightned, and all other <hi>wayes</hi> obstructed but through <hi>their Institutes▪</hi> of which the <hi>credit</hi> would be much <hi>impared</hi> should the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi> tene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts and theirs be thought indifferent. Nor is it more possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for a <hi>Civil Magistrate</hi> to carry the <hi>Scepter</hi> steady, where the winds of <hi>contrary Doctrines</hi> are observed to blow. From whence <hi>it is become</hi> not only the endeavour of <hi>Rome,</hi> but <hi>Reason of State</hi> to maintaine those
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:113531:35"/>
                  <hi>customes</hi> that appear <hi>usefull,</hi> us rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to <hi>Salvation,</hi> and under a no lesse Imperious an Injunction than the <hi>Command of God:</hi> yet not able to extend a <hi>punishment</hi> for a <hi>breach</hi> of them, beyond <hi>Death;</hi> the onely prerogative of <hi>our Maker.</hi> Nor can <hi>Magistracy in</hi> prudence be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for promoting all means ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>unity,</hi> or <hi>Subjects</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that seek to <hi>disturbe</hi> them: who ought rather to conceal all <hi>Opinions</hi> contrary to that <hi>generally confessed,</hi> or remove their persons to <hi>other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> where they find them with more safety Indulged, then by divulging them to kindle a contrary <hi>zeal</hi> in the people, which in a small time <hi>converts</hi> into <hi>Hypocrisy,</hi> the demoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sher of all things Humane and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; being able to promote, under the specious pretence of <hi>the service of God,</hi> the foulest ends <hi>Covetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, Malice,</hi> or <hi>Ambition</hi> were ever found to point at. Wherefore
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:113531:35"/> all <hi>distinctions are, or may be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after</hi> thought <hi>dangerous</hi> in a State, to the severall <hi>Orders</hi> of <hi>Friers,</hi> who though observed to agree amongst themselves, are in sharp contests with other <hi>Covents</hi> &amp; <hi>Fraternities:</hi> so as <hi>Christendom</hi> may be wakened in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Admiration how <hi>his Holinesse</hi> should pretend to an <hi>Infallibility,</hi> and not be able to decide <hi>whether our Lady lay under the universall pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, or was conceived and born immaculate.</hi> The maintaining and controverting of which hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy wasted <hi>candle</hi> and <hi>paper,</hi> and may come one day to <hi>Blood,</hi> as the <hi>Regulars</hi> and <hi>Jesuits</hi> have hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frained from. Nor <hi>need we</hi> go to <hi>Rome</hi> for examples in this Kind, since the truth of this is confirmed in the <hi>Jars</hi> arising between <hi>Towns-men</hi> and <hi>Scholars,</hi> one Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and another; though under the <hi>Institutes</hi> of one and the same <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stotle</hi> and <hi>Government:</hi> which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:113531:36"/> considered, may serve to put the <hi>best construction</hi> on all we find of use in <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Excesse in any thing, a portent of ruine.</note>21. There is an <hi>extent</hi> in <hi>Wit, Learning, Civility, Honour,</hi> and all other <hi>Felicities,</hi> no lesse then in <hi>Conquest;</hi> which neither <hi>Greece, Rome, Goth, Vandall,</hi> nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other <hi>Nation, Person</hi> or <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munalty</hi> delighting in <hi>virtue,</hi> or <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine,</hi> were ever in any Age yet found able to exceed: The Reason that many did draw a <hi>Calculation</hi> for the late <hi>Gustavus King of Swedens Fortune</hi> from the <hi>Lines</hi> of his <hi>suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse,</hi> and the miraculous <hi>dexterity</hi> he used before he met with any consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable <hi>Opposition;</hi> Though not quite divested of <hi>second Causes.</hi> The least of which did not lie in the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Imprudence, where a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration of a will</hi> to <hi>Inslave Germany was discovered before provision was made of a Power likely to effect it.</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:113531:36"/> The Reason such as adhered to <hi>Caesar,</hi> were no lesse <hi>remisse,</hi> then those that <hi>opposed</hi> him, <hi>vigorous</hi> in their <hi>Prosecutions.</hi> But in relation to that is at this time more current in my Fantacy, All <hi>extremes</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>virtue</hi> or <hi>Vice</hi> may be reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned as a <hi>Portent</hi> of the <hi>ruine</hi> of a <hi>people,</hi> and amongst these an excesse in <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Hypocrisy,</hi> the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultes</hi> of a too <hi>high indulged zeale</hi> are the most <hi>Vocall,</hi> and do not sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome like <hi>Castor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> appear mingled with the sayles upon the change of weather. Though the flames of <hi>Superstition</hi> are in this more destructive than they meerly Naturall and <hi>Independent,</hi> on any remoter causes then those of <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> or more sublimate than hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane vessels are able to containe without breaking into <hi>Enthusiasms,</hi> Because found the most ordinary <hi>Precursers of Shipwrack.</hi> Nor is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing likelier to comply with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:113531:37"/> causes of Ruin in this Nation than the vastnesse of London; which like the Liver of an <hi>Italian Goose,</hi> or a <hi>Rotten Sheep,</hi> weighs more than the <hi>whole Nation,</hi> and may not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come in probability <hi>to starve that, but suffocate it self.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a sign of shallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</note>22. A <hi>vacuity</hi> may with safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be concluded in that <hi>Head,</hi> whose <hi>Body</hi> &amp; <hi>Discourse</hi> is filled with too much <hi>Affectation.</hi> Such, through an <hi>overmuch care</hi> about their <hi>Outside</hi> and <hi>Words, proclaime</hi> a <hi>remissenesse</hi> in what relates to the <hi>Mind. It remaining equally rare,</hi> to find a <hi>starch'd and Complementall Man wise,</hi> as <hi>a woman Valiant:</hi> the most serious <hi>Indeavours</hi> of them both being <hi>to captivate the Ignorant Beholders.</hi> And though this may passe but for a <hi>blemish</hi> in <hi>Youth,</hi> it becomes an <hi>Ugly deformity</hi> in <hi>Age: Asserting</hi> their <hi>Opinion</hi> who have formerly thought <hi>Apes</hi> to be of the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:113531:37"/> extraction of <hi>Cham,</hi> or some other <hi>By-blow</hi> of <hi>Humane Generation,</hi> by their too neer <hi>approaching</hi> towards the nature of <hi>women:</hi> wherefore to be avoided as one of the highest ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesses in <hi>folly.</hi> No <hi>Mode</hi> or <hi>behaviour</hi> appearing sutable to all Companies, but what is <hi>Manly, Constant,</hi> and <hi>Resolute:</hi> Overmuch <hi>Cringing</hi> and <hi>Complement</hi> appearing in all Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>unforestalled by a like Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome,</hi> no lesse <hi>Impertinent</hi> then <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious,</hi> as intruding too far on <hi>time</hi> and <hi>better Imployments.</hi> Nor are the <hi>French,</hi> with whom these <hi>Mimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call gestures</hi> are most in <hi>fashion,</hi> the better esteemed amongst <hi>graver Nations;</hi> who are rather found by reason of this <hi>Levity,</hi> to put a baser ally upon their greater <hi>excellencies,</hi> which those conversant in their <hi>Books</hi> cannot but allow them: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst which you may find recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the number of <hi>extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies,</hi> all <hi>Ceremonies</hi> not essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:113531:38"/> depending on <hi>Civility.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A sole A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mick education renders men pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantick.</note>23. It is a saying, no lesse ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall than true, That <hi>a meer Scholar</hi> becomes, through a <hi>sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular</hi> and <hi>Pedantique practice,</hi> not far removed from <hi>an abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute,</hi> &amp;c. None being better able to man out and array with a <hi>Motly</hi> and <hi>pie-bald carriage</hi> (the <hi>habit</hi> of a <hi>Fool</hi>) than he that hath crouded to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether an unsorted <hi>rabble</hi> of all <hi>Stuffs</hi> and <hi>Colours.</hi> A rude <hi>masse of Reading</hi> till it be throughly <hi>fixed</hi> and <hi>concocted</hi> in the <hi>Sun-shine</hi> of <hi>Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> becoming like <hi>Atoms</hi> so <hi>vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile</hi> and <hi>unsetled,</hi> as <hi>for want</hi> of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall <hi>mixture</hi> of the more solid and necessary <hi>Elements</hi> of <hi>Prudence</hi> they <hi>justle</hi> and <hi>whirle</hi> up and down, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out incorporating any thing but <hi>aire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> occasioning</hi> through a too great <hi>dose</hi> of <hi>Mercury,</hi> rather <hi>Palsies,</hi> than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>steadinesse</hi> in the <hi>Understanding,</hi> by rendring it more <hi>bold</hi> than <hi>Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall:</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:113531:38"/> Like <hi>Children,</hi> who <hi>confident</hi> of their perfect skill in the <hi>Game,</hi> before experience hath taught them how to <hi>shuffle</hi> and <hi>deale</hi> the <hi>Cards,</hi> or lay them down in order, Advance little but the <hi>scorne</hi> of <hi>Standers by,</hi> To see a <hi>Courtier</hi> kept out, and a <hi>mean trump</hi> foisted in, where the <hi>best</hi> is required: Manifest through all they either <hi>speak</hi> or <hi>write,</hi> to their <hi>private Epistles,</hi> in which for want of an exact measuring <hi>persons</hi> and <hi>degrees,</hi> they accost all to the <hi>Butler</hi> and <hi>Landeresse</hi> in one and the <hi>same Stile;</hi> or if <hi>possibly changed,</hi> it is in more <hi>tedious</hi> and <hi>Impertinent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions</hi> to <hi>their betters;</hi> in relation to whom <hi>Courtship</hi> requires the most reserved <hi>Brevity</hi> can be found on the outside of <hi>Ambiguous Obscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> Nor can this be laid to the charge of <hi>true Learning,</hi> the <hi>nurse</hi> of <hi>Understanding,</hi> But the <hi>long time</hi> spent before they be <hi>weaned</hi> from the <hi>breasts</hi> of the <hi>Universities,</hi> &amp; put
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:113531:39"/> into <hi>Commerce;</hi> the onely means of attaining <hi>strength</hi> and <hi>ability</hi> to <hi>Judge</hi> what is fit to be retained, and what to be <hi>neglected,</hi> sutable to the <hi>Course,</hi> Fortune or Necessity hath alotted for a future <hi>subsistence:</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibly to be gained under such a <hi>narrow Erudition</hi> as <hi>Cambridge</hi> or <hi>Oxford</hi> affords: which like <hi>Stonage,</hi> the <hi>Pyramids,</hi> and other <hi>Rarities,</hi> may be well worth a <hi>visit,</hi> but not to be made <hi>Habitations</hi> or places of abode. It not <hi>residing</hi> in the power of any <hi>Tutorage</hi> to inculcate a <hi>wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> beyond the extent of its own knowledge, and the ability it hath to back its <hi>Rudements,</hi> by visible <hi>experience; one Example</hi> prevailing more upon the <hi>Memory,</hi> than <hi>ten Rules;</hi> and one that is for the <hi>present to be seen,</hi> than twenty found in <hi>Old Authors,</hi> not <hi>possible to quadrate with all times and occasions.</hi> Nor is there made generally such choice of <hi>Tutors</hi> as are able to distinguish what
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:113531:39"/> is fit to be taught to every respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive <hi>Pupil,</hi> in relation to his <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensity,</hi> and the future <hi>Employment</hi> he is likely to have in the <hi>State,</hi> but do infuse <hi>one and the same rudiments</hi> into all in generall; as if the world had use of no more tooles but one. Which minds me of a laudable and more improving way for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, practised in my time by some of the <hi>Peerage,</hi> that obtained leave for their <hi>Sons</hi> to stand by the <hi>Chaire of State,</hi> and heare all the <hi>debates</hi> in the <hi>House of Lords.</hi> And if the same <hi>were continued</hi> and suffered amongst the <hi>Commons,</hi> it might be a greater improvement than can be found in observing the unmannerly and Insignificant di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stempers in the <hi>Schooles,</hi> &amp;c. To which I shall onely adde that Mr. <hi>Hampden,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pim,</hi> &amp;c. were resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in all <hi>Parliaments,</hi> their age gave them <hi>opportunity to Assist in;</hi> whose highest <hi>excellencies,</hi> so farre
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:113531:40"/> as my poor Judgement can extend, lay rather in <hi>timing their designes</hi> and <hi>concealing their passions,</hi> than in any more prodigious advantage they had of other men. Nor are there any qualities more essentiall than these to a <hi>Politician,</hi> nor lesse In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulged amongst <hi>Schollars;</hi> who, out of a strong presumption of <hi>what they have not,</hi> fall into a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest demonstration of <hi>that they</hi> real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly want.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">An uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spection into scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces most be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note>24. It is recorded of <hi>Solomon,</hi> that <hi>God had given him a large Heart,</hi> through which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came universally <hi>knowing</hi> from the <hi>most despicable Herbe,</hi> to the highest <hi>Cedar,</hi> and deepest <hi>Secret</hi> in <hi>Nature</hi> (then) under <hi>knowledge.</hi> Which may serve to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer their <hi>Curiosity,</hi> who think they have done something towards the confutation of this <hi>assertion</hi> of <hi>his wisdome,</hi> when they find his <hi>sayings</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:113531:40"/> parallel'd in other <hi>Authors:</hi> Since it is a sufficient manifestation of <hi>Gods extraordinary Grace</hi> upon him, that we are assured from his own <hi>wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,</hi> no less than from the testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>Sacred Scriptures,</hi> that part of the whole masse of <hi>Humane Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> lay included in his Person; and so, if equalled in <hi>one indowment,</hi> he was not exceeded by any single In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuall in the <hi>generall Knowledge</hi> of <hi>all.</hi> And as this appeares by the <hi>Donor,</hi> to be none of the smallest <hi>giftes,</hi> no lesse than in the estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Solomon</hi> that did aske it, so may we strongly presume that <hi>an u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niversall inspection</hi> is the most be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming quality a <hi>Gentleman</hi> (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed in a setled calling) can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow his <hi>indeavours upon.</hi> And my memory neither doth nor (I believe possible ever can) direct me to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards an <hi>example</hi> more splendid in this Kind, than the <hi>Lord Bacon Earl</hi> of St. <hi>Albanes,</hi> who in all <hi>compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:113531:41"/> did appear</hi> a good <hi>Profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> if not a <hi>Master</hi> in those <hi>Arts</hi> entertained for the Subject of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ones <hi>discourse.</hi> So as I dare maintain, without the least affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Flattery</hi> or <hi>Hyperboly,</hi> That his most <hi>casuall talk</hi> deserved to be <hi>written,</hi> As I have been told his <hi>first</hi> or <hi>foulest Copyes</hi> required no great <hi>Labour</hi> to render them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent for the nicest judgements. A high <hi>perfection,</hi> attainable onely by <hi>use,</hi> and <hi>treating with every man</hi> in his respective <hi>profession,</hi> and what he was most vers'd in. So as I have heard him entertain a <hi>Country Lord</hi> in the proper <hi>termes</hi> relating to <hi>Hawkes</hi> and <hi>Dogges,</hi> And at another time out-Cant a <hi>London Chyrurgion.</hi> Thus he did not onely <hi>learne</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, but <hi>gratify</hi> such as taught him; who looked upon their <hi>Callings</hi> as honoured through <hi>his Notice.</hi> Nor did an easie falling into <hi>Arguments</hi> (not unjustly taken for a <hi>blemish</hi> in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:113531:41"/> the <hi>most</hi>) appeare lesse than an <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament</hi> in <hi>Him:</hi> The eares of the hearers receiving more <hi>gratification,</hi> than trouble; And (so) no lesse <hi>sorry</hi> when he came to <hi>conclude,</hi> than <hi>displeased</hi> with any did <hi>interrupt</hi> him. Now this <hi>generall Knowledge</hi> he had in all things, <hi>husbanded by his wit,</hi> and dignifi'd by so <hi>Majestical</hi> a <hi>carriage</hi> he was known to own, strook such an awfull <hi>reverence</hi> in those he <hi>question'd,</hi> that they durst not <hi>conceale</hi> the most <hi>intrinsick</hi> part of their <hi>Mysteries</hi> from him, for feare of appearing <hi>Ignorant,</hi> or <hi>Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</hi> All which rendred him no lesse <hi>Necessary,</hi> than <hi>admirable</hi> at the <hi>Counsell Table,</hi> where in reference to <hi>Impositions, Monopolies,</hi> &amp;c. the meanest <hi>Manifactures</hi> were an usual Argument: And, as I have heard, did in this <hi>Bassle the Earl of Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sex,</hi> that was born and bred a <hi>Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen,</hi> &amp;c. Yet without any great (if at all) interrupting his other <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:113531:42"/> as is not hard to be Imagined of a quick <hi>Apprehension,</hi> in which he was <hi>Admirable.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Great li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braries more sor pomp than use.</note>25. It is a wonder to see the publique and private <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braries</hi> extant almost every where: yet upon an <hi>impartiall</hi> search into their worth, Most of the <hi>Bookes</hi> they containe will appeare like <hi>salt</hi> that hath lost its <hi>savour,</hi> fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the <hi>Dunghill,</hi> than the <hi>Stalles</hi> they fill; where they abide an unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary <hi>Lumber</hi> in the <hi>Houses</hi> of <hi>Schollars.</hi> The <hi>Ore they afford</hi> not comming to any more <hi>profitable</hi> accompt, after the time required to separate the drosse is reckoned for, besides a <hi>broken stile,</hi> which they do <hi>insensibly obtrude</hi> upon the <hi>neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est wits</hi> and <hi>accutest Judgements,</hi> Through the <hi>meannesse</hi> of their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions and <hi>invalidity</hi> of their <hi>Proofs,</hi> commonly no other than a <hi>vain repetition</hi> of such <hi>Authors Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:113531:42"/> and <hi>names</hi> as did own the <hi>Thing</hi> or <hi>Opinion</hi> they indevour at that instant to make good. As if it were Reason Imperative enough to <hi>lead</hi> us <hi>on, because such as they</hi> can be found to have <hi>gone before:</hi> Though God hath made all <hi>Times alike,</hi> and more capable of <hi>Improvement</hi> than <hi>decay:</hi> The contrary of which would redound as <hi>little</hi> to <hi>his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> as <hi>ours.</hi> If the <hi>Languages</hi> now in ordinary use, which are but the <hi>Paint</hi> of <hi>Bookes,</hi> be not so <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant,</hi> as other <hi>Tongues</hi> more <hi>antient</hi> (a question, that in refference to some of our <hi>Neighbour Nations,</hi> may admit of a disputation) whose fault is it, but theirs, that instead of <hi>Imbellishing</hi> do <hi>corrupt</hi> and <hi>adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> them quite, by a <hi>dialect</hi> as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sutable to the <hi>understandings</hi> as the <hi>Mouthes</hi> of the <hi>Inhabitants:</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the use of the wiser <hi>Italian</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> that explode all <hi>wordes</hi> they find <hi>rough</hi> upon the <hi>pallat:</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:113531:43"/> Abominating no lesse those that savour too much of the <hi>Schools,</hi> then such as retaine the <hi>Barbarisme</hi> of the <hi>Country:</hi> And are by this means able to pick out the <hi>Kernell</hi> in all <hi>Learning,</hi> without the assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of any other <hi>tongue</hi> but their Mothers. The Canting termes of <hi>Arts</hi> being naturall to them, as they might be in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish,</hi> But that the <hi>Academies</hi> dare not <hi>permit it,</hi> out of feare to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Beggars themselves.</hi> The cure of Ignorance being far more ready and easie then our <hi>Empericks</hi> make it, and sooner obtained through the open aire and daily <hi>exercise</hi> of <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience,</hi> than the <hi>confinement</hi> to a <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> under a <hi>set-form</hi> of <hi>Erudition,</hi> &amp;c. For my own particular, as <hi>History</hi> hath been the <hi>chiefest</hi> of my <hi>Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> so I shall extend no censure beyond what I have <hi>found,</hi> which is
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:113531:43"/> so <hi>little</hi> of <hi>certainty,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty in Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> as I rest quite unsatisfied, especially where many do relate to one &amp; the same time. A <hi>Cloud of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses</hi> by reason of their manifest clashings and contradictions, rather <hi>darkening,</hi> then <hi>cleering</hi> the waies of <hi>truth▪</hi> so as we cannot credit <hi>Books in matter</hi> of <hi>fact,</hi> farther then they relate to <hi>names,</hi> which is an uselesse sound to those that never did coverse with the <hi>persons:</hi> Yet are in this so far to seek, as to leave us divers <hi>founders</hi> for <hi>one</hi> and the same <hi>City,</hi> and as many <hi>Cities</hi> for the <hi>Birth</hi> of one and the Same <hi>Man.</hi> The <hi>ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall</hi> of People, if not <hi>of all things else</hi> being rendred as <hi>questionable,</hi> as their <hi>wars</hi> and <hi>conquests,</hi> which like <hi>stories</hi> in <hi>Hangings;</hi> shew <hi>fair</hi> and <hi>legible</hi> towards <hi>that Nation</hi> the <hi>Historian</hi> designes to adorne: but if <hi>examined on the other side,</hi> there's nothing appeares but <hi>ends</hi> and contrary <hi>figures</hi> or <hi>expressions:</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:113531:44"/> The <hi>records</hi> of <hi>one Country</hi> receiving a strong <hi>contradiction</hi> from those of the <hi>next,</hi> and if <hi>Authors</hi> be never so little numerous, from some of <hi>her own.</hi> Wherefore the bright Raies of <hi>honour,</hi> that doth now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne the heads of <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> have rather resulted from their <hi>Pens</hi> then their <hi>Swords,</hi> and a <hi>felicity</hi> they had in being only able to <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify</hi> themselves to <hi>posterity:</hi> And that <hi>humane relations</hi> intend more the satisfaction of <hi>particular Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rests,</hi> then that of <hi>Truth;</hi> may be guessed by any that have but mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the <hi>Occurrences</hi> of our Daies, where the same <hi>Press,</hi> if not the same <hi>Pen,</hi> was often found to contradict it self. Nor have we reason to Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine the <hi>Antients</hi> more candid in their <hi>recitements</hi> of <hi>Naturall</hi> and <hi>Contingent events,</hi> since we find them so <hi>Romantique</hi> and <hi>Hyperbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall</hi> in those they took for <hi>Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous,</hi> which might not unpossibly
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:113531:44"/> be no more than <hi>Naturall,</hi> though they were unable to assign thē their <hi>true cause;</hi> all Nations being at their <hi>beginning</hi> under as thick a vaile of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> as the Innocent <hi>Indians</hi> are found to lie now. Who did <hi>regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster in their belief,</hi> the <hi>Armed Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> for <hi>Angels,</hi> and the <hi>Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stication</hi> of an <hi>Eclipse</hi> for a high <hi>prophecy:</hi> So as no Rationall man will question, but if these people had expell'd by force their <hi>glorious Invadors,</hi> before <hi>true information</hi> had of their condition, <hi>Tradition</hi> would have delivered them to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity in the same <hi>Characters</hi> and <hi>shapes</hi> their first abused <hi>Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> had cast them <hi>in.</hi> Wherefore such <hi>Miraculous Conclusions</hi> relating in <hi>History</hi> to respective <hi>places, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> and <hi>Times</hi> are subject to <hi>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion,</hi> unlesse <hi>warranted</hi> by a more <hi>Authentique Attestation</hi> then what is <hi>Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e:</hi> It being <hi>a certaine sign</hi> of a jugler, <hi>not to be able or willing to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:113531:45"/> do one &amp; the same thing often, and in diverse places, and before sundry wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses.</hi> Nor is the vast <hi>difference</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most every where observable in <hi>Chronology,</hi> a small obstruction to an <hi>Historicall Faith:</hi> it being much easier to know the certaine <hi>time</hi> when a <hi>battell</hi> was fought, than eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>accident</hi> happenable in the <hi>Field</hi> or <hi>circumstance</hi> attending a <hi>Miracle;</hi> through which <hi>the first</hi> may appear the <hi>lesse honourable,</hi> and <hi>the latter</hi> the <hi>more Naturall.</hi> The <hi>effects</hi> of <hi>a Confederated Company</hi> and prepared to <hi>deceive,</hi> Lying obnoxious to no other <hi>discovery,</hi> than what the <hi>whip</hi> or their own more Ingenious <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession</hi> hath power to extort. Nor are <hi>Authors,</hi> otherwise creditable, barren of unlikely <hi>Productions,</hi> which leaves the <hi>verity</hi> of the rest in <hi>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion;</hi> witnesse <hi>Livy, Herodotus, Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sephus,</hi> &amp;c. amongst the <hi>Heathen,</hi> without reckoning <hi>Eusebius, Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> and other <hi>writers</hi> relating to the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:113531:45"/>
                  <hi>Church:</hi> The which whosoever Reads, may find cause enough to think they took up most of the <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders recorded</hi> by them upon the <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit</hi> of such <hi>reporters,</hi> as might, not unpossibly have abused <hi>them</hi> as much, as <hi>they</hi> are found the <hi>mislea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> of <hi>Posterity.</hi> Wherefore <hi>Histori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ought not to be over luxurious in their Narrations of <hi>Improbable things,</hi> but rather to imitate the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor</hi> of the <hi>Jew</hi> formerly mentioned, who leaves his <hi>Reader</hi> to a <hi>free</hi> choice of that he thinks fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject or receive, in his <hi>History</hi> of the <hi>people of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For, though the <hi>attestation</hi> of <hi>so many Pens</hi> may authorize a <hi>beliefe,</hi> that there was once <hi>such a Man</hi> as <hi>Alexander.</hi> Yet double their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber would hardly perswade a <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Reader,</hi> that he <hi>Conquered the whole world,</hi> or that <hi>he perfumed all places with his sweat,</hi> together with the <hi>old-wines tales</hi> written of <hi>Buce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalus,</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:113531:46"/> in which <hi>he</hi> appeares little lesse <hi>rationall,</hi> than <hi>themselves.</hi> And this we <hi>carefully hord up,</hi> with a huge masse of <hi>wast Paper,</hi> which containes no richer <hi>Legacy</hi> than that of our <hi>Forefathers Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Credulity.</hi> Yet a Generation is still in being, that do not onely <hi>plead the causes</hi> of such <hi>Improbabilities,</hi> but <hi>Anathematize</hi> for <hi>Infidels</hi> all that cannot admit them a roome <hi>in pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibility:</hi> Not considering, that as strong a <hi>delusion</hi> might darken the apprehensions of those that <hi>convaid</hi> them to us, as doth yet appear in <hi>such,</hi> that (notwithstanding our <hi>clearer light</hi>) keep them still in <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit</hi> with the world. Now if it be not a <hi>Prodigy</hi> to find <hi>Belief</hi> abused in <hi>Grosse,</hi> as it was when two <hi>Armies</hi> were <hi>routed,</hi> the one by an <hi>Host</hi> of <hi>Thistles,</hi> the other through the <hi>dust</hi> of a <hi>Drove</hi> of <hi>Cattle</hi> coming to <hi>Victuall the Camp,</hi> why may we not Imagine a far greater <hi>paucity</hi> of <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:113531:46"/> lyable to a like <hi>fascination? a few</hi> being more <hi>obnoxious</hi> to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception,</hi> than <hi>Many; Fear</hi> having, in all Ages, retained a power to stamp upon the <hi>Fantasy</hi> what <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures</hi> she pleases. This may advise you not to follow <hi>History</hi> beyond the <hi>Pillars</hi> of <hi>Possibility:</hi> No more then to count <hi>Controversy</hi> binding; but <hi>where she leaves no room for Reply.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <p>26. <hi>Iron</hi> is of more <hi>use</hi> to <hi>Man,</hi> than <hi>Gold,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iron of grea er use than gold, and manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture then lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note> though ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary for <hi>pride</hi> to <hi>rate it</hi> and <hi>Jewels</hi> at a higher price; The greatest <hi>Riches of Princes</hi> consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting in that which (like <hi>Honour</hi>) is no other waies beneficiall to <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce,</hi> but as it is prised by <hi>Opinion:</hi> So <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Manifactures</hi> have been, in all <hi>Happy Commonwealths, looked upon</hi> as far more <hi>Necessary,</hi> than <hi>Learning.</hi> Under the notion of which all things deserve no better title, thou those of <hi>Splendid Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencies,</hi>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:113531:47"/> that do not bring a reall advantage to <hi>Commerce.</hi> Heretofore <hi>neglected</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> as it is yet in other places; where through an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse</hi> of <hi>Ecclesiastiques</hi> the Church becomes more <hi>Populous</hi> than the <hi>Temporalty:</hi> whose <hi>wealth</hi> and <hi>Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor</hi> cannot long be wanting to raise so great a Cloud of <hi>Jealousy,</hi> and <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetousnesse</hi> in the <hi>Lay power,</hi> as they may not <hi>unpossibly</hi> be <hi>Immerged</hi> in <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Confusion,</hi> the <hi>Cords,</hi> or <hi>Ligaments</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> having been, in these later Ages, much <hi>staked</hi> no lesse then <hi>enervated</hi> through <hi>Dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,</hi> and the immense <hi>charge</hi> the <hi>Laity</hi> are, through their <hi>Incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> daily exposed to. Sutable to a <hi>Story</hi> of wise <hi>Gondamor,</hi> who urged by <hi>King James</hi> to relate the <hi>intrinsick</hi> cause of the <hi>D</hi> of <hi>Lerma</hi>'s declension, from the most potent <hi>Favourite</hi> his Catholique Majesty ever rais'd, to a <hi>condition</hi> so <hi>deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,</hi> as litle if any thing was left,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:113531:47"/> besides <hi>a Cardinals Cap,</hi> able to shrowd his head from the, &amp;c. Made him this Metaphoricall Parable, <hi>That two</hi> Rats <hi>having tempted their Fortune in persuit</hi> of Livelihood <hi>and</hi> honour, <hi>fell upon a</hi> house <hi>of no lesse</hi> receipt, <hi>then</hi> plenty <hi>of all</hi> Provisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; <hi>where for many yeares they lived in the greatest</hi> sensuality <hi>their wills or wishes could prompt them to desire: Till overcome by an</hi> ambitious <hi>thirst of</hi> advancing <hi>together with</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, <hi>all could pretend to their</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance <hi>or</hi> Friendship, <hi>so much</hi> spoile <hi>was commited, as did Alarum the whole</hi> Family, <hi>and they becoming thus Numerous, had</hi> Traps <hi>and</hi> Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son <hi>laid for them in every place,</hi> The like disaster may not <hi>impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> impend such <hi>Academies</hi> as teach meer speculative and useless conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, not capable of fixation under any <hi>Theories,</hi> which with <hi>Hawking</hi> &amp; <hi>Hunting,</hi> may better become the Gentry, than the <hi>Sons</hi> of the <hi>Menu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:113531:48"/> whose <hi>heads;</hi> like drink, it doth In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicate with <hi>flatulent</hi> &amp; <hi>insignificant vapors,</hi> for want of <hi>money</hi> and <hi>means</hi> to estate them in <hi>experience:</hi> without which, <hi>Learning</hi> is of no more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the <hi>possessor,</hi> then a <hi>Pearle</hi> to a <hi>Dunghill-Cock,</hi> or a <hi>Ring</hi> in a <hi>swines Snout: wisdome</hi> being a <hi>Lady</hi> of too high a <hi>straine</hi> for any <hi>base Converse,</hi> or <hi>Idle Company;</hi> it being far more <hi>naturall</hi> for good parts to plot mischief than stand still. From whence I conclude, that all receiving benefit from any <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,</hi> should be tied to follow some <hi>calling</hi> or other, and not to live upon a bare hope an <hi>University</hi> may in time advance them to.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Learning makes men fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious.</note>27. Such a <hi>poeticall Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> as <hi>Ovid</hi> raiseth against <hi>Cadmus,</hi> the Founder of <hi>Letters</hi> (feighned by him to have put the <hi>Gods</hi> and <hi>Men</hi> into a <hi>Disaray</hi>) may <hi>admit</hi> of a <hi>Morrall</hi> equall with an <hi>Historicall,</hi> no lesse than <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:113531:48"/> Truth:</hi> Since a too univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sally dilated <hi>Learning</hi> hath been found upon triall, in all Ages, no fast friend either to <hi>policy</hi> or <hi>Religion;</hi> being no lesse ready To <hi>discover Blemishes</hi> in the <hi>one,</hi> than <hi>Incongru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ities</hi> in the <hi>other. Sophisters</hi> like the <hi>Cantons</hi> of the <hi>Swisse,</hi> becoming willing upon the least apprehension of <hi>advantage,</hi> to plant the same <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins</hi> and <hi>weapons</hi> against the <hi>wrong side</hi> as the <hi>right,</hi> And not seldom with as good <hi>successe.</hi> Most of the <hi>Heritiques,</hi> Anathematized of old, having been observed to lay the foundation of their <hi>Schismes</hi> in <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content</hi> for the losse of some <hi>Church Preferment</hi> denied them from <hi>their own,</hi> or to gain a greater offered by some <hi>other.</hi> Thus we see that <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> have ever been and will still continue, the <hi>corner-stones</hi> of the <hi>Devils Chappel:</hi> wherefore most <hi>men,</hi> no lesse than <hi>places</hi> render themselves obnoxious to the brand
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:113531:49"/> of <hi>Hypocrisy,</hi> where <hi>these</hi> are found <hi>too earnestly prosecuted:</hi> not pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible to be avoided, but by affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>Clergy</hi> so much <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>riches,</hi> as may guard them from <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> and the opinion of <hi>covetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,</hi> (which are meer results of <hi>necessity</hi>) and too mean a rate so high a <hi>Calling</hi> and usefull both to <hi>this life</hi> and <hi>a better</hi> no lesse then all sortes of <hi>Governours</hi> is set at; though not able to <hi>subsist</hi> without them, or be <hi>victorious.</hi> The <hi>Trumpets</hi> not proving so prevalent before <hi>Aye</hi> in the hands of the <hi>Souldiers,</hi> as the poor despicable <hi>Rammes-hornes</hi> blown by the Priests.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
               <p>28. Do not through a <hi>too ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid and obstinate Observation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Let not a Cynicall humor make you wave Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility.</note> convert <hi>Virtue</hi> into <hi>Vice,</hi> or render it more <hi>unsociable,</hi> than in <hi>Reason, Nature</hi> and <hi>Civility</hi> it ought to be: As such blunt and ill-tutor'd people often are
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:113531:49"/>
                  <hi>found to do,</hi> who, to wave <hi>Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,</hi> fall into <hi>Incivility,</hi> and to avoid <hi>Pride,</hi> into <hi>Basenesse. Religion</hi> no lesse than <hi>Honour</hi> admitting a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and politique <hi>Complyance</hi> with all <hi>Humours</hi> so farre as <hi>Manners</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend. It having been the guise both of <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Patriarckes,</hi> rather to <hi>sweeten</hi> with a <hi>complacentiall car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage</hi> than <hi>exasperate</hi> through a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof</hi> such as they knew out of the <hi>Pale of the Church: Truth</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at all times <hi>in case</hi> to be <hi>showne</hi> without the <hi>ornaments</hi> of <hi>Courtship,</hi> nor people in a condition to <hi>enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it. Tough</hi> and <hi>downright hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours</hi> gaining more <hi>favour</hi> from <hi>Plebeans,</hi> than <hi>Persons of quality;</hi> the <hi>Market-place,</hi> than the <hi>Court,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards which it is no lesse <hi>Lawfull</hi> than <hi>expedient</hi> to turne your eyes in all things meerly indifferent, as <hi>the highest promotor of Honour.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:113531:50"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Moderation &amp; compl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver out of greatest dangers.</note>29. When you find your selfe <hi>strike</hi> upon the <hi>Rock</hi> of <hi>danger,</hi> or <hi>Moored</hi> in an <hi>Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience,</hi> cast <hi>Obstinacy over bord,</hi> And call <hi>Wisdome</hi> to the <hi>Helme;</hi> which, with the helpe of <hi>Moderation</hi> and <hi>Complyance,</hi> do alwaies keep an <hi>Error</hi> from <hi>grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worse,</hi> if not <hi>expunge</hi> it quite. Nor doth the want of these <hi>appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations</hi> seldome cause <hi>Fooles</hi> to make <hi>shipwrack</hi> of all; whilest <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> by <hi>tacking about</hi> and recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>winde</hi> and <hi>Tide,</hi> doth at worst but <hi>lessen their Fraight.</hi> To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, <hi>wilfullnesse,</hi> like <hi>Jonas, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth stormes</hi> and contrary <hi>billowes,</hi> against all <hi>persons</hi> and <hi>Fortunes,</hi> where ever it commands.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
               <p>30. Though taken in the world for <hi>an Honour To be constant to your first Post,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Advised rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on no le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity.</note> Yet in case of <hi>Weaknesse, Conviction,</hi> or <hi>Defect,</hi> it may be no <hi>Imprudence,</hi> any
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:113531:50"/> more than a marke of <hi>Levity to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert it.</hi> All <hi>Assurances,</hi> to that of a <hi>voluntary,</hi> and so the most <hi>Sacred Oath,</hi> being bounded within the compasse of <hi>things Possible:</hi> of which <hi>wisdome</hi> doth ordinarily make <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability</hi> the Judge; yet in my O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion not <hi>Infallible</hi> but in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Conscience:</hi> who should be an imperfect <hi>witnesse,</hi> could she not as justly <hi>acquit</hi> as <hi>condemne:</hi> And with whose <hi>consent</hi> it is no more crime to <hi>change,</hi> than to <hi>follow</hi> your <hi>Guide,</hi> or become lesse <hi>foolish</hi> and <hi>intemperate</hi> upon the sight of a <hi>Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief,</hi> than before <hi>experience</hi> had marked it for such. <hi>Self preservation</hi> being <hi>the first and strongest Principle in Nature;</hi> And so not to be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected but upon the score of <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>honour or vindication of an unquestio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Truth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:113531:51"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">To be the stirrup of anothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s preferment, dangerous.</note>31. It is not alwaies safe, to be found a <hi>step,</hi> by which an other hath mounted himself into the unsteady <hi>Chariot</hi> of <hi>honour:</hi> least his <hi>foot slipping</hi> your <hi>fall</hi> should become a necessary <hi>consequence</hi> of <hi>his,</hi> or <hi>prove so</hi> foul in the opinion of such enemies as new beginners do ordinarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, as will render you irreconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leable to <hi>the other side,</hi> which may not <hi>improbably</hi> prove no lesse au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicious to you and your Fortunes. <hi>Ingratitude</hi> remaining not only use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but necessary to those <hi>in</hi> power: Upon the <hi>Contemplation</hi> of <hi>Pollicy</hi> no lesse than <hi>Thrift: untried Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters</hi> being ever in most credit with such as have a <hi>new Game</hi> to play. Nor is it usuall with men after their <hi>assumption</hi> into <hi>dignity</hi> to hate those did place them there.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:113531:51"/>
               <p>32.<note place="margin">Annuall Magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies too sho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t for great refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations.</note> More <hi>Prudence is</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the Administration of a <hi>temporary</hi> or <hi>annuall power,</hi> than one of longer continuance: because an <hi>over-remisnesse</hi> is as likely to question his repute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst <hi>Strangers,</hi> as too <hi>rigid a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution</hi> to abate his estimation in relation to his <hi>Friends.</hi> For though such a <hi>time</hi> may be <hi>long</hi> enough to <hi>produce errors,</hi> it is farre too <hi>short</hi> to perfect a <hi>Reformation.</hi> Wherefore no bad advice, to follow all <hi>Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes,</hi> that appeare <hi>Indifferent,</hi> though none of the <hi>best,</hi> and such <hi>pathes</hi> as are beaten by <hi>experience,</hi> rather than seek <hi>new:</hi> as I have known▪ many to the losse of themselves and their <hi>fame,</hi> when they came to mingle again amongst the <hi>Society,</hi> and were reduced to an equall <hi>parity</hi> with the rest. For he that is really able to <hi>mend</hi> a <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> will <hi>undoubtedly be more advised</hi> than to perplex so <hi>short</hi> a
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:113531:52"/>
                  <hi>Magistracy</hi> with what there can be no room found to bring about, but by <hi>exposing</hi> the <hi>Jurisdiction,</hi> no less than your own <hi>Credit</hi> to a dearer experiment and greater Hazard than a <hi>Reformation</hi> (never quadrating with all <hi>Interests</hi>) is <hi>at the best</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to give caution for. From whence it may be concluded <hi>greater Prudence to follow than lead:</hi> Yet under such a Management as no hand may appear to act above bord but your <hi>own.</hi> Not to wade far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this <hi>shallow Honour,</hi> which whosoever carries under an <hi>elated Neck,</hi> cannot but appeare to own a <hi>narrow Heart,</hi> no lesse than a <hi>meane Birth</hi> and <hi>sordid Education:</hi> And so a <hi>year</hi> may be <hi>too long</hi> (for such a <hi>Beast to abide in Honour</hi>) whereas a Man of desert cannot but thinke the time too short for to produce any considerable <hi>change</hi> either in <hi>matter</hi> or <hi>Forme:</hi> Though I could Instance many that have lost more
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:113531:52"/>
                  <hi>Reputation</hi> and <hi>friends</hi> during an <hi>Annuall Preferment,</hi> Than they were ever after able to regain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
               <p>33.<note place="margin">Whose dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course or Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traies their mind un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for Embassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors.</note> All <hi>Complections</hi> and <hi>Natures</hi> are not competent for to be imploy'd as <hi>Embassadors:</hi> some lying at <hi>too open a Guard</hi> in their <hi>Discourse;</hi> a fault inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to <hi>free people</hi> and persons not bred under <hi>restraint.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of a <hi>faculty retentive enough</hi> in relation to <hi>Taciturnity,</hi> are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to keep the <hi>intentions</hi> of their <hi>Hearts</hi> from slying into their <hi>Looks (which</hi> by the way a <hi>publique Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister is to regard more than words.</hi>) Masters of their <hi>Tongues</hi> being not seldome betray'd to a full <hi>discovery</hi> by their <hi>Blood;</hi> which the <hi>shame</hi> of <hi>Lying</hi> or some one <hi>passion</hi> or other <hi>pumps</hi> up, for want it may be of an <hi>Impudence,</hi> none, but those <hi>wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly bred</hi> from their <hi>Cradle</hi> are capable of. The reason <hi>Swarthy
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:113531:53"/> persons</hi> and people bordering upon the <hi>Sun</hi> are more apt for <hi>Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> than the <hi>Ruddy English;</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for <hi>Fine Force,</hi> rather than <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvention the businesse of an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassador.</hi> Nor shall posterity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend <hi>Truth,</hi> if they think it any great Hyperboly in those that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain what <hi>Gondamor</hi> the <hi>Spanish A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent</hi> writ unto his <hi>Prince,</hi> which was, That <hi>King James his most intrinsick desires were Legible in his Countenance.</hi> Wherefore his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was, first to <hi>disturbe</hi> his <hi>Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions,</hi> and after to <hi>appease</hi> them by some facetious <hi>Drollary,</hi> before he imbarked himself in what he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to make the Imployment of the present <hi>Audience:</hi> Being, in my <hi>Opinion,</hi> a more perfect <hi>patterne</hi> for all <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>State</hi> (which <hi>in little</hi> ought to practice what <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chivill</hi> adviseth <hi>in grosse</hi>) than <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar Borgia</hi> prescribed for the <hi>Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of Princes:</hi> who out of <hi>Designe,</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:113531:53"/> or not <hi>provided of better,</hi> did usual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his private <hi>visits,</hi> and <hi>Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences</hi> with <hi>King James</hi> speak <hi>false Latine;</hi> For which he had such dexterous <hi>evasions,</hi> as <hi>his Majesty</hi> could by no meanes make so good use of what was <hi>more congruous.</hi> It remaining alwayes in his power to alter the <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Cases</hi> of his <hi>words,</hi> an <hi>advantage</hi> no <hi>Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> could <hi>possibly afford.</hi> Nor can Indeavour be mispent in making a farther inspection into <hi>the Life of this Incomparable Agent,</hi> which I confesse my self unable to do: Though, in my <hi>own</hi> vindication, I can say he was <hi>Tall,</hi> as I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served a number to be in these days very <hi>wise,</hi> and on the contrary, <hi>not many Fooles, of an extraordinary sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> By which is given a <hi>reall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation</hi> to that <hi>common error,</hi> no wayes authorised from any Reason or Experience, That <hi>the Faculties of the mind cannot be so active in vast
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:113531:54"/> bodies, as little;</hi> provided they be not suffocated by <hi>Fat,</hi> but, like <hi>His, straight</hi> and <hi>meager.</hi> Though I have found <hi>Subtilty,</hi> which is <hi>a more base and slye kind of wisdome,</hi> very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in <hi>small</hi> and <hi>crooked bodies,</hi> which the <hi>properer people</hi> do, in a greater <hi>gallantry</hi> of Nature, scorn. <hi>Gondamor</hi> did, in all <hi>companies</hi> as well as the <hi>Kings,</hi> incline more to <hi>Mirth,</hi> than <hi>Melancholly;</hi> choosing rather to <hi>conceale,</hi> than demonstrate the <hi>Wisdome</hi> and <hi>Arts</hi> by which he brought about <hi>his Masters Designes;</hi> no lesse to the <hi>shame</hi> of the <hi>English,</hi> &amp;c. than <hi>honour,</hi> of his own <hi>dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity:</hi> Who was much wronged at his return into <hi>Spain,</hi> if he made use of all the <hi>advantages his Nations Prudence</hi> and <hi>our remisnesse</hi> afforded him. But to what my knowledge was more perfect in, he had <hi>so quick a wit</hi> as he was able to vindicate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in his greatest <hi>imperfections;</hi> Not wanting Spirit to tell <hi>King
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:113531:54"/> James,</hi> when he upbraided him with his <hi>Latine,</hi> That <hi>he himself spake like a</hi> Prince, <hi>free and unconfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, his Majesty like a</hi> Grammarian, <hi>as if affraid of the Ferula.</hi> Yet the <hi>excellency</hi> of <hi>his parts,</hi> could not shroud him from the <hi>Spanish Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude,</hi> which for many ages hath been observed to <hi>impond</hi> the <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test desert:</hi> for after the <hi>Prince of Wales</hi> safe <hi>returne,</hi> whose <hi>restraint</hi> he did in the <hi>opinion</hi> of the <hi>Conde Olivares</hi> too <hi>strongly oppose,</hi> he fell into <hi>disgrace,</hi> and was, with his <hi>Son,</hi> most Cruelly <hi>cast by;</hi> Being, if a <hi>Papist,</hi> no rigid one, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by many of his <hi>Stories:</hi> amongst which this is one, he told upon some question he was asked concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Intercession. The Picture of</hi> our Lady <hi>being observed to weep,</hi> (an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary deceit used by the <hi>Fryers</hi> to wring money from the Ignorant) <hi>the Neighbourhood where it happened became much troubled, as esteeming
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:113531:55"/> it a bad Omen for the future: Nor were the Church-men backward to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment this feare, Though strongly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed by an exceeding old man in the Village, that did maintaine it was unlikely to be so; Who upon this was convented, and did a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> stifly before the</hi> Fathers of the Inquisition <hi>justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy what he formerly had said: And being by them demanded how he came to be so well acquainted with</hi> the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God, <hi>he repli'd, he knew eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inch of her, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> having been then the Prentise of the Joyner that set her up; And by his appointment had bored a hole in her back-side with his biggest Anger, a hand deep: From whence he concluded, that if ever she could have wept, it would have been then.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To end with <hi>Embassadors,</hi> where I began, it is an <hi>Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> more suitable to the <hi>Prudence</hi> than <hi>Candor</hi> of a <hi>free Spirit;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to an <hi>excuse</hi> of an <hi>Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:113531:55"/> Person</hi> I did once know, who chosen to this <hi>Office,</hi> rather in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the greatness of his <hi>Estate,</hi> than <hi>Love of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> King;</hi> answered, <hi>he could not undertake it without rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his Majesties affaires, for want of Impudence, and his own, through the greatnesse of the expense.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
               <p>34.<note place="margin">Nature en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s no indiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dual wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h all perfection.</note> Such as are exact Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servours of the proceedings of <hi>Nature,</hi> find her not so boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull in her <hi>distributions,</hi> as to accumulate all her <hi>rich indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> on <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>same Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduall:</hi> So as <hi>many</hi> can <hi>write well,</hi> who <hi>by reason</hi> of too great a confluence of <hi>words</hi> &amp; <hi>Matter,</hi> or for want of <hi>Confidence,</hi> (through which their <hi>tongues,</hi> no lesse than their other <hi>Organs,</hi> become <hi>shackled</hi> and <hi>Paralitique,</hi>) are rendred <hi>unintelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible,</hi> and so <hi>Impertinent Speakers;</hi> whereas <hi>others,</hi> owning no meane <hi>perfection</hi> in <hi>both these,</hi> appeare upon
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:113531:56"/> triall no body at <hi>Transaction,</hi> The highest effect of <hi>Prudence:</hi> Though the <hi>two first</hi> for the most part runne away with the <hi>Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>se;</hi> Because the latter is a <hi>milder temper,</hi> and not so able to <hi>rant</hi> out her own <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations,</hi> yet deserves best to be indulged by <hi>Princes,</hi> as being indeed the greatest <hi>rarity</hi> in these <hi>nortbern Clymates,</hi> not yet famed for much excellency in <hi>Negotiation:</hi> For want of which and <hi>secrecy (the Seal of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy)</hi> great affaires have miscarried in my time, Though under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Persons in other capacities not unusefull, especially those of <hi>writing</hi> and <hi>Speaking,</hi> qualities yet more apt to <hi>rayse broyles,</hi> than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to <hi>compose</hi> them: which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed an <hi>Imployment</hi> for more <hi>steady heads,</hi> and such as from their Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, have learned to <hi>Barter</hi> and <hi>contest.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Minist<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> ought some<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>time to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their sense ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous.</note>35. Though to <hi>write</hi> and <hi>speak</hi> intelligible to the <hi>weakest
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:113531:56"/> capacity,</hi> be very commendable, Yet a <hi>Minister of State</hi> ought to be able, by making such <hi>Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theses in his Art,</hi> and leaving out <hi>Points, Comma's,</hi> &amp;c. to render the <hi>Sense Ambiguous,</hi> where the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thest extent of benefit or losse in a <hi>Negotiation</hi> cannot yet be perfectly <hi>Discovered:</hi> upon which a <hi>deniall, excuse,</hi> or farther <hi>debate</hi> may be made use of not so easily done in a <hi>Tongue</hi> universally understood as <hi>Latine</hi> seems to be. The ordinary imploying of which in all or the most things treated about, amongst <hi>Neighbours,</hi> may help to discover a Reason, why <hi>England,</hi> and all other <hi>Nations</hi> esteemed <hi>North,</hi> are so fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently over-reached by <hi>Spaine, Italy, France,</hi> &amp;c. That own Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants far wiser than to be ashamed of, or to disovow their Native <hi>Idiom through a pride they take in being perfect Masters</hi> of one more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain. Yet upon their drawing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:113531:57"/> a <hi>Conclusion,</hi> they may yield so far to Equity, as to choose <hi>Latine</hi> for the most <hi>Indifferent,</hi> and subject to the least mistakes. Nor can I, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fallen on the Art of <hi>writing,</hi> think it any great Impertinency to note, that the <hi>illnesse</hi> of your <hi>inck,</hi> or the frequent taking up <hi>haires</hi> with a <hi>Pen,</hi> may put a man out of the road of his former sense and Line of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention:</hi> wherefore <hi>That</hi> ought to be <hi>fluen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and <hi>This good.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Good cloaths com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellor.</note>33. It is no bad Counsell for a <hi>Travellor</hi> to appear in his <hi>best equipage</hi> upon every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move to a <hi>new place;</hi> especially if he hath no better <hi>recommendation</hi> than his <hi>own</hi> to procure his <hi>welcome,</hi> commonly suitable to the <hi>Opinion</hi> people do at first sight apprehend of his <hi>worth,</hi> the best <hi>assurance</hi> they conceive of honest <hi>payment,</hi> which persons <hi>meanly habited</hi> give small <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ution for; and therefore rarely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:113531:57"/> to a convenient <hi>Lodging</hi> or good and cheap <hi>Pension</hi> or <hi>Dict.</hi> A <hi>new commer</hi> having nothing to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him acceptable, or to advance him in the worlds estimation, but a <hi>gentile Garbe</hi> and <hi>decent Habit: yet under this advice,</hi> that it be not <hi>Clinckant</hi> or <hi>Rich;</hi> since <hi>Gold lace, Rings</hi> or <hi>Jewels,</hi> hath not seldome rendred Travellers the prey of <hi>Braves</hi> and <hi>Murderers.</hi> Besides, an over high <hi>Ostentation</hi> puts an <hi>Excise</hi> on all things you <hi>want</hi> or are forced to <hi>buy.</hi> Nor is this Counsell the less to be esteemed, because borrowed from a <hi>Scot,</hi> whose usuall custome is to shrowd themselves under the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>English:</hi> And if owners of any <hi>Merchandise,</hi> they take up the <hi>best Houses</hi> they can get, by which <hi>they</hi> gain <hi>credit,</hi> though their <hi>Landlord</hi> doth not seldome loose his <hi>Rent.</hi> Wherefore no <hi>honour, Profit</hi> or <hi>Safety</hi> to be known an <hi>owner</hi> of <hi>their acquaintance,</hi> Lest you fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:113531:58"/> a repute no waies suitable to a <hi>Gentleman;</hi> who by <hi>just dealing</hi> may gain in a short time from all, so great a <hi>confidence,</hi> as may render himself secure, and what he wants, supplied at the best hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Princes need wise Counsells.</note>37. <hi>Kings</hi> have their <hi>stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> no lesse than <hi>Motions</hi> in <hi>slip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery Places,</hi> And had need of <hi>good eyes:</hi> wherefore if their own be weak, it behoves them to be <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspect</hi> by whom they are <hi>led. Courtiers,</hi> for the most part, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their <hi>particular Interests,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than things of more <hi>publique concernment.</hi> From whence it may be concluded, that in case of defect, which all <hi>Princes</hi> are, upon some temptation or other, either <hi>at home</hi> or <hi>abroad</hi> liable to; <hi>Birth,</hi> next to <hi>sufficiency</hi> is to be <hi>regarded;</hi> The <hi>sense of honour</hi> supplying in divers persons the place of <hi>Conscience: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> in our daies, being so blen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:113531:58"/> in <hi>Hypocrisy,</hi> that tis come to signify in <hi>Statesmen</hi> greater <hi>danger,</hi> than <hi>advantage,</hi> by raising more <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strust,</hi> than <hi>Confidence. King James,</hi> out of too strong a presumption of <hi>his own reach,</hi> did not weigh the <hi>weaknesse</hi> of those he admitted to the <hi>Counsell-Table:</hi> which might have been the better excused, had his <hi>Juncto</hi> consisted of such as were <hi>Noble</hi> or <hi>wise:</hi> But since these Indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were not onely frequently wanting, but a <hi>Pension</hi> from some one or more forrain <hi>Princes</hi> taken to suborne <hi>Fidelity,</hi> who can won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> fell into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stempers, after the <hi>Governours</hi> had totally neglected the wholsome <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, Queen Elizabeth</hi> had so long used with good <hi>successe:</hi> and did never cease <hi>tampering,</hi> till by <hi>new conclusions</hi> they had put it whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>out of frame. King James</hi> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipating so far of the Misfortune of all <hi>Passionate Men</hi> (especially such
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:113531:59"/>
                  <hi>as abound</hi> in <hi>Fear</hi>) as he carried al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies a <hi>Traitor</hi> in his <hi>face;</hi> of which every wise <hi>By-stander</hi> was able to make use. And from this <hi>patency,</hi> his <hi>Policy</hi> was not onely <hi>enervated,</hi> but rendred more <hi>destructive</hi> than an open and Candid <hi>Discovery</hi> might possibly have proved. From whence his Majesty may be thought, not throughly acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the <hi>Constitution</hi> of <hi>Engl.</hi> when he bestowed the strongest of his Labours, in the <hi>suppressing</hi> and <hi>vilifying</hi> the <hi>Nobility,</hi> not onely found the <hi>Glory,</hi> but the reall <hi>safety</hi> of the Nation: till their virtue was allaied through a <hi>too great dilatation,</hi> by which the <hi>House of Lords</hi> became <hi>numerous,</hi> and as it were of one Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with the <hi>Commons:</hi> a fault so far incapable of amendment, as the <hi>King</hi> was forced, for want of a <hi>party</hi> strong enough for his particular ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, every <hi>session</hi> to Increase their <hi>number:</hi> who being <hi>exhaled</hi> out of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:113531:59"/> the greater <hi>Masse of Gentry,</hi> through the <hi>heat</hi> of <hi>affection,</hi> or cast into this <hi>figure</hi> by the help of <hi>Mammon,</hi> they brought up with them into the House of Commons the same de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires they had of a <hi>Reforming</hi> all things amisse in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State;</hi> w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> in a greater paucity, the Lords could not have so much felt; being above all <hi>oppression,</hi> but what drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped upon them from the <hi>Anger</hi> of the <hi>Prince,</hi> about whom they had, in their <hi>absence,</hi> some <hi>friend</hi> or other to mediate in their behalf. I confesse <hi>our Kings</hi> have been often <hi>worsted</hi> by their <hi>Peerage,</hi> but very rarely, &amp;c▪ Nor were the <hi>conveniencies</hi> of any <hi>other Government</hi> put in the scales, much lesse <hi>Monarchy</hi> exploded▪ The <hi>ancient Nobility</hi> being in their greatest <hi>fury</hi> and highest <hi>Pride,</hi> wise enough to <hi>remember</hi> the <hi>Plume of State</hi> could not be <hi>rufled</hi> without putting in <hi>disardy</hi> all their <hi>smaller feathers.</hi> Nor were the <hi>Kings</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:113531:60"/> of this nation, before <hi>free-holders</hi> grew so <hi>numerous,</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> came to be valued by the <hi>Candle,</hi> not <hi>desert,</hi> to seek with whom to <hi>compound,</hi> in the greatest <hi>dangers</hi> their own <hi>Tyranny,</hi> or others <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition</hi> had cast them upon; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the <hi>chief Leaders</hi> in all <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions</hi> were <hi>persons of Quality;</hi> and bore so much <hi>Zeal</hi> to the <hi>preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of their <hi>Country,</hi> being of the same piece with the <hi>Crown,</hi> As not to demand more than the Prince could well spare, and without which <hi>themselves,</hi> their <hi>Tenants,</hi> and <hi>friends</hi> (amounting amongst them all to little lesse than the whole <hi>Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty</hi>) could not be happy: it being the nature of this Climate to <hi>Love Parliaments,</hi> and <hi>abhorre</hi> all <hi>Arbitrary Government.</hi> Wherefore the <hi>dammage</hi> the <hi>long Sessions</hi> brought, or might farther have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumulated upon this wretched Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, had it not been stopped by the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:113531:60"/> hand of <hi>Providence:</hi> which (consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the <hi>unwillingnesse</hi> of the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder</hi> to give over, or call others to them better able, if not more willing to unload the people) ought not (in my Judgement) to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded. It being as unnaturall for a <hi>Parliament</hi> to be <hi>perpetuall,</hi> as for a person to be continually fed with <hi>vomits</hi> and <hi>purgations.</hi> But to wind up these Politick <hi>Enthusiasmes</hi> (at least for the present) out of my head. The <hi>English</hi> used their Kings, in case of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> As the <hi>Catholick Princes</hi> were wont to do the <hi>Pope,</hi> from whom, after they had taken away, for former <hi>misdemeanors all that he had,</hi> they did, out of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, fear</hi> of their neighbours, of their own conveniency, quietly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him, or some other, into the same Sea, &amp;c. wisely apprehending that no <hi>quiet</hi> can remaine, either in <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> without a <hi>Governour,</hi> or <hi>Community</hi> of strength
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:113531:61"/> sufficient to head and maintain the <hi>Lawes.</hi> Wherefore the <hi>fift Monarchy men,</hi> together with the pretenders to a present <hi>Terrestrial Kingdome of Christ</hi> (if not able to produce more authentique warrant than hitherto they have done) deserve little pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection from the <hi>Magistrate,</hi> because they deny <hi>obedience,</hi> where it is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out question due.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Uxorius Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of dangerous consequence to a State.</note>38. It may be numbred amongst things noted of dangerous consequence, for a State to be governed by <hi>an Uxorious Prince, though reputed no fool in other Relations.</hi> It raising so great <hi>Jealousies</hi> both at home and abroad, as none will <hi>treate</hi> with him about <hi>businesse</hi> of any <hi>Secret con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment,</hi> but upon an unavoidable Necessity; being in all <hi>Negotiations</hi> bound to <hi>communicate</hi> as punctually with the <hi>Queen</hi> as the <hi>King,</hi> upon a no lesse penalty (in case she should take her self <hi>slighted</hi>) then the ruine
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:113531:61"/> of the affaire. The <hi>like caution</hi> may be given in reference to such <hi>Priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do's</hi> or <hi>Minions</hi> as are really, or thought able to <hi>dispose</hi> of <hi>their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters Concessions:</hi> which, besides the <hi>dishonour</hi> it brings to the person of the <hi>Prince,</hi> causeth a far greater <hi>after indigency,</hi> out of <hi>distrust</hi> (in all <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> with <hi>forrainers,</hi> no lesse than his own <hi>Counsel at home</hi>) than there can be found room for, where but one is to be <hi>addressed</hi> to. Since Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence forbids to venter <hi>wholsome Counsell</hi> (ever distastfull to some) in a bosome not right enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it. Wherefore in such <hi>Effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Courts</hi> wisdome is not to tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per at all, or to sit <hi>advice</hi> to the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staffe,</hi> rather than <hi>Scepter,</hi> as the more <hi>dangerous weapon,</hi> and from whence many <hi>blows</hi> have proceeded in my time capable of no milder a <hi>cure</hi> than losse of all hope for the future, if not of <hi>estate</hi> and <hi>life</hi> it self. Nor is it possible for such
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:113531:62"/>
                  <hi>Kings</hi> to be better attended than by <hi>fools</hi> and <hi>Parasites,</hi> being compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon all events to take the <hi>worst</hi> of <hi>Counsells</hi> themselves, and as upon their own Score, out of <hi>shame</hi> to say from <hi>whence they had it.</hi> Nor can a <hi>Prince,</hi> in prudence if in Justice, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse his <hi>Consort</hi> for any <hi>incontinency in speech,</hi> after such an <hi>example</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as to tell <hi>her</hi> what is not sit for any other besides <hi>himself</hi> to know. Where <hi>Polygamy</hi> is in use, this error, of most dangerous consequence to all in a Superlative power, is not so <hi>frequent.</hi> It being <hi>inconvenient</hi> if not <hi>pernicious</hi> for such to Love or <hi>hate</hi> any, beyond so exact a proportion in either of these passions, as may disinable him to <hi>alter</hi> upon every as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance of a contrary Desert. A small <hi>blemish</hi> in the conduct of a <hi>private family,</hi> becomes a no lesse pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then ugly <hi>Deformity</hi> in that of a <hi>State:</hi> where <hi>the wives of Kings</hi> should wholly intend <hi>the content</hi> of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:113531:62"/> their <hi>Husbands,</hi> and <hi>security</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> in <hi>producing</hi> a fair and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questionable <hi>Succession;</hi> and not by <hi>fidling</hi> (as they are too commonly found in <hi>Europe</hi>) with <hi>Government,</hi> to put all <hi>out of tune.</hi> From whence it may be thought no bad counsell, for those of the <hi>first magnitude</hi> in a <hi>State,</hi> to be no longer in <hi>private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation with women,</hi> than during the lesse serious Imployment of <hi>Love:</hi> Their <hi>Advice</hi> like <hi>Eves</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not seldome suborned from the <hi>Maligners</hi> of their <hi>Husbands</hi> Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and the rest of the time spent in <hi>querimonious accusations</hi> of his <hi>best Servants,</hi> or as <hi>unreasonable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> in favour of <hi>their own.</hi> So as if the <hi>head</hi> of <hi>Sampson</hi> had contained but the tithe of that <hi>Strength</hi> said to have resided in his <hi>haire,</hi> a <hi>woman</hi> had never understood <hi>where</hi> it lay: who through an impertinent and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious <hi>Importunity</hi> (which is not sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome mixed with <hi>deceit</hi>) do often
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:113531:63"/> beguile such into a <hi>discovery,</hi> as have been thought <hi>proof</hi> against <hi>Honour, Money,</hi> or the <hi>Rack</hi> it self. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I apprehend <hi>this caution</hi> to be of greater <hi>concernment</hi> than it hath been Imagined, take this <hi>example</hi> which lies yet amongst a number more crowded in my memory, as thought the fittest, because brought about through a combination of <hi>Passions,</hi> of which <hi>Fear</hi> got the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominance by the Mediation of <hi>lust.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> being presented with an <hi>Overture</hi> out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> so secretly mannaged by the <hi>Counsell there,</hi> as the first newes of its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach came with it self; the <hi>Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sengers</hi> (out of fear of a surprisall) dispensing with the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> commonly used in behalf of <hi>Embas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadors,</hi> (because it appeared some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing prodigious, considering the <hi>pride of his Nation</hi>) did much inflame the <hi>Lord Treasurers</hi> desire to know the farthest <hi>extent</hi> of the <hi>Negotiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:113531:63"/> as <hi>conducing</hi> to a present advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, that such an <hi>Answer</hi> might be made as should in some proportion quadrate with the demand of the <hi>Catholick King,</hi> at that time stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding upon <hi>termes</hi> little different from those of an <hi>enemy.</hi> And being informed from the ordinary <hi>espyalls</hi> he kept about his person, that the <hi>attempt</hi> was <hi>difficult,</hi> if any thing neerer than <hi>Impossible,</hi> the <hi>Don</hi> out of distrust <hi>still carrying his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions in his Bosome: Burghely</hi> caused such a <hi>Jesuite</hi> to be <hi>apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> as by reason of former miscar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage could not expect Mercy, and <hi>imparts his desires</hi> to him under as large <hi>promises,</hi> if he brought them about, as <hi>threats</hi> to be revenged on him or his <hi>Associates,</hi> if he found himself <hi>abused.</hi> All which, though with some reluctancy he <hi>undertook</hi> and <hi>performed,</hi> through the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>fair Lady</hi> that first <hi>took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his Commission,</hi> and then <hi>laid it
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:113531:64"/> again under his Pillow</hi> whilest he slept: So <hi>wise</hi> are <hi>women,</hi> or such <hi>fools</hi> be <hi>men</hi> during the <hi>time</hi> they abide under <hi>their Incantation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The alliance of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ian fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily most succesfull to England</note>39. Few <hi>Marriages</hi> have suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded better, <hi>than those</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted between the <hi>Austrian Family</hi> and <hi>England.</hi> Nor is this a bare result of <hi>Luck</hi> but <hi>Reason:</hi> The <hi>remotenesse</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> but above all, their Love to their own <hi>Sun-shine, Customes,</hi> and <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> having fixed their affections so firme to their own <hi>doores,</hi> as they have no desire for <hi>Change:</hi> a quality the <hi>levity</hi> of other Nations that renders them the more univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall Citizens of the world, doth not admit of: whereas a <hi>Spaniard</hi> is a rare Ingredient in any Climate but his own. Out of which may be drawn this presumption, that their <hi>Ladies</hi> cannot but be thought to leave an <hi>Issue</hi> subject to the lesse
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:113531:64"/> question. Nor is the Naturall <hi>fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality</hi> of this <hi>graver people</hi> (seldome found amongst the <hi>French</hi>) a small advantage to the <hi>English Court;</hi> And might not <hi>unpossibly</hi> cure it of that <hi>expensive itch</hi> she hath long borne to <hi>change her fashions:</hi> an humour no lesse <hi>Mad</hi> than <hi>destructive.</hi> And through the prosecution of which all <hi>markes</hi> of <hi>knowledge</hi> are remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and the <hi>Serving Man,</hi> with the <hi>Master,</hi> the <hi>Mistris</hi> with the <hi>Maid</hi> reduced to an equall <hi>parity</hi> in relation to <hi>distinction,</hi> where they have no more certainty to g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ess by, than is deducible from the <hi>Habit.</hi> Whereas in <hi>Queen Eiizabeths daies,</hi> and long since, all <hi>degrees</hi> of persons were <hi>discernable</hi> by their <hi>Cloathes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudistin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits a cause of much po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty.</note> Nor hath any abuse passed over, under so little no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, made deeper Impressions into the wealth of both <hi>Court, City,</hi> and <hi>Country</hi> than this; or hath ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered them more the Objects of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:113531:65"/>
                  <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Contempt:</hi> who are in this become so ridiculous, as to owne <hi>fashions,</hi> by which they are so <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacled</hi> as they cannot <hi>stirre,</hi> carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>Armes</hi> in as great a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint,</hi> as the Women of <hi>China</hi> were reported to <hi>bear</hi> their <hi>feet;</hi> through which they are necessitated to remaine idle, as not able to use their <hi>hands,</hi> or any other honest di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version, but what can be deduced from <hi>discourse;</hi> which the <hi>Spanish gravity</hi> waves. Their <hi>Ladies</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unlike the <hi>French,</hi> whose luck having been of late to be left <hi>guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> to <hi>Minor Kings,</hi> do assume to themselves a sufficiency to manage a <hi>State:</hi> through which their <hi>Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes</hi> come to be perplexed in their affaires.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hope</hi> lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s <hi>Indust<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y</hi> asl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ep &amp; is often the <hi>decoy</hi> to <hi>ruine.</hi>
                  </note>40. Though <hi>Hope</hi> intrudes her self as a Medium in all <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresses,</hi> yet it cannot but be found in experience to <hi>obstruct</hi> (if too farre reli'd upon) the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:113531:65"/> of more prevalent <hi>reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> by dazling the understanding; and like a <hi>white Witch,</hi> keeping <hi>Resolution</hi> so long <hi>in suspense,</hi> and imploy'd in <hi>ceremoniall applications,</hi> as the single sit of a <hi>Feaver</hi> doth not rarely in a small time prove ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the danger of an <hi>Incurable Hectick.</hi> And thus through a plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible and naturall Complyance, <hi>Hope</hi> becomes <hi>the false Prophet of Fortune,</hi> who by her <hi>more happy predictions</hi> is able to <hi>ruine</hi> often the <hi>Affaires,</hi> and not seldome the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> of <hi>Princes;</hi> the evill conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of which having been found to produce <hi>sadder effects</hi> than those of <hi>Despaire</hi> (the <hi>youngest Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of her <hi>Sister, Feare</hi>) who though <hi>last heard,</hi> hath sometimes been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served to give <hi>none of the worse coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels.</hi> Nor is Play looked upon by me for a weak <hi>fomenter of this chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish Deception:</hi> And therefore marked here, as elsewhere, for
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:113531:66"/>
                  <hi>dangerous</hi> and <hi>destructive</hi> to <hi>Princes,</hi> and those at the <hi>Helme,</hi> making them <hi>expect</hi> the <hi>like Auspicious changes</hi> in <hi>worldly occurrences,</hi> as they do ordinarily observe in the <hi>flux</hi> and <hi>reflux</hi> of <hi>Luck at Cardes &amp; Dice:</hi> Not apprehending, <hi>through</hi> a <hi>Contrary Custome,</hi> that though the <hi>termes</hi> be <hi>equivalent</hi> in relation to <hi>uncertainty,</hi> (all <hi>Games</hi> being a kind of <hi>war</hi> and <hi>contest for superio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi>) Yet the <hi>Cunning</hi> used by <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lititians,</hi> like that of <hi>Cheaters,</hi> will overcome the strongest indeavours of <hi>Fortune,</hi> if unassisted by the same advantages. Wherefore since <hi>the success of a Battaile</hi> depends not only upon the Imperceptible conduct of <hi>Providence,</hi> but the Mysterious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions of a <hi>Prudence</hi> confined to no other goodnesse but what relates to <hi>victory,</hi> a <hi>Prince</hi> ought to quit himself of all <hi>dependance</hi> upon this blind Goddess <hi>Chance,</hi> with as much dexterity, as his own preservation
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:113531:66"/> and the emergency of his affaires will admit. The <hi>security</hi> of <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,</hi> like that of <hi>unthrifts,</hi> seldome proving gainfull at the conclusion. Manifest in <hi>Charles Duke of Burgun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> and many others easy to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, who out of a ridiculous <hi>Gaye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> did forfeit his present felicity, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his life, in an <hi>Imprudent expedition</hi> against the <hi>Helvetians;</hi> who, with halfe <hi>the charge he</hi> was at to <hi>ruine himself,</hi> might have <hi>hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them to destroy one another.</hi> And all this was attempted upon no stronger a mediation or Assurance than that of <hi>Hope,</hi> &amp; the incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of those suborned to betray his <hi>youth</hi> into the hands of <hi>Fortune.</hi> From whence may be deduced this <hi>wholsome Aphorisme of State;</hi> That <hi>what is safe can hardly prove dishono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable:</hi> the <hi>report</hi> or <hi>Opinion</hi> of <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rainers</hi> being as farre <hi>below a Prince,</hi> as <hi>Prudence</hi> is <hi>above valour:</hi> Not unlikely to be the reason so <hi>few na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:113531:67"/> have prospered under a Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Counsell,</hi> who by <hi>often provoking successe,</hi> do at last <hi>drive it</hi> quite <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> Wherefore if a <hi>Prince</hi> in a <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Commotion</hi> (especially where he is left the liberty of Choice) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends a <hi>power</hi> neer equivalent with his own, it can be no Impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to <hi>knock off,</hi> by yielding to the <hi>first demandes</hi> of his <hi>Subjects,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more reasonable than those can be expected shall come attended with a greater probability of success on their side: <hi>The rabble</hi> being sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome capable to learne at a cheaper price than <hi>wofull experience,</hi> That <hi>the fall of a Prince doth rarely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any milder a consequence, than the undoing of his people,</hi> by putting all things into a <hi>combustion,</hi> and teaching the <hi>Monster</hi> to know its own <hi>strength,</hi> which cannot safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be opposed but with weapons made of the <hi>same iron;</hi> the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of <hi>forraigne force</hi> appearing
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:113531:67"/> to prudence little better, if not worse than the disease, as having been the <hi>Originall of most</hi> of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests</hi> we read of. All which may tempt a <hi>King</hi> to a charitable, rather than a bloody Complyance, more subject to impaire than better the condition of a <hi>Naturall Prince,</hi> who upon any successe cannot be <hi>Cruell,</hi> without irritating <hi>his own party,</hi> no more than <hi>Mercifull,</hi> since the first will increase their <hi>fears:</hi> as the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth delude their <hi>hopes:</hi> which in such cases cannot be satisfied but with <hi>Confiscations,</hi> not possibly to be so equally divided, as not to oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion more <hi>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oy</hi> than <hi>love.</hi> Because in case of <hi>Victory,</hi> he is no more able to <hi>punish</hi> all appeared <hi>against him,</hi> than to <hi>satisfy</hi> their expectations that stood <hi>for him,</hi> who in another <hi>Commotion</hi> may upon that score be as ready to become his <hi>enemies:</hi> The <hi>Impudence</hi> of <hi>Souldiers</hi> increasing more by one <hi>intestine war</hi> than three
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:113531:68"/>
                  <hi>forraign;</hi> and do breed in a <hi>Politick</hi> the like <hi>distempers</hi> too great a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of <hi>Blood</hi> is found to cause in a <hi>Naturall Body.</hi> Wherefore since the markes of <hi>precept</hi> make not so deep Impressions, as those of <hi>Example,</hi> all former <hi>ill successe</hi> being imputed to some <hi>miscarriage</hi> in the attempt; as the <hi>good</hi> is cried up beyond <hi>desert,</hi> it may not be bad Prudence in Kings to <hi>obliterate out of Bookes all markes of Sedition</hi> (As I heard that famous <hi>Antiquary</hi> Sr. <hi>Robert Cotton</hi> say, <hi>thirty had been in England since the Conquest</hi>) lest Posterity should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them into <hi>precedents</hi> for the like disorders. To conclude, if a Prince finds his <hi>friends</hi> (which in a <hi>rebellion</hi> are hard to be discerned from <hi>Enemies</hi>) not able at the <hi>first Essay of force</hi> to bring in the <hi>conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators,</hi> The <hi>Lion's Skin</hi> is to be <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vested,</hi> and all <hi>hope</hi> layed by, but what may be deduced out of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance;</hi> for fear some about his
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:113531:68"/>
                  <hi>Chaire</hi> should <hi>discover</hi> the <hi>weaknesse</hi> of his <hi>game,</hi> or by <hi>playing booty</hi> ruine him quite: <hi>One losse</hi> being in such cases more than an ordinary <hi>presage of a greater to follow.</hi> For though the <hi>Rabble</hi> are not capable of <hi>prudence</hi> enough to <hi>temper themselves,</hi> they own so much <hi>strength,</hi> as, through the <hi>guidance</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> they are able to <hi>distemper a State.</hi> The <hi>materialls</hi> being easier to be <hi>discovered</hi> than the <hi>contrivers</hi> of any <hi>Rebellion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
               <p>41. <hi>Plantations</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plantations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ost happy at their first plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, because lesse numerous.</note> like <hi>fish-pooles</hi> and <hi>Lakes</hi> are <hi>quietest,</hi> if not <hi>most Happy</hi> at <hi>first founding</hi> or <hi>Storing.</hi> For after some <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution of time hath rendred</hi> them <hi>Numerous, Necessity,</hi> no lesse the <hi>parent</hi> of <hi>Spurious</hi> than <hi>Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Aris,</hi> doth in a <hi>naturall favour</hi> to <hi>self-preservation,</hi> teach them to <hi>cheate</hi> and <hi>Oppresse</hi> one the other. Wherefore the <hi>golden Age,</hi> so much
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:113531:69"/> celebrated in <hi>Poetry,</hi> is as remote from <hi>Fiction</hi> as <hi>Miracle.</hi> The <hi>Earth</hi> affording more <hi>felicity</hi> to a <hi>Few</hi> than <hi>Many,</hi> which those people bordering upon the <hi>Sun,</hi> from whence <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind</hi> is at first said to proceed, might, by reason of a <hi>slower increase,</hi> longer enjoy; Till by falling into conjunction with our <hi>colder Climes,</hi> &amp; (so) apter for <hi>Generation,</hi> she came to <hi>over-stock</hi> her self: Loosing the <hi>universall felicity</hi> in a <hi>crowd of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants.</hi> From whence sprung not onely the <hi>Use,</hi> but an unavoidable <hi>Necessity</hi> of introducing <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which falling under distinct <hi>Headships</hi> or <hi>Royallets,</hi> needed no greater provocation to <hi>Rapine</hi> and <hi>war,</hi> than the <hi>strongest</hi> found in their <hi>Naturall temper:</hi> The same <hi>Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy</hi> abounding <hi>then,</hi> as doth <hi>now,</hi> though palliated by the great <hi>plenty</hi> of all things the <hi>world</hi> afforded at the <hi>beginning:</hi> none being so much in love with <hi>Choller,</hi> or any other
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:113531:69"/>
                  <hi>passion,</hi> as to to fall into it unprovo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. This proves <hi>want the originall of Law,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> makes that <hi>an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of Sin.</hi> And from hence might spring a greater <hi>sincerity</hi> in the <hi>service of God,</hi> the sole <hi>refuge</hi> of those that have none other to fly to. <hi>It being common with all men to extend their hope beyond the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of what they fear;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore easily slattered into a <hi>beliefe</hi> of any <hi>felicity</hi> though never so <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable</hi> or <hi>remote.</hi> And because this is <hi>Natuall</hi> and imprinted in the <hi>character</hi> of all <hi>Humanity,</hi> I look upon it as none of the weakest assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of our <hi>future blisse.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
               <p>42. <hi>The world</hi> was never in so <hi>serene</hi> a temper,<note place="margin">Most wars occasioned by the jealousies of small Royallets.</note> as under <hi>Augustus Caesar;</hi> During whose raign the <hi>King of Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> appeared, and the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of war</hi> stood sealed up, so as the <hi>Gods</hi> and <hi>Goddesses</hi> assigned by the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:113531:70"/>
                  <hi>Heathen</hi> for <hi>Military Imployments,</hi> had leave to <hi>play;</hi> being <hi>emancipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> from all <hi>perturbations,</hi> arising through <hi>the variety of Petitions,</hi> the <hi>contrary Interest</hi> of <hi>Mortalls</hi> caused them to make. Nor can this <hi>Halci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Tranquillity</hi> be in Reason impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any remoter <hi>Earthly cause,</hi> than the entire <hi>unity</hi> of those times, <hi>terminating</hi> in the single person of <hi>a Moderate Prince.</hi> From whence may be Naturally <hi>deduced</hi> this <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oreme,</hi> That <hi>Christendome</hi> would not onely strengthen h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> posture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Grand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>igniour,</hi> but be more secure in her self, under <hi>one Monarch</hi> than thus <hi>cantoniz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> as she is: Though I shall not dispute what Nation is most opportunely situated for such a Design, to avoid Controversy, being as ready (and I believe under protection of as strong Reason) to present <hi>England,</hi> as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may be to offer <hi>France,</hi> or any member belonging to the <hi>House
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:113531:70"/> of Austria.</hi> Wherefore to passe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the discourse of <hi>an Universall Monarchy,</hi> as savouring too much of <hi>the Utopian Dialect,</hi> and rendred <hi>unpossible</hi> through the huge and invincible <hi>proportions,</hi> so much <hi>Time, Ignorance</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>wisdome</hi> of <hi>Princes</hi> hath laid toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I shall modestly examine, Whether <hi>inferior Communalties</hi> and <hi>small Roylets</hi> be not as great a <hi>Bar</hi> to <hi>an Universall Tranquillity,</hi> as the extravagant <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>Peerage</hi> was to <hi>France,</hi> before <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated</hi> by the wisdome of <hi>Lewis the eleventh.</hi> These <hi>lesse Potentates</hi> being compelled, through <hi>weaknesse</hi> and <hi>want,</hi> to cast the <hi>Balls of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention</hi> amongst the <hi>mightier Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs;</hi> which if <hi>reduced</hi> to an <hi>abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Obedience,</hi> as they are already to little lesse, through a Necessary <hi>dependance</hi> from their own preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, on <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Spaine;</hi> Their <hi>malevolence</hi> rendred, through <hi>Fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts</hi>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:113531:71"/> and <hi>Jealousy,</hi> generall, and not sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome contracted out of false sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestions, might be rebated; And <hi>the more powerfull</hi> left at better leasure to attend the montions of the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Family,</hi> and stop the leaks of <hi>Heresy</hi> and <hi>Schisme,</hi> which if suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>run on,</hi> will <hi>suffocate</hi> the power, if not totally <hi>eclypse</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall glory of <hi>the Christian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi> Nor can a better cause be found, why <hi>the Pope's power over Kings</hi> (no question at first usurped) should still remaine floting betwixt the bladders of <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition,</hi> but that he is able to foment a <hi>party</hi> amongst these, which he can increase out of the natives of any Nation that doth oppose him. Thus as it were through an <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peristasis</hi> raised between a burning Zeal in the <hi>people,</hi> and Fear of the <hi>Prince,</hi> he comes to domineer over all alike, but those have crept from under his <hi>Censures;</hi> who are never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:113531:71"/>
                  <hi>lyable</hi> to his <hi>Lash,</hi> at some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time or other, in respect of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Seminaries</hi> he hath ready (yet unpaid by himself) to vindicate his <hi>Quarrels</hi> in every place. Nor are the desires of the <hi>Pope,</hi> no more than the rest of such <hi>petty Princes,</hi> as have nothing <hi>but shifts to subsist by,</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall for the totall abolition of the <hi>Turk,</hi> out of a dread of themselves; which also extends to the distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of an <hi>Universall peace:</hi> They looking upon <hi>the diminution of their Grandeure,</hi> as the onely <hi>Sacrifice</hi> able to <hi>purchase</hi> it. And this gives them, like <hi>whelps,</hi> the boldnesse to <hi>bite</hi> the <hi>greater Monarchies</hi> by their <hi>legs</hi> and <hi>extreamer parts,</hi> when they find them at oddes amongst them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, or (which is worse) grappied with the <hi>Grand Signiour.</hi> And he that is Ignorant in this, cannot be thought knowing in the <hi>Imperiall History,</hi> no more than in other <hi>Passages,</hi> where not onely <hi>his
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:113531:72"/> Holinesse,</hi> but <hi>the most Christian,</hi> to obtaine advantage of the (in that) more <hi>Catholick King,</hi> are reported to have made <hi>a solemne league</hi> with this enemy of <hi>Christ.</hi> Nor have the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Princes</hi> remained long tongue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide in this behalf, no more than their <hi>Caesar;</hi> who may be the <hi>better excused,</hi> as having done it sometimes to prevent a more immediate dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from them at home. It being common with these <hi>petty Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> to hatch such <hi>plots,</hi> and give birth to those <hi>Designes</hi> with which the rest of the world is commonly disturbed: Manifest in the <hi>Duke of Birone,</hi> formerly so far instrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall to the reduction of the <hi>Crown of France,</hi> who became after to have his <hi>fidelity</hi> corrupted through the poyson he received from <hi>Savoy;</hi> that continuall <hi>thorne</hi> in the <hi>Sides</hi> of her <hi>Neighbours.</hi> Nor can <hi>Rochel</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit her self so well, during the time <hi>her walls</hi> did separate the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:113531:72"/> from the obedience of their <hi>Prince,</hi> as, for the Honour of <hi>the Reformation,</hi> I desire it could from like practises, no more than other <hi>Corporations,</hi> &amp;c. have done; the blemishes of which it goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the grain of my <hi>Profession</hi> to discover: Though I wonder from the inspiration of what <hi>Spirit</hi> we come to prosecute the followers of <hi>an unrevealed Anti-Christ,</hi> for ought I ever yet could learn from any <hi>Expositor,</hi> with so great an Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mosity, and passe without notice one doth face us already: Being without question better able and more ready to do greater Dishonour and Mischiefe to <hi>the Christian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> than <hi>the Bishop of Rome</hi> can be tempted to, in regard of his own particular Interest. Through which is Justified that common Impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence generall in the world, where <hi>men prosecute a small dammage from a neighbour, with a fiercer revenge,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:113531:73"/> than a greater sustained by an enemy;</hi> like <hi>Connies,</hi> that may be observed to tear and fight with those of their own kind, but will make no resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance against the <hi>Pol-cat,</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enemy of all. And thus do our high Nos'd Hypocriticall <hi>Zelots,</hi> that pretend to smell ranck <hi>Idolatry</hi> in all professions, but their own: yet in the mean time are found not onely to neglect the open and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed <hi>Antagonists of Christ,</hi> but with <hi>Pharo's leane Kine,</hi> are obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to devour the <hi>Revenues,</hi> &amp; take the <hi>Houses of God</hi> into Possession under the pretence of a <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> first begun in <hi>Germany,</hi> which, as some have thought, was left by providence to <hi>the Austrian Family,</hi> not out of Gods wrath, but a tender care of the <hi>Christian affaires.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Spaniards waving Asia in expectation to conquer Europe impolitick and unsuccesfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</note>43. Had the <hi>Catholique King</hi> sought <hi>extension of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi> at the prejudice of <hi>Asia,</hi>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:113531:73"/> and not <hi>incroached</hi> upon the <hi>Territories</hi> of his <hi>Christian Neighbours,</hi> he might in probability have been neerer, if not his whole ends, yet far more than he is <hi>Master of,</hi> or can in likelyhood be ever able to obtaine, by the course he takes. Nor is this my single Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but an assertion of a <hi>Spaniard</hi> in a small treatise, where he handles five <hi>Problemes,</hi> of which this appears not to savour of the least Likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: Since in the first prosecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of such a project, his <hi>Sailes</hi> would not onely be <hi>emptied</hi> of much of the <hi>envy</hi> all the <hi>Princes</hi> of Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome do <hi>swell</hi> with now in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to his undertakings, but <hi>filled</hi> with their wishes for a happy successe. Nor could the <hi>Pope</hi> in <hi>shame,</hi> if in <hi>conscience,</hi> have refused him a <hi>Crusado,</hi> or any <hi>assistance</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> could afford, at least with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his owne Kingdomes: if he should have owned an Impudence
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:113531:74"/> to deny a larger <hi>Contribution,</hi> or the uttermost of his indevours to staye off <hi>France</hi> from fastening upon his patrimony in his <hi>Absence.</hi> Nor can <hi>Ambition,</hi> as <hi>Machiavill</hi> wisely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves, promise it self a more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable successe than is likly to follow an <hi>Invasion</hi> of <hi>Turkey;</hi> whose <hi>strength,</hi> as <hi>the same Author</hi> attests, lyes more in <hi>Tradition</hi> than reall <hi>Truth,</hi> at this day in <hi>peace</hi> with the <hi>Persian,</hi> and so secure of the rest of <hi>Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> as if they were all asleep, yet hath not been able to wrest <hi>Candy,</hi> in all this time, out of the weakly-supported hands of the <hi>Venetians.</hi> Nor doth any <hi>Prince</hi> in the world own those <hi>advantages</hi> for such an <hi>attempt</hi> as the <hi>Spaniard:</hi> his other <hi>Limb,</hi> the <hi>Emperour,</hi> lying at the Mouth of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> ready to atache him upon the sound of any <hi>Mutiny</hi> or <hi>Rebellion,</hi> at this day ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>frequent</hi> amongst them: And might, with the more probability
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:113531:74"/> of advantage, <hi>be fomented,</hi> because the people are in a condition not capable to be <hi>impowered.</hi> Nor is there any Nation in the world of more <hi>contrary Complexions</hi> in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>People</hi> and <hi>Religions.</hi> Nor can any man think it a Matter of difficulty, to take in the <hi>Grand Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior's out-workes,</hi> that hath heard what report Sr. <hi>Robert Mansel</hi> made, at his returne from <hi>Algiore,</hi> where, upon sight of a <hi>Commissionlesse Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,</hi> that <hi>King James</hi> sent, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons became <hi>Sutors</hi> to their <hi>Slaves</hi> for <hi>Mercy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
               <p>44. Though <hi>Machiavill</hi> may deserve <hi>Commendations,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative and practick part of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litickes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</note> for the excellent use he hath made of the proceedings of his first <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py,</hi> then <hi>Miserable</hi> Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance <hi>Caesar Borgia,</hi> Son to <hi>Pope Alexander the</hi> 6. Yet I doubt, if himself had filled the same roome, and owned <hi>the like advantage,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:113531:75"/> he had been able to have attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to that height <hi>Caesar</hi> did, though in <hi>wisdome</hi> and splendor of <hi>Birth</hi> not inferiour to him. It requiring <hi>one</hi> Spirit to <hi>write</hi> and <hi>another</hi> to <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to the Life</hi> and sutable to every occasion, all <hi>Scenes</hi> both <hi>Comicall</hi> and <hi>Tragicall</hi> in relation to <hi>friends</hi> or <hi>foes,</hi> likely to furnish out, with a present security or future conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, a Person fit to mount into a <hi>throne</hi> made vacant by <hi>fraud;</hi> Since none but such as from their birth have been used to <hi>personate</hi> what really <hi>they never were,</hi> can, in this wise <hi>Authors Opinion,</hi> pretend upon a lesse hazard than the ruine of himself or his family, to <hi>the government of State:</hi> To which there are required such <hi>contrary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricacies,</hi> as whilest one is unrave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, another <hi>twines;</hi> so as without an exact observance of those <hi>Elle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of policy</hi> he prescribes, there can be no hope for a <hi>Tyrant</hi> to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist.
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:113531:75"/> Nor were these <hi>Aphorismes</hi> common only to <hi>Caesar Borgia,</hi> or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him, but continue to this day, especially in <hi>Italy:</hi> where no <hi>wickedness</hi> is shunned, any waies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the <hi>Extension of Empire</hi> and the <hi>ends of Ambition. His Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse</hi> himself entertaining all meanes for <hi>Lawfull</hi> and <hi>right,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying any probability of advancing his <hi>Children</hi> or <hi>Nephewes.</hi> In which they have remained so long <hi>prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,</hi> as most of the <hi>small Princes</hi> beyond the <hi>Alpes,</hi> are themselves, or their wives, <hi>chippes of the Crosse▪</hi> And meer <hi>excrescencies</hi> of the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> which <hi>practice</hi> is made so <hi>common</hi> through <hi>Custome,</hi> as all markes of <hi>Reproach</hi> lye covered, if not in the <hi>Nature,</hi> in the <hi>Necessity</hi> of the attempt, Nothing lesse than a <hi>superlative strength</hi> being able to secure the <hi>Issue</hi> of a present <hi>Pope,</hi> from the rapine and spoile of him that may
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:113531:76"/> not unpossibly succeed. It running qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te contrary to the wise practice of <hi>the Conclave,</hi> to choose twice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether out of one and the same <hi>House,</hi> but rather to exclude all the immediate possessors <hi>Confidents</hi> or <hi>Kindred, out of a dread they have</hi> to affix the <hi>Miter</hi> in a particular <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</hi> Yet notwithstanding the <hi>Pope's</hi> prudent <hi>management</hi> of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, during their own time, they have not seldome been so fowly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staken by counting upon the score of their own <hi>Judgements</hi> and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall affections, as to anticipate the ruine of them they studied to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, for want of making an Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall survey of the <hi>Prudence</hi> of such <hi>Children</hi> or <hi>Nephewes</hi> as they sought to advance, and a through conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the strength of their <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plections,</hi> and depth of their <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences,</hi> whether able to disgest all sorts of blood, cold and hot, likely to obstruct the waies to what
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:113531:76"/> was aimed at. The venerable Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian <hi>Guicciardine</hi> noting, that though <hi>Alexander the sixt</hi> was at first so far perplexed at <hi>the death</hi> of his <hi>eldest Sonne,</hi> as to <hi>renounce the world,</hi> The same Author saith, <hi>he resu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it again</hi> upon the first assurance given, that <hi>his other Sonne the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall</hi> had been <hi>the Murderer;</hi> And did, after his <hi>resignation</hi> of the <hi>red Hat,</hi> redouble his <hi>indeavours</hi> to raise him; as if he had looked upon the throwing of his Brother into <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and the laying his <hi>Sister</hi> upon the bed of <hi>Incest,</hi> as a good Portent of his future greatnesse; whose <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> though something <hi>gelt</hi> by reason of the <hi>Scandall</hi> it gave, may be worth the reading, no lesse than <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavil's</hi> Notes upon <hi>Caesar Borgia;</hi> out of which, and all <hi>Politicks</hi> else, may be observed, That <hi>People in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure oppression with more patience, from an old, than a young Prince,</hi> as thinking it lesse durable, and <hi>from
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:113531:77"/> an Usurper, than one ascending through a continued succession;</hi> as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steeming it more <hi>naturall,</hi> and no lesse <hi>than they looked for,</hi> or do acknowledge to have deserved, for not seeing when they were well: A consideration a <hi>Polititian</hi> should ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punge, by contrary practices, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them a <hi>liberty</hi> in all <hi>innocent punctilio's,</hi> and every thing else re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to their <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>estates,</hi> so long as they remaine quiet, let the persons be of what <hi>Magnitude</hi> they will: sutable to the wise conduct of <hi>Spain,</hi> where <hi>the elder Family</hi> is suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered annually to renew <hi>his Claime to the Crown,</hi> though with as little successe as interruption. Nor is it safe for a Prince incessantly to afflict his people, who may, like <hi>Dogges,</hi> quietly for a time indure it, though upon a too unreasonable <hi>continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> they do not seldome so farre participate of that beasts (well known) condition, <hi>as to fly in their
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:113531:77"/> face.</hi> Wherefore <hi>Governours</hi> should, for their own sake, no lesse than the Nations, Imitate <hi>God,</hi> who though absolute disposer of <hi>Promise</hi> and <hi>performance,</hi> doth conforme <hi>the latter</hi> punctually to <hi>the first:</hi> which whosoever doth not, may, like <hi>a drunken man,</hi> be justly thought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicated in his understanding: since <hi>the breach of an Oath</hi> must needs be a <hi>Trap</hi> abominated by all, in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the more Innocent <hi>Sheep,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause honest men hardly can dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spence with the use of it, in the insnaring of such <hi>wolves</hi> as do op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse and devoure them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
               <p>45. <hi>Machiavill</hi> doth accuse as <hi>Imprudent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bloody Princes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and imprudent.</note> all such <hi>Princes</hi> (and most especially those whose <hi>Virtue,</hi> as he calls it, hath given <hi>a beginning to Empire</hi>) That <hi>knew not when to stop that Issue of blood, which may at first be neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to steep such Titles in, as have no
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:113531:78"/> better colour to face their Legality, but what is attained by Prudence, or the Sword</hi> (from the benevolence of which all powers now extant were at their originall derived) <hi>But did continue their bloody Cruelties and Malignant Aspect.</hi> Keeping by that meanes <hi>the Peoples discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents</hi> waking, and so by consequence <hi>their own</hi> no lesse chargeable than terrible <hi>feares</hi> and <hi>Jealousies:</hi> nothing being more obvious to probability, than the raising some <hi>Spirits</hi> (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the number of enemies, such a continued practice will in all reason produce) as can never rest satisfied without <hi>Revenge;</hi> Often brought about by so uncouth and <hi>improbable meanes,</hi> and the mediati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of such <hi>despicable Instruments,</hi> as no <hi>purvoyance can shield</hi> the person of a <hi>Prince</hi> from: who, whilest his prudence, like the <hi>Philosophers eyes,</hi> are fixed upon higher and more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote <hi>dangers, he fals into some nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:113531:78"/> Trap he never dreamt of.</hi> And to manifest the truth of this Asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>the same Author</hi> doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other <hi>examples</hi> borrowed from <hi>Antiquity;</hi> which I shall wave, and onely content my self with that of <hi>the Duke of Buckingham.</hi> That fell by the hand of <hi>Felton,</hi> whose <hi>Picture</hi> I am the willinger to draw, as thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it well becomming <hi>the bosome of all Persons in power.</hi> In which I am not likely to be partiall, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to my knowledge never seen the man, Though <hi>his Father</hi> owed an <hi>Imployment</hi> under <hi>mine</hi> in the <hi>Office</hi> of <hi>Remembrance</hi> for many yeares. He was of a <hi>Religious and quiet conversation,</hi> given to no <hi>open vice</hi> nor <hi>whimsicall Opinions,</hi> being <hi>a frequent hearer of those Preachers</hi> as were never found to give incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to such <hi>practices,</hi> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the contrary: <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Teares</hi> being the sharpest <hi>weapons</hi>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:113531:79"/> that were then <hi>formed</hi> in the Pulpit by <hi>Parochiall Pastors;</hi> what ever <hi>Lecturers</hi> did; from whose doctrine I have been told he was ever averse; <hi>nor was honest Jack,</hi> a title al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes given him, (though ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred after more diffusive by the <hi>Dukes</hi> enemies, than so ill a conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence might merit) Agitated by <hi>revenge,</hi> or any <hi>privater Spirit</hi> than what he was perswaded did regard the <hi>Common-weale;</hi> As I heard <hi>William Earl of Pembrooke</hi> protest, who could not but be the best infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, having assisted at <hi>his examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> who did with all aver he never saw <hi>piety</hi> and <hi>valour</hi> better or more temperately <hi>mixed in one Person.</hi> Nor was he found, as <hi>the same Lord</hi> attested, in any <hi>untruth.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse that through the continuall Inculcation of his <hi>Majesties Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines,</hi> and others of the <hi>long Robe,</hi> he did <hi>disavow</hi> so far the <hi>Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> of the <hi>Fact,</hi> which before his
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:113531:79"/> Conscience never blanched at, as he desired <hi>The hand that did it might be cut off:</hi> But neither himself, nor the indeavours of the <hi>Dukes</hi> friends could procure him a sharper <hi>punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> than <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Custome</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides, in case of a <hi>Murder,</hi> for the <hi>meanest Subject.</hi> Nor can this <hi>Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to the Tower</hi> be looked upon for lesse than the best Fortune so high a Malefactor could be capable of. Since during his abode there, which was many weekes, he had <hi>a plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Diet</hi> provided for him at the Kings charge. By all which it may appeare, the Man was onely led through strong <hi>Enthusiasmes</hi> That <hi>Buckingham</hi> was <hi>an enemy to the State:</hi> An Opinion Princes ought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things to avoid, by shuning every occasion likely to represent him <hi>cruell</hi> or <hi>Implacable</hi> in the eyes of the people, by being continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tumbling and tossing that lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber out of his way, which ought (if
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:113531:80"/>
                  <hi>at all</hi>) to be removed <hi>at one and the same time,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">To ascend a Throne by much blood unsafe.</note> and then <hi>with as little noise and Injustice as may be, Repetition of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishments, Confiscations</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonments</hi> being apt to be thought by those not able to see to the end of the prospect (yet most considerable for number) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult rather from <hi>the Princes Nature</hi> than emergency of the cause; And therefore not improper to Alarum the most Innocent; rendring <hi>the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Hydra</hi> an Historicall truth, the cutting of <hi>one head</hi> producing from Kindred and friends <hi>hundreds</hi> in the place, of which perhaps the Major part were none before: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing carrying a greater propensity towards <hi>fertility</hi> than <hi>blood.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore since a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> by reason of the <hi>crooked waies</hi> that lead to an <hi>usurped Crown, Holds not his safety under so Conscientious a tye</hi> as a <hi>Naturall Prince,</hi> till he become <hi>so</hi> through
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:113531:80"/>
                  <hi>Lenity, Justice</hi> and <hi>Continuance:</hi> it behoves him to be more <hi>moderate</hi> in the prosecution of others: <hi>Lest through their Innocency, either reall or Imputative, his own prevaricati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons should be kept in remembrance.</hi> And, for a vindication of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary practice, <hi>Merchiavill</hi> presents as his best patterne to <hi>the house of Medici</hi> (That had not onely at first Surreptitiously gotten, but did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter regaine, through the mediation of like artes, <hi>The Principality of Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scany) Caesar Borgia,</hi> who was found to remove all enemies and Obstructions out of his way <hi>in gross,</hi> and not dribling <hi>by retaile:</hi> The <hi>people</hi> being as <hi>partiall</hi> in their <hi>pitty,</hi> as ready upon the apprehension of <hi>Injustice</hi> and <hi>Cruelty</hi> to exercise a <hi>more extravagant Tyranny of their own.</hi> For though a frequent pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing of single persons may <hi>stoppe the mouth</hi> of this <hi>Monster</hi> for a time, it doth more increase than diminish
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:113531:81"/> its desire to <hi>bite,</hi> upon the approach of a small advantage, which is farre easier found than may be Imagined. Wherefore no cause of <hi>discontent</hi> can in Prudence be admitted, but what is squeesed out by <hi>necessity,</hi> but rather <hi>Lenitives</hi> applied: the <hi>Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> being of so <hi>brutish</hi> a nature, as to become more plyant to obedience through <hi>Stroking,</hi> than <hi>smart,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially if any thing they <hi>Fear</hi> lyes in the way, <hi>or where that they Love is removed;</hi> it remaining beyond peradventure, That <hi>Clemency</hi> did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver occasion <hi>Repentance,</hi> but in case of <hi>Example</hi> or <hi>Competitors, Blood</hi> being like <hi>Opium,</hi> which taken in a just proportion causeth <hi>quiet,</hi> but that once exceeded, <hi>Death.</hi> Or if <hi>patience</hi> &amp; <hi>connivance</hi> should find their virtue lost in some <hi>incorrigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble natures,</hi> yet the errour were ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily redeemed; whereas <hi>Cruelty</hi> is of so staining a quality that, like the <hi>Scorpion,</hi> nothing can expunge it,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:113531:81"/> but what results from its own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Now where this <hi>Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is observed, and all <hi>Liberties, Honours</hi> &amp; <hi>Immunities</hi> Religiously preserved, I apprehend no more cause of <hi>Griefe,</hi> than the <hi>English</hi> had occasion for <hi>Joy,</hi> when they exchanged <hi>King Richard the third,</hi> for <hi>Henry the seventh:</hi> It remaining indubitable, that however <hi>the first</hi> might be a <hi>Murderer,</hi> he did not with <hi>the second oppresse</hi> the people: wherefore such as call him <hi>Tyrant,</hi> offer violence to a number of <hi>good Lawes</hi> he <hi>made;</hi> and <hi>shew too much partiality,</hi> if they esteem <hi>him</hi> the better Prince that <hi>brake</hi> them: <hi>Kings,</hi> that succeed by <hi>birth,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging no obligation to any but their <hi>Ancestors:</hi> whereas <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> indeavoured to gain the <hi>Love</hi> of the Nation, and did so farre pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, as to have <hi>an Army</hi> appeare for him against <hi>the Duke of Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> in those dayes <hi>the Darling of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:113531:82"/> the Commons,</hi> and wherein were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>of quality;</hi> a strong presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Juster and milder temper in Government, than the Ignorant and partial <hi>Historians</hi> of those times are found to record: So as though <hi>he</hi> may be reckoned amongst the <hi>worst of Men,</hi> his <hi>Lawes</hi> will recover <hi>him</hi> a place with the <hi>best of Kings;</hi> And <hi>no bad precedent for those</hi> that may at first ascend, contrary to the Gusto of a considerable part of the <hi>people,</hi> whose <hi>affections</hi> do coole or heat proportionable to their <hi>feares</hi> and <hi>oppressions,</hi> which none ought <hi>to continue; A doubtfull condition</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the most terrible to Man.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">That Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy most durable, that's foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded on the best Policy.</note>46. Though <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar</hi> amongst the Antients, And <hi>the Kings of Sweden</hi> in our days, may be thought to receive their Impulses from <hi>the Lord of Hosts,</hi> Yet the <hi>dampes</hi> and chill proceedings that fell upon the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes,</hi>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:113531:82"/> especially of the <hi>first</hi> and <hi>last</hi> after their decease, may give us leave to observe, How in all ages <hi>such na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have flourished most and lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest as were able to maintaine the the choisest Prudence at the Helme.</hi> For want of which, after <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der's Death,</hi> the <hi>Grecian Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> was weakened, and in a Manner lost, in the <hi>Division</hi> his <hi>Captaines</hi> made of it; each taking for his share <hi>so great a proportion,</hi> as his owne <hi>Dexterity,</hi> or the <hi>Love</hi> of the <hi>Colony</hi> he commanded, gave him the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to graspe: opening through this meanes an entrance for <hi>the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Conquest,</hi> which followed next, and, by reason of <hi>a better esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment,</hi> did longer indure. From whence it may be supposed, That <hi>the Fortune of</hi> Greece <hi>lay more in the handes, that of the</hi> Romans <hi>in the Heads of their Founders: Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> having <hi>proved,</hi> in all ages, <hi>more prevalent,</hi> at long running,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:113531:83"/> than <hi>Successe;</hi> which may become sometimes the <hi>Dowry,</hi> but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Inheritance</hi> of a <hi>Foole,</hi> or the owners of no farther <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scerning Spirits</hi> than the present. The Reason <hi>great Achievements</hi> do not seldome Terminate no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than in the ruine of his name, <hi>Fame,</hi> and <hi>Family,</hi> that did at first <hi>bring them about:</hi> the <hi>advancement</hi> of which is onely able, if any thing be (an Opinion ever doubted of) to palliate the <hi>Blood, Labour</hi> and <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard</hi> such undertakers run for the present, without casting up what at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends them in future. Nor can I rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily call to mind an <hi>Usurper</hi> that did ever better <hi>compose his affaires,</hi> than <hi>William Duke of Normandy,</hi> who, after the defeat of <hi>Harold,</hi> the last <hi>great Card</hi> likely to indanger his <hi>game,</hi> is not repotted continually to face the Nation of <hi>England</hi> with an <hi>Army</hi> (of no lesse terrible as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect alwaies to the <hi>people,</hi> than it is
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:113531:83"/> of dangerous consequence some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to the <hi>Issue of a Prince</hi> after the death of his Father; Their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall <hi>readinesse in being,</hi> affording them the fairest opportunity to choose a <hi>successor</hi>) yet did secretly maintaine a convenient <hi>militia</hi> out of the <hi>spoiles</hi> alotted to such as had imbarked their Fortunes with his: not <hi>passing</hi> any <hi>Land</hi> from the Crown, but upon <hi>Contract</hi> with the owners to <hi>assist</hi> him at his call, with a proportion of <hi>horse</hi> and <hi>men</hi> sutable to their estate; a covenant not hard to be performed by such whose <hi>wel-being</hi> lay wholy inclusive with <hi>his.</hi> And of these <hi>Tenants for Men and Armes</hi> there was not a few, as appears in the <hi>Register</hi> yet remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their <hi>Names,</hi> amongst whom I am not ashamed to find those of <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Mother:</hi> Nor did the <hi>Mustering of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se</hi> in every <hi>County,</hi> and upon all occasion faile to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, though with far lesse expence
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:113531:84"/> and <hi>universall terror,</hi> all the ends <hi>an Army</hi> can serve for. Thus by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing his <hi>Rod</hi> and sparing the <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples purses,</hi> he shewed them <hi>the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might be as Happy under a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rainer, as a Native, one Family as another:</hi> not possibly to be done but by removing out of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples eyes all appearance of <hi>Oppressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> There lying so <hi>vast a difference between the Regiment of Love and that of Fear,</hi> as <hi>This</hi> may chance to <hi>stand,</hi> but <hi>That</hi> is never likely to <hi>fall.</hi> All which is said, <hi>not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne any contrary Practise,</hi> but modestly to shew, <hi>where divers waies lead to one and the same end, the least destructive to the generall quiet ought to be taken, in Policy, if not in Conscience.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Tyranny not only natural but necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note>47. The <hi>weight</hi> of <hi>Superiours</hi> will be born with the lesse <hi>anx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iety</hi> and <hi>perturbation,</hi> if we seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously consider, That <hi>Oppression</hi>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:113531:84"/> &amp; <hi>Tyranny</hi> is not only <hi>Naturall</hi> but <hi>Necessary</hi> to preservation. For if the <hi>stronger Creatures</hi> did not spoile and devour the <hi>weaker,</hi> the whole masse of <hi>Animalls</hi> would perish by <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine;</hi> or <hi>stifle</hi> for want of <hi>roome.</hi> Since the <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>Sea, Nature▪ Magazines for Provisions,</hi> are not able to sustaine the <hi>Stock,</hi> a despi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable <hi>Mouse</hi> or <hi>Pilchard</hi> would in a small time swell to, <hi>did they not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come</hi> the <hi>food</hi> of others. Wherefore wise <hi>Providence</hi> hath matched eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry things <hi>strength,</hi> in their respective gradations, with such proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Antagonist<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> that they are all contained within the compasse of a just <hi>proportion</hi> (like a nest of boxes) through a <hi>restraint</hi> from such as own a greater extent in <hi>power.</hi> And to counterpoise the <hi>wisdome</hi> in <hi>Man, which renders him subordinate</hi> to none but his particular <hi>Species,</hi> the same <hi>Providence</hi> doth permit him to be actuated by such Impetuous
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:113531:85"/>
                  <hi>Passions</hi> and brutish <hi>Desires,</hi> as, through the Mediation of <hi>excesse, Covetousnesse,</hi> and <hi>Ambition,</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the <hi>Moderator,</hi> no lesse than <hi>Destroyer</hi> of <hi>his own kind.</hi> The <hi>Sword</hi> receiving from these a daily <hi>Commission</hi> in one place or other to <hi>kill</hi> and slay. And <hi>where this is too little</hi> to ballance the <hi>Incomes</hi> of <hi>Lust,</hi> an <hi>over-repletion</hi> calls in <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stilence</hi> and <hi>famine</hi> to turne the Scales. All which cannot be Voted <hi>Plagues,</hi> but in a <hi>respective</hi> sense, as onely relating to such as perish in them; since a great, if not the most considerable part do receive benefit by it, and <hi>Nature</hi> her <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>light,</hi> which seems to reside in <hi>variety.</hi> All this considered cannot but bear witnesse for <hi>Seneca's</hi> Truth, <hi>That nothing would accept of Life upon such hard conditions as the Creature doth under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, if it lay in its power to refuse:</hi> whose <hi>being,</hi> together with the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance</hi> in it, is imposed without
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:113531:85"/> any <hi>primary consent</hi> at all, or <hi>future,</hi> but for the dread of falling into a <hi>worse:</hi> Adorning the glorious <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot of Nature</hi> in this world, till like <hi>withered Flowers they be laid aside</hi> by the same <hi>Hand</hi> first gathered them out of <hi>Nothing,</hi> and still pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves their <hi>Root</hi> through the act of <hi>Generation,</hi> by which they are led in a brutish Sensuality to betray <hi>Posterity</hi> to the same <hi>Inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> those capable of reason cannot but apprehend uncapable of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensation from the highest tasted <hi>content</hi> this world affords; That whirles about in a continuall <hi>Circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> changing the <hi>Formes,</hi> but not the <hi>Nature</hi> of things. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though it appeare against the decree of <hi>Providence,</hi> to obstruct the course of <hi>Generation,</hi> it may not be undecent to mind <hi>Christians,</hi> that the great <hi>reluctancy</hi> usually found in them towards <hi>Death,</hi> doth not only question their <hi>integrity in
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:113531:86"/> Religion,</hi> but <hi>understanding:</hi> else <hi>they would never adjourn,</hi> by so much labour and anxiety of spirit, what <hi>Nature</hi> hath <hi>alotted</hi> for all in <hi>generall,</hi> without the excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any thing capable of <hi>Life:</hi> who may injoy a free prospect of all her <hi>beauties,</hi> though possibly not of every <hi>Malignity,</hi> within the revolution of a <hi>yeare,</hi> if not during the shorter space of 24 <hi>houres;</hi> our time being composed of <hi>day</hi> and <hi>night;</hi> the rest appearing meerly but a <hi>Repetition</hi> of the same thing. Now <hi>since it is the Sin</hi> of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> to <hi>under-rate what hath already passed by her in the visible apparitions</hi> of <hi>Experience;</hi> so it may not impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be as great a <hi>mistake</hi> in <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> to <hi>overvalue</hi> all she never <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:</hi> and consequently becomes the cause of the generall <hi>Terror</hi> appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in <hi>Death,</hi> the onely depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>temporall pain,</hi> The farthest confines of the <hi>Land of Knowledg,</hi>
                  <pb n="159" facs="tcp:113531:86"/> beyond which nothing is discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but what is ingraven upon the <hi>Pillars</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> read and interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted according to the <hi>Dialect</hi> of the <hi>Place,</hi> and manner of the <hi>Erudition</hi> it is our luck to fall under, and out of the verge of which (without a miraculous inspiration) it is <hi>next</hi> to <hi>unpossible for a Man to extend</hi> his <hi>Beliefe.</hi> Wherefore in any Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>to leave the world unwillingly,</hi> or with an <hi>unsetled hope</hi> (since tis the decree of <hi>nature,</hi> and condition of our <hi>birth,</hi> not to continue us here) cannot but appear in the eyes of discretion, no lesse <hi>manly</hi> than <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian.</hi> Yet <hi>many</hi> are so unadvisedly foolish▪ as to <hi>multiply Deaths,</hi> through the agonies their <hi>feares</hi> raise in them, <hi>that one day they must die:</hi> the sole meanes left to free us from <hi>Oppression,</hi> if not to attaine perfect <hi>felicity,</hi> which no servant of <hi>Christ</hi> can doubt of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:113531:87"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Honesty and Prudence not inconsistent.</note>48. <hi>Our Saviour</hi> would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have commanded, under a like Emphasis, <hi>Innocency</hi> and <hi>Subtilty,</hi> had he thought them <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>competible,</hi> or not rather as <hi>Neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary in things Sacred</hi> as <hi>Prophane.</hi> It remaining unlikely, if not unpos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible (during this totall Eclipse of <hi>miracles,</hi> but what reflect upon the world under the notion of <hi>Faith,</hi> which cannot be taken for other than <hi>Implicit,</hi> in any thing that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendes or relates to a more <hi>forraign witnesse</hi> than our own) to keep <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty within the bonds of Peace,</hi> but through <hi>Policy</hi> or (if you had rather have it so) <hi>Prudence:</hi> Though <hi>Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> who may be worthily placed on the highest shelfe ever <hi>Clergy-man</hi> reached to, is not ashamed to intitle his <hi>Workes</hi> by the <hi>first.</hi> Nor are the loudest bawlers against <hi>Discipline</hi> found to neglect it in their own af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires: But do rather back and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the power of it through the
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:113531:87"/> force of the same arguments they laboured formerly to confute it. Making a like use of <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Reason of State,</hi> as <hi>Marishmen</hi> do of their <hi>Sluces,</hi> by which they keep out the <hi>Sea,</hi> formerly owner of the place, and onely imploy them for the benefit of <hi>Land Flouds.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Discipline,</hi> which is the same thing in the <hi>Church,</hi> as <hi>Law</hi> in the <hi>State,</hi> can <hi>be no more spared</hi> than <hi>Government</hi> it self; by which we are taught our <hi>duty</hi> to the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate,</hi> who without this will be as far to seek <hi>when to Command,</hi> as we <hi>what to obey;</hi> from whence we shall find it an easy <hi>descent</hi> into <hi>war,</hi> the greatest <hi>Hell</hi> upon Earth, and of most consequence to be avoided by people any degree short of mad men. Now since we are not onely led by the <hi>example,</hi> but <hi>Precepts</hi> of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> to yield <hi>obedience</hi> to our <hi>Governours,</hi> This in my appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension avowes it presumption in
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:113531:88"/> any, <hi>below the owners of a supream power,</hi> to question the <hi>Decency, Sanctity,</hi> or <hi>Legality</hi> of what the <hi>Church</hi> hath heretofore, or may at this present avouch. For though really converted into <hi>Idolatry,</hi> which is <hi>Treason</hi> against <hi>God,</hi> as the <hi>Brazen Serpent</hi> was; Or into <hi>Heresy</hi> or <hi>Sedition,</hi> which imports no lesse in relation to his <hi>Earthly Represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives,</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Prince</hi> (as the <hi>Mosaicall Purifications,</hi> &amp;c. were in the daies of <hi>Christ</hi>) yet it cannot warrant the hands of any single person, no <hi>not of the multitude in grosse,</hi> to appear in their <hi>abolition,</hi> unlesse by way of <hi>Petition:</hi> But to admit them as trials of their farther <hi>patience,</hi> till <hi>God</hi> inclines the heart of some <hi>lawfull Power,</hi> the onely place such a zeal can be safely kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled in, without threatning destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the whole frame. Men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing commonly partiall in their own care, else such as stile themselves
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:113531:88"/>
                  <hi>the best of them,</hi> would never have exploded <hi>the Call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng of Bishops</hi> (and suffered so many of <hi>their persons</hi> to want, though approved of in their own hearts, for men no lesse <hi>exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary</hi> in their <hi>Lives,</hi> than <hi>Learning,</hi>) under no milder an aspect than <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichristian:</hi> yet did not at the same time <hi>refuse to themselves</hi> the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious title of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> under which notion the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthiest</hi> amongst them did, only in a lesse volume, though in the same or a larger extent, exercise the <hi>like power</hi> over the people of God (if the nation afford any, a Blasphemy to doubt of) as was before held Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny by them for the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> to administer within the circuit of a <hi>Dioc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sse:</hi> not remembring <hi>the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Bishops</hi> have not onely been <hi>Champions</hi> in the cause of <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> but have Justified the conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency of their <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>scipline</hi> through the experience of the <hi>longest peace</hi>
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:113531:89"/> and <hi>greatest felicity England</hi> ever enjoy'd, and with the effusion of the <hi>least blood;</hi> which <hi>these had the fortune</hi> or <hi>will to be aspersed by.</hi> I confesse what hath been said, is something beyond my intent, though much short of, &amp;c. Yet the consideration of this little, may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish out a competent proportion of <hi>Charity</hi> both at home and abroad, to restrain us from taking any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Scandall:</hi> since <hi>the most,</hi> if not the <hi>worst of things the rigid and precise blanch at in our daies, were at the beginning set up to as plausi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an end as they labour now to pull them down:</hi> The first intention of which, cannot be quite lost to any, but such as abuse them to a contrary sense to what they were at first intended for; any more than a Mortall misapplication of a whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some <hi>Drugge,</hi> by an <hi>Ignorant Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perick,</hi> can render it <hi>Poison</hi> in the hands of a <hi>Learned Physitian.</hi> The
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:113531:89"/> same may almost be said of all the <hi>Controversies</hi> in <hi>Christendom,</hi> where the <hi>Priests</hi> have reduced <hi>our gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance to Heaven</hi> into a <hi>gainfull Art,</hi> by rendering the <hi>ways thither</hi> so <hi>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy,</hi> as to be <hi>bought,</hi> or so <hi>difficult,</hi> as to be little lesse than <hi>Impossible to be found.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
               <p>49. I have often indeavoured the contrary,<note place="margin">The opinion, that good works m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall.</note> yet <hi>could never longer than during some</hi> hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>extasy,</hi> separate any <hi>good work</hi> in my self or another, from the <hi>Opinion of Merit;</hi> Though no man's <hi>Education</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> did ever more bandy against it. From whence I have been often ready to conclude it as naturall in <hi>Religion</hi> as <hi>Reason:</hi> For though a <hi>pepper-corne</hi> doth in no sense quadrate with the value of a great <hi>Copy-hold,</hi> yet it doth serve to answer (as far as we are able) the will of the <hi>Donor,</hi> and in that sense alone, through the mediation of <hi>Christ, Heire apparent</hi> to our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:113531:90"/>
                  <hi>Landlord,</hi> it becomes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable it self, though far below our <hi>duty.</hi> For though, as a Christian of the <hi>Reformed Church,</hi> I confesse the principall ingredients in our <hi>Creed</hi> uncapable of reaching, but by the hand of <hi>Faith;</hi> yet where the <hi>seeds</hi> of <hi>good workes</hi> are not mixed, <hi>Religion</hi> growes <hi>flatulent</hi> and <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall:</hi> It being far easier and <hi>chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to refraine</hi> open and <hi>negative Sins, than to performe</hi> the more <hi>chargeable affirmative duties of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity:</hi> which if they were pressed home, not onely in <hi>Pulpits,</hi> but <hi>practice,</hi> and every one Conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiously <hi>examined,</hi> whether he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth <hi>Sanctity To gain an Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or an earthly inheritance,</hi> you would see Hypocrisy sneak away like the <hi>young man in the Gospel,</hi> who was ready to <hi>ride post to Heaven,</hi> provided he might <hi>carry his riches behind him.</hi> Now to prove <hi>Hypocrisy</hi> and <hi>uncharitablenesse</hi> are the crying
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:113531:90"/> offenses of this Age, consider how many have, with <hi>Zacheus,</hi> met and compounded by <hi>Restitution</hi> for what they may not have peradventure come by so well. And in relation to <hi>Governours,</hi> to whose wiser conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations I humbly offer these few following <hi>Observations,</hi> if they shall be pleased to cast their eyes upon the Nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and inquire <hi>in what condition they stood</hi> at the coming of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> &amp; till <hi>Vespa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sian</hi> besieged <hi>Hierusalem,</hi> they shall find not only their <hi>Sins</hi> but <hi>Destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> proceeded from <hi>Hypocrisy;</hi> w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> doth wholly rob the <hi>Prince</hi> of that <hi>benefit</hi> might be made of <hi>Religion,</hi> by converting it into a meer out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side and deceaveable <hi>godlinesse,</hi> far more destructive to <hi>Government</hi> than <hi>Atheisme</hi> it self;<note place="margin">Hypocrisy more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive to Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then Atheisme.</note> Hiding under the <hi>cloake of Piety</hi> such <hi>wicked designes</hi> as open <hi>profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> was never found <hi>to bring about.</hi> Nor doth <hi>Reason</hi> or
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:113531:91"/>
                  <hi>experience</hi> afford better meanes to devest this maske, than by resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> to their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Splendor, And rendring them onely the <hi>markes of confidence</hi> and <hi>wayes to Preferments:</hi> the sense of <hi>Honour</hi> having been found alone more conducing to <hi>Fidelity,</hi> than the bare formes of an over precise Zeal in the company of <hi>Covetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> with which at this day more are thought to converse than suites with the honour of their <hi>Profession</hi> or safety of the <hi>State,</hi> to whom I recommend a timely <hi>reformation</hi> of these pretending <hi>Reformers</hi> of all but <hi>themselves.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies weakly handled, prejudice the Truth.</note>50. If <hi>Lucian</hi> found cause to upbraid the ordinary <hi>Scribes</hi> in his dayes, for owning more <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> to their <hi>Gods</hi> in their <hi>supercilious aspect,</hi> and spurious <hi>censures</hi> of others, than they were really masters of themselves: what may we judge of
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:113531:91"/> the no lesse <hi>Hypocriticall</hi> than <hi>Theatricall</hi> over-actings in ours▪ Where it is ordinary with Men to bear the impresse in their <hi>Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads</hi> and <hi>looks</hi> (like <hi>Mountebanks Bils</hi>) of <hi>more Sanctity,</hi> than the most exact Observer can note in their <hi>Lives</hi> or <hi>Commerce.</hi> Who fill those roomes <hi>Swearing</hi> and <hi>Prophanenesse</hi> was wont to take up in <hi>Tavernes</hi> and <hi>Playes,</hi> with more Blasphemous and uncharitable <hi>Censures</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precations</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> against any Judgment looking a squint up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theirs, though in things meerly <hi>Philosophicall,</hi> &amp; undetermined. Nor are their <hi>Books</hi> free from the <hi>leaven</hi> of <hi>Hypocrisy</hi> and <hi>Malice,</hi> especially if not able to answer the <hi>Spirit of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> he they oppose is <hi>armed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> nor the people willing upon their bare warrant to stone the contrary party, for then, like painted <hi>Iezabel,</hi> the lively image of an <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> they Proclaime him a <hi>Blasphemer</hi> against <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King.</hi> Forgetting, that
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:113531:92"/> though a State may be <hi>indamaged</hi> through the <hi>discovery</hi> of an <hi>Errour, God</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> are not <hi>gratifi'd</hi> in the <hi>persecution</hi> of <hi>Truth.</hi> Yet these <hi>Anti-Veritarians</hi> are such professed Antagonists to all the most proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble new Ideas in <hi>Phylosophy</hi> or <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> not hitherto scru'd up to the <hi>highest pitch;</hi> and in the mean time advancers of <hi>Enthusiasmes</hi> in <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Known</hi> through the mercy and sufferings of <hi>Christ</hi> to be long since sufficiently revealed; That with the <hi>Red Dragon in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,</hi> they seek to <hi>destroy</hi> both <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent▪</hi> and <hi>Child:</hi> Of which failing they <hi>vomit</hi> out <hi>a floud</hi> of insignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant words and reproaches against them, to the discouragement and Obstructing all future indeavours. <hi>Wisdome, like water in a well, not exceeding an ordinary height, till pumped or allured</hi> by <hi>Emulation</hi> or <hi>Honour.</hi> Nor is there a more proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble way to stop the mouthes of these railing <hi>Shimea's</hi> that <hi>curse</hi> and
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:113531:92"/>
                  <hi>cast dirt</hi> upon those <hi>Davids</hi> which labour to quell Ignorance, the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumcised Philistine</hi> of the world, than by appointing all <hi>Bookes of Controversies</hi> to be garbled, and if found not strong enough for their <hi>Adversary,</hi> to restraine them: since <hi>silence</hi> cannot prejudice <hi>Truth</hi> comparably to an over <hi>weake de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</hi> Manifest in <hi>Religion,</hi> and if maturely considered as <hi>palpable</hi> in <hi>Philosophy.</hi> Yet these bold <hi>atta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of wits</hi> do at first gain such <hi>credit</hi> with <hi>ordinary Readers,</hi> upon a presumption they durst not assault these <hi>excellent Spirits</hi> but in an assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of <hi>greater Illuminations</hi> of their own; that they buy their <hi>Books</hi> through which <hi>Ignorance</hi> becomes incouraged and <hi>Knowledge</hi> depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, by a discovery of small faults and perverting the sense of more excellent things. And thus <hi>Fooles</hi> fall into esteem for noting the <hi>ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mishes</hi> in <hi>wise men,</hi> and <hi>they</hi> accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>simple,</hi> for wanting that <hi>abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:113531:93"/> perfection</hi> no waies attainable in this world. The <hi>Students of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> in our days lying under the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy fate the <hi>Mathematicians</hi> did of old, in being thought <hi>Conjurers</hi> and <hi>Atheists;</hi> an indictment I doubt not but the more <hi>refined Judgement,</hi> if not of this Age, of the next, will acquit the one of, as cleer, as it hath the other. Wherefore in case of such purblinded <hi>Censurers,</hi> make them rather the objects of <hi>Scorne</hi> than <hi>Anger</hi> or <hi>Reproofe.</hi> Such <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping natures</hi> resembling <hi>Dogges,</hi> more incouraged and better grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd by the sharpest <hi>answer,</hi> than none at all: upon which they commonly give over, or meet with a fouler blow from a stander-by, and one ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thought of, than you may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently give in your own Cause.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Interest</hi> never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furnished of faire <hi>Pretences,</hi> for subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science.</hi>
                  </note>51. All things quadrating with <hi>Interest</hi> or <hi>Affection,</hi> though in their own Natures <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>unjust,</hi> do labour
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:113531:93"/> to be furnished with such <hi>faire pretences,</hi> as may palliate the <hi>throwes</hi> of <hi>Conscience:</hi> which through use becomes able with the <hi>Stomack</hi> to convert <hi>Poyson</hi> into <hi>Nourishment,</hi> and the most <hi>enormous Sins</hi> and <hi>Cruelties</hi> into <hi>comelinesse</hi> and <hi>zeal.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
               <p>52. No <hi>security</hi> can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or taken either <hi>single</hi> or <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocall</hi> between the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>people,</hi> but <hi>an Oath;</hi> held,<note place="margin">Oathes <hi>becames</hi> Trappes <hi>of the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, where</hi> Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thron'd.</note> in all <hi>Professions, sacred,</hi> and its breach of dreadfull consequence, Till the <hi>Pope,</hi> arrogating the abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute power of <hi>Christ's high Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour upon earth,</hi> did dispence (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of <hi>Equity, Justice</hi> and <hi>necessity</hi>) with the <hi>breach of</hi> all <hi>Lawes,</hi> both <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Divine,</hi> (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst which <hi>Perjury</hi> is Inclusive) and so from an undeniable Infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, <hi>Religion</hi> it self; superscribed by our blessed <hi>Saviour</hi> within this narrow Circuit of <hi>Love to God and
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:113531:94"/> our Neighbour,</hi> on every side invaded through <hi>this high violation of Faith, no lesse destructive to the Conscienci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than Impotent; and only advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to Princes and Subjects liquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish after Profit and Soveraignty:</hi> who, by reason of a vaster power are able to perpetrate the greater mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, and so most likely to <hi>be ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at</hi> by God in his first Instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>this most sacred bond,</hi> in which <hi>his own name</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> is made the <hi>pledge:</hi> And Therefore his patient passing the <hi>breach</hi> of it by in this world raiseth no lesse <hi>confidence</hi> in the <hi>Atheist</hi> that he shall never be-punished, than <hi>assurance</hi> in the <hi>Godly</hi> his <hi>Reward</hi> is not to be expected upon <hi>Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Netherlands</hi> after their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt,</hi> framed <hi>an Oath for the whole League,</hi> wherein all those formerly taken to the King <hi>of Spaine</hi> were without exception or any manner of qualification Abjured: by which I could understand no lesse when I
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:113531:94"/> read it, but that they <hi>called God himself to attest,</hi> that <hi>his name was become of no validity.</hi> Which to speake plaine <hi>English,</hi> was as much as <hi>to forsweare all opinion of Religion or sanctity in swearing.</hi> I do not think my Judgement of an extent large enough to span the height of such an <hi>Impiety</hi> as a <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> or <hi>Regall Perjury</hi> extends to, No more than the temporall <hi>mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe</hi> it may bring to a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> by giving Subjects an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to think the articles of <hi>Faith,</hi> virtually inclusive in an <hi>Oath,</hi> are of no more validity, than <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest,</hi> through the mediation of <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> is pleased to afford them. Yet it may imbolden me to believe, that those <hi>learned</hi> amongst the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes</hi> do not with us look upon <hi>Conscience</hi> as <hi>a distinct quality or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Indowment of Man,</hi> but meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>acquired by Custome at</hi> the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>shame</hi> or <hi>Losse,</hi> which upon the working or boyling of the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory,</hi>
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:113531:95"/> is taught to approve <hi>This,</hi> or dislike That, according to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem <hi>the Opinion of the place,</hi> and <hi>company</hi> they most commonly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse with, are pleased to rate it at: <hi>the smallest morsell of flesh taken into the stomack upon a fasting day clog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it more, than a whole armefull of that which is more sinfull doth in a bed.</hi> Nor are they lesse troubled at the <hi>memory</hi> of <hi>losses</hi> and <hi>apprehension</hi> of <hi>Dangers,</hi> than <hi>Offences</hi> against <hi>God;</hi> The which do not seldome produce far <hi>greater agonies</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaires:</hi> The <hi>blood</hi> of <hi>ten Men in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly</hi> being digested with lesse relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctancy, than the <hi>glance of a Rivals eye.</hi> Wherefore we may <hi>Imagine,</hi> they do really believe no such thing, but look upon <hi>Conscience</hi> not only as <hi>a Roome in the Memory,</hi> that stood empty till <hi>the Fall,</hi> but a meer <hi>bubble</hi> in the <hi>Imagination,</hi> which <hi>Feare</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> by the assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of <hi>Use,</hi> can <hi>blow</hi> like a <hi>glasse</hi> in what <hi>fashion</hi> or <hi>bignesse</hi> they
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:113531:95"/> please, shewing there, to the <hi>Life</hi> represented, good or bad according to the <hi>tincture</hi> a former suborned passion may have <hi>dipped</hi> them in: And this (wisely viewed) will be found of no more solid substance, or drawn by no steadier hand than <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome</hi> or <hi>Education,</hi> nor set in a more durable frame than that of <hi>Fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</hi> And from this <hi>undervaluing of Conscience</hi> (the <hi>security</hi> of the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>terrour</hi> of the <hi>wicked,</hi>) the <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity of Oathes</hi> is lost, or converted into <hi>trappes</hi> to catch the <hi>Innocent</hi> and <hi>unadvised.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="section">
               <p>53. <hi>Conscience</hi> is no lesse sway'd through particular <hi>Interest,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Where <hi>Conscience</hi> is sway'd by <hi>Interest,</hi> there is no true judgement of either <hi>Faults</hi> or <hi>Merit.</hi>
                  </note> than the rest of <hi>passions</hi> or <hi>accidents</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to <hi>Memory.</hi> Manifest in our <hi>Henry the eight,</hi> perhaps no more guilty than all Princes else, who at his <hi>Death</hi> looked upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering <hi>Empson</hi> and <hi>Dudly</hi> (In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments of his own and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Oppression</hi>) to the fury of
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:113531:96"/> the people, as a <hi>Sinne</hi> of a deeper tincture, than the number of <hi>Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red persons</hi> his <hi>Remembrance</hi> could not but at that time present him with. From whence we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude our selves in nothing more apt to be abused, than in the calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of <hi>our own Faults</hi> and <hi>Merits:</hi> And so, <hi>much unlikely to give a just estimate of those belong to others.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Difference in <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> a wrong ground for aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of affection.</note>54. <hi>How darest thou (O Man!) Judge another?</hi> carries such an awfull sound in my apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, as I cannot but tremble at the generall boldnesse, One <hi>Profession</hi> takes to condemne ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: so as none lie capable of <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> under an universall consent. This <hi>Church</hi> Anathematizing what the next receives; which cannot but proceed from the more damnable root of <hi>uncharitablenesse;</hi> every where <hi>Condemned</hi> throughout all <hi>Religions</hi> extant. Though <hi>equally culpable</hi> in imposing a restraint up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:113531:96"/> every way to <hi>Heaven,</hi> but what <hi>custome</hi> and <hi>education</hi> hath rendred familiar to themselves; each being really, or in their suborned Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations supposed able to detect <hi>Error</hi> and <hi>Absurdity</hi> in all <hi>divine worship</hi> beside their own. Wherefore this <hi>humor</hi> being <hi>universall,</hi> if not <hi>naturall,</hi> it ought to cut off all <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Feuds,</hi> and mitigate the rigor of <hi>Law,</hi> and severity of every respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive <hi>Prince;</hi> who can onely justifie (and that perhaps rather to his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular conveniency, than the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties universall mercy) the raising a <hi>persecution</hi> upon no higher provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation than <hi>Opinion,</hi> in no mans power to rectifie, but upon a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest <hi>conviction of his Judgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now since it is no prodigy in the <hi>Schooles</hi> for two <hi>Disputants</hi> to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel about one &amp; the same thing, hid from them only through the nice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of <hi>Distinctions,</hi> why may not such <hi>Protestants,</hi> as measure the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Profession</hi> by the ordinary stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:113531:97"/> of the <hi>Court of Rome,</hi> take, not onely a <hi>false</hi> but, an <hi>Uncharitable survay,</hi> and too far to the disadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of that <hi>Church,</hi> which hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed <hi>Christianity</hi> ever since the <hi>Apostles</hi> time, and may look no more as <hi>Canonical</hi> upon all the <hi>Pope</hi> for his <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Profit</hi> maintains, than we take for <hi>legall</hi> every Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that passeth from the <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Counsell-Table?</hi> many <hi>Ceremonies</hi> being admitted for <hi>order, splendor,</hi> and <hi>decency</hi> (which, under correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I may say, cannot be spared in lesse Corporations) that are <hi>not es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentiall</hi> to <hi>Salvation,</hi> and confessed of no more validity, than what they receive from the Inspiration of <hi>power;</hi> wherefore <hi>meerly locall,</hi> and of no larger extent, than <hi>his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse Authority</hi> doth naturally, or is suffered through the Indulgence of <hi>Princes</hi> to reach.<note place="margin">The redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant zeal of the Papists to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pittied &amp; admir'd.</note> Nor doth the redundant <hi>zeal</hi> of our <hi>English Papists</hi> (not to give it a courser Epithete) deserve
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:113531:97"/> lesse pitty than admiration; through which they are so far blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as not to see the <hi>Popes Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy</hi> concerns them no more in point of <hi>Salvation,</hi> than it did the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> heretofore, <hi>whether a Lord spirituall</hi> or <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall should passe the door first.</hi> It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unpossible but such punctilios at the beginning should result from humane institution or connivance of Kings, from whose benevolence or ignorance those <hi>Appellations</hi> and that <hi>Power</hi> reached to the <hi>Bishop of Rome;</hi> &amp; not from <hi>him,</hi> whose <hi>Vicar</hi> he pretends to be: our <hi>Saviour Christ</hi> owning no such <hi>Jurisdiction</hi> or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of Earthly power. It is confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, I should look upon that <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishman</hi> as a <hi>betrayer</hi> of the <hi>honour</hi> of our <hi>Nation,</hi> that denys the <hi>Kings claime</hi> to <hi>France;</hi> because his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors</hi> once had it in Possession. Yet did I own land and a being there, it were a high <hi>folly,</hi> if not <hi>Treason</hi> to maintaine it upon the place: The
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:113531:98"/>
                  <hi>Title</hi> having possibly as justly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to them again, as it was at first assumed by us. Yet such power hath the present <hi>feare</hi> of losing their interest in <hi>future felicity,</hi> that it doth not onely stifle the sense of <hi>Reason</hi> and <hi>Concernment,</hi> but the apprehension, of <hi>Martyrdome</hi> it self, which might altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them, That since the <hi>Bishop of Rome</hi> converseth not here suta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our <hi>Saviour,</hi> who was so far <hi>from disposing</hi> of Earthly <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,</hi> as he refused to divide a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>Inheritance, Interest</hi> may not unpossibly lead him out of the way in other things: For though an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility</hi> should be granted him, in what relates to the <hi>Church,</hi> tis more than the <hi>Cardinalls</hi> themselves will admit, in what is purely <hi>Civill.</hi> It being none of the Articles of our <hi>Creed,</hi> That <hi>Christ</hi> was <hi>an earthly Prince,</hi> or had any other <hi>soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty over Kings,</hi> but as <hi>God over all.</hi> Yet since this misled people recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:113531:98"/> no advantage of their <hi>errors,</hi> as some more hypocriticall <hi>Schisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> may be Imagined to do, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but raise <hi>pitty</hi> in you towards them, and <hi>Charity</hi> to your self, in case Fortune should cast you in any region under the <hi>Popes Jurisdiction:</hi> who owning a <hi>Temporall Power</hi> no lesse then a <hi>Spirituall,</hi> may not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibly punish in more Prudence, then you can suffer. Wherefore lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving behind you all <hi>Obstinacy</hi> and <hi>prejudice,</hi> consider whether the <hi>Sign of the Cross</hi> may not with more pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be admitted, than <hi>Baptisme</hi> whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neglected, or the <hi>bread</hi> in the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> onely taken, rather then that <hi>Seal of our Covenant</hi> quite O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. Yet I desire you to look upon all is said under the notion of <hi>an Advice,</hi> not <hi>a Command.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="section">
               <p>55. I hold in <hi>Charity</hi> no lesse than <hi>Commerce,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploding Atheisme.</note> with <hi>all sorts of people,</hi> that do <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a Divine and universall providence:</hi> But <hi>abominate</hi> those that
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:113531:99"/> have the <hi>Impudence,</hi> no lesse than the <hi>Indiscretion to deny it, openly</hi> in their <hi>words,</hi> or <hi>tacitly</hi> in their <hi>acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> as such cannot but be thought to do, that Destroy others under a pretence of <hi>Sanctity,</hi> meerly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich themselves; who <hi>deny God</hi> no lesse in <hi>his Justice,</hi> than the other in <hi>his Power.</hi> Since without a <hi>Creator,</hi> Man must be the product of a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingency,</hi> together with all things extant, <hi>if not the maker of himself,</hi> or, which is <hi>as prodigious</hi> an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surdity, <hi>Nothing, out of its own strength, must have produced all things.</hi> Nor could so many descend into this <hi>low and damnable error,</hi> were they not led by that common Calculation incident to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>through which</hi> each in its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective gradation, is rendred out of Ignorance <hi>unable,</hi> or out of pride <hi>unwilling,</hi> to find a <hi>sublimer excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency</hi> than his own. The cause, not only that <hi>the virtues,</hi> but <hi>the Gods</hi> themselves were by the <hi>Heathen</hi>
                  <pb n="185" facs="tcp:113531:99"/> represented in <hi>Humane shapes,</hi> and <hi>their inclinations</hi> confined to the same <hi>Sins</hi> and <hi>Passions</hi> mortalls are found subject to. It exceeding the largest extent in Nature to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend a <hi>higher wisdom</hi> than its own, or to assigne it <hi>a more honourable aspect,</hi> or furnish it with <hi>richer In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments,</hi> than her senses and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience <hi>hath adorned Fancy with all.</hi> The <hi>Devill</hi> being painted as <hi>white</hi> amongst the <hi>Negroes,</hi> as he is <hi>black</hi> here. Wherefore <hi>knowledge</hi> being at a <hi>non plus (a thing she doth natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abhorre)</hi> many, because they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not decipher a Reason, <hi>why Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in this world appeares so oft in the favour</hi> (to our seeming) <hi>of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and unjust designes, and so far discourages the good, as to leave them in the hands of their oppressors,</hi> they, like inconsiderate <hi>sea-men,</hi> do cut the <hi>Cable of hope,</hi> and forsaking the <hi>Anchor</hi> of <hi>Providence,</hi> resigne the conduct of all things to <hi>Fortune,</hi> who is yet so <hi>constant</hi> in her <hi>vicissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes</hi>
                  <pb n="186" facs="tcp:113531:100"/> (familiar to <hi>Gamesters</hi>) that in <hi>a small time</hi> she doth not onely take away, but returnes to every man his <hi>Money</hi> again. And if the world hath, for ought we know to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, been till this age ignorant in <hi>the Circulation of the blood,</hi> though <hi>the principall Engine of Life,</hi> and such a necessary one, as every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture moves not without, why should we rob <hi>our selves</hi> of the <hi>Comfort,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> of the <hi>honour</hi> of <hi>Managing</hi> whatsoever happens, though yet ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the <hi>manner</hi> and <hi>reason</hi> of his doing it, which hereafter we shal see revealed: the <hi>age of man</hi> being <hi>too short</hi> to discover every <hi>spoke</hi> in this <hi>wheel,</hi> that may within a span or two be twisting the destruction of those that are now at the <hi>top.</hi> Nor can any man ghesse how an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fares by an outward aspect ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from his Moveables, but must sleep with him &amp; enter his bosome, which <hi>God</hi> doth; and can no doubt by <hi>slacking</hi> of <hi>Grief</hi> in one, and <hi>win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:113531:100"/> up Feares</hi> and <hi>Jealousies</hi> in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, make the world even. It being the <hi>Spring</hi> and intrinsick <hi>part</hi> of the <hi>watch</hi> that the <hi>work-man</hi> lookes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and not the <hi>case,</hi> though it may possibly be <hi>gold,</hi> or some richer Materials, which <hi>the Rabble</hi> do u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sually cast their eyes upon, as <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren do on the Lord Maiors Pageants.</hi> Admiring the <hi>splendor</hi> of <hi>those that ride</hi> in them; who considered in their own nature are but <hi>mean</hi> mens Issue, and thus adorned at the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Cost:</hi> Yet their <hi>externall varnish</hi> doth so obstruct the Organs of Sense, as they do not perceive the <hi>poorness</hi> of the <hi>people that bear them up,</hi> No more than how long they may be <hi>able,</hi> or found <hi>willing</hi> to do it. And if men cannot, by a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reflection upon their own af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, <hi>distinguish</hi> the <hi>operations</hi> of <hi>Providence</hi> from those of <hi>Contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency,</hi> Yet since it is <hi>the most uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall Opinion,</hi> and, for ought e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I could heare objected to the
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:113531:101"/> contrary, the least obstructed from <hi>Reason</hi> or <hi>Consent, That every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture holds its Production,</hi> no lesse than preservation, at the will of an <hi>Omnipotency,</hi> by us stiled <hi>God;</hi> Though the <hi>wayes how he operates be beyond our fathome and past fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out,</hi> why should not <hi>credulity</hi> rest at the <hi>brinck</hi> of this <hi>Abysse</hi> (by all acknowledged the <hi>least dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi>) rather than hazard all <hi>hope</hi> of <hi>future beatitude,</hi> in the <hi>uncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Gulfe</hi> of a <hi>retchlesse Atheisme.</hi> There remaining as <hi>litle visible losse</hi> to such as award all <hi>honour</hi> to our <hi>Maker,</hi> as <hi>gain</hi> for those that <hi>deny him</hi> quite. Nor are we bereaved totally of the shadow of <hi>Omniscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> since from a farre lower situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than <hi>Heaven,</hi> we are able at one glance to over-look a <hi>whole City,</hi> And by a single <hi>Trumpet</hi> to Alarū an <hi>Army.</hi> Yet our <hi>senses</hi> are capable to receive no small <hi>augmentation</hi> from the assistance of <hi>Art:</hi> an Infallibile argument that the perfection of
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:113531:101"/> these <hi>qualities</hi> doth not determine in the person of any Creature; but something <hi>paramount</hi> all that hath yet risen within the compass of our experience, it being <hi>unpossible but a Superlative perfection should rest some where.</hi> Nor can we be compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <hi>Judges</hi> of the <hi>motions</hi> of <hi>God</hi> that have nothing to <hi>measure</hi> by, but <hi>Sense,</hi> much too weak to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the <hi>motion of a shadow,</hi> or the growth of a <hi>plant,</hi> till time hath ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered them apparent: wherefore far unable to comprehend the <hi>Lines of Providence,</hi> Imperceptible to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Intelligence</hi> but his who hath the sole disposure of all things. It not being <hi>probable</hi> man should comprehend the <hi>out-goings</hi> of <hi>God</hi> whilest he is not able to give any <hi>Reason</hi> for <hi>his own.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:113531:102"/>
            <head>Index.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 1.</hi> The Proeme.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 2</hi> TO praecipitate revenge no prudence.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 3</hi> No Enemy so contemptible as to be despis'd.</item>
               <item>To Contend with inferiours brings discredit.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 5</hi> A friend necessary to a Courtier.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 6</hi> To oblige a Prince or State, dangerous.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 7</hi> Self-praise great imprudence.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 8</hi> To jest with Princes not safe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 9</hi> Counsell to be given with Caution.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 10</hi> To laugh at a Mischance, uncharitable.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 11</hi> To upbraid any with naturall defects un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civill, especially with Bastardy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 12</hi> The issue not bearing the markes of their Ancestors, an ill ground of Jealousy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 13</hi> The multiplying of Crosses highest folly, as an immoderate desire of, or care for posterity, and Impertinent Jealousy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 14</hi> Patience and moderation most necessary in humane life.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 15</hi> O Economicks neglected, the Ruine of great Families.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 16</hi> Great wealth sometimes a snare.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 17</hi> No relatiō, besids a Father, to be confided in.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 18</hi> The Tyranny of Custome a restraint to the progresse of knowledge.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 19</hi> The Secrets of State not to be prostrated to the Vulgar.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 20</hi> The tolleratiō of contrary opinions dangerous.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 21</hi> Excesse in any thing a portent of Ruine.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 22</hi> Affectation a sign of shallownesse.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:113531:102"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 23</hi> A sole Academick education renders men Pedantick.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 24</hi> An universall inspection into science most becoming a Gentleman.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 25</hi> Great Libraries more for pomp than use.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 26</hi> Iron of greater use than Gold, and Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture than Learning.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 27</hi> Learning makes men factions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 28</hi> Let not a Cynicall humour make you wave civility.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 29</hi> Moderation and Complyance deliver out of greatest dangers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 30</hi> Advised retraction no levity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 31</hi> To be the stirrop of anothers preferment dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 32</hi> Annuall Magistracies too short for great Reformation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 33</hi> Whose discourse or Countenance betraies their mind, unfit for Embassadors.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 34</hi> Nature indowes no Individuall with all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 35</hi> Ministers of state ought sometimes to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their sense ambiguous.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 46</hi> Good cloathes commend a Traveller.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 37</hi> Princes need wise Counsells.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 38</hi> Uxorious Princes of dangerous Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to a State.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 39</hi> The Alliance of the Austrian family most succesfull to England.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 40</hi> Hope luls industry asleep, and is often the decay to nature.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:113531:103"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 41</hi> Plantations most happy at their first plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, because lesse numerous.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 42</hi> Most wars occasioned by the Jealousies of small Royallets.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 43</hi> The Spaniards waving Asia in Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Conquer Europe Impolitick &amp; unsuccesful.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 44</hi> The speculative and practicall parts of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks require different tempers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 45</hi> Bloody Princes odious and imprudent. To ascend a Throne by much blood unsafe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 46</hi> That Monarchy most durable, that is founded on best Policy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 47</hi> Tyranny not only naturall but necessary.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 48</hi> Honesty and Prudence not inconsistent.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 49</hi> The opinion that good workes merit, very naturall. Hypocrisie more destructive to Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than Atheisme.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 50</hi> Controversies weakly handled, pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udice the Truth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 51</hi> Interest never unfurnished of faire preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for suborning Conscience.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 52</hi> Oathes become Traps for the innocent, where Conscience is unthron'd,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 53</hi> Where Conscience is sway'd by interest, there is no true judgement of either Faults or Merit.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 54</hi> Difference of judgment a wrong ground for alienation of affection. The redundant zeal of the Papists to be pitied.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Part. 55</hi> The Conclusion exploding Atheisme.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>